<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Classes</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>1023</id>
  <revision>
    <id>52221</id>
    <parentid>50577</parentid>
    <timestamp>2024-04-02T15:22:37Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Jekyll Grim Payne</username>
      <id>2175</id>
    </contributor>
    <origin>52221</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2064" sha1="hb0c6hqb8fi9q4wfz2vt4nhrjzc59sr" xml:space="preserve">{{note|For historical reasons, this page only lists classes based on the {{class|Actor}} class — objects that can be spawned in the game's world. In [[ZScript]], however, a lot of classes are not actors. See '''[[ZScript classes]]''' for other classes.}}

Every type of {{Class|Actor|actor}} (enemies, projectiles, item pickups, obstacles, special effects...) in GZDoom is called a class. For the purpose of this article, a class can be thought of as a way of grouping all the properties of an object under a single name. ZDoom defines all the classes needed for each of the supported game, and as long as the needed graphics and sounds are provided they can all be used in any game.

Normally, objects are placed on a map using either the [[Editor number|thing numbers]] in a level editor, or using the [[Spawn numbers|SpawnID]] in an [[ACS]] script. However, each game supported by ZDoom has conflicting thing numbers, so to facilitate spawning objects from other games, the [[Spawn]] and [[SpawnSpot]] ACS commands were created. To place actors from another game directly in the map editor, you can define {{Class|RandomSpawner|spawners}} that will have a non-conflicting editor number and drop the wanted actor.

You can also spawn classes  manually while playing, via the [[Console Commands#summon (actor-class)|Summon console command.]]

Click on one of the links below to get the full list of classes for the specified game.

* [[Hierarchical class list]]
* [[Classes:ZDoom|Common classes]]
* [[Classes:Doom|Doom classes]]
* [[Classes:Heretic|Heretic classes]]
* [[Classes:Hexen|Hexen classes]]
* [[Classes:Strife|Strife classes]]
* [[Classes:Chex Quest|Chex Quest classes]]
* [[Standard editor numbers]] for classes that can be placed in a map editor.

The following classes are [[Skulltag]] specific actors that are currently '''not''' available in ZDoom but may be in the future.
* [[Classes:Skulltag|Skulltag-specific classes]]

[[category:Actors]]

==See also==
{{Categories by game}}
{{Categories by type}}
[[Category:ZScript]]
[[Category:DECORATE]]</text>
    <sha1>hb0c6hqb8fi9q4wfz2vt4nhrjzc59sr</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>