<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>DeathTrap</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>1184</id>
  <revision>
    <id>25463</id>
    <parentid>10295</parentid>
    <timestamp>2010-01-30T17:03:00Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>template</comment>
    <origin>25463</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="6100" sha1="h8omtr5out2wikahbax6nsok1gqtr5j" xml:space="preserve">'''&lt;sup&gt;Death&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;Trap&lt;/sub&gt;''' is a 9 level episode featuring lots of [[ZDoom]] stuff, most notably heavy scripting. It used to be [[User:Destroyer|Destroyer]]'s first project, before it was abandoned.

=Progress=
==Part 1==
* Intro: '''100% - Completed'''
** Part 1: '''100% - Completed'''
*** Mapper: '''Destroyer'''
*** Stage: '''Complete'''
** Part 2: '''100% - Completed'''
*** Mapper: '''Destroyer'''
*** Stage: '''Complete'''
* Map 1 - The Ship: '''35% - Partial'''
** Mapper: '''Destroyer'''
*** Stage: '''Detailing'''
* Map 2 - Surface of Amara: '''35% - Partial'''
** Mapper: '''Destroyer'''
*** Stage: '''Detailing, Layout'''
* Map 3 - Surface of Amara Continued: '''5% - Partial'''
** Mapper: '''dron'''
*** Stage: '''Detailing, Layout'''
* Map 4 - Surface of Amara Boss: '''0% - Never started'''
* Map 5 - Depths of Amara: '''0% - Never started'''
* Map 6 - Depths of Amara Continued: '''0% - Never started'''
* Map 7 - Depths of Amara Boss: '''0% - Never started'''
* Map 8 - Hijacking: '''0% - Unknown'''
** Mapper: '''Bio Hazard'''
*** Stage: '''Unknown'''
* Map 9 - Escape!: '''0% - Unknown'''
** Mapper: '''Bio Hazard'''
*** Stage: '''Unknown'''

==Part 2==
* Intro: '''0%'''
* Map 1 - Into The Installation: '''0%'''
* Map 2 - Ground Level: '''0%'''
* Map 3 - Entrapments: '''0%'''
* Map 4 - Lower Boss: '''0%'''
* Map 5 - Communications: '''0%'''
* Map 6 - Upper Communications: '''0%'''
* Map 7 - War Room: '''0%'''
* Map 8 - Upper Boss: '''0%'''
* Map 9 - Testing Chambers: '''0%'''
==Part 3==
Never planned...

=Storyline= &lt;!-- Storyline was typed as written, may contain errors. --&gt;
==Part 1: The Beginning==
A platoon of four space marines has been sent to destroy a well-known Alien base: Amara, a sub-moon of Phobos. But, the aliens already know about the attack operation. This will make the operation much harder to carry out. But if they did it before, they can do it again, right? You decide.
*'''Demo''' (dead link)
==Part 2: The Trip Home==
After destroying the sub-moon of Phobos, You return to Mars for debriefing. But your pod takes an unexpected turn and you land on Deimos, mars' second moon. You notice that you're not alone. The old alien installations are back online and working. Time to finish the job and exterminate them once and for all.
==Part 3: Attack on Mars==
After getting stuck on Deimos, you work your way through the old installations, ridding them of hellspawn. You also find out the military has been working on a secret project: the PTD or Personal Teleportation Device, which is designed to open a temporary gateway between two locations. You find a stable working version of the PTD and use it to teleport to a Gate Station on Mars. There, you find out they're working on a global version which allows the user to teleport to anywhere on the current planet, and they they're going to test it the following night! You try to stop them, but they don't listen and initiate the test anyway. They open the gate, and you watch as hellspawn begin teleporting in from everywhere. Not surprised, you grab the nearest weapon, a shotgun, and make your way through the base to try to find a more powerful weapon to get through the hoards of monsters to the PTD to disable it and stop the invasion. Good luck, you're going to need it!
=Progress Log=
==Monday, November 27, 2006==
*Wow... I remember this thing.. Well, unfortunately, as much as I hate to admit this, the project is now considered abandoned. You can contact me through my email if you would like the WIP files for any reason, including the scripted marine control system that makes a debut in the Surface of Amara 1 map. --[[User:Destroyer|Destroyer]]

==Thursday, March 31, 2005==
*dron is now a guest mapper, he is currently working on Map 3
*Progress is being made, Maps 1 and 2 are slowly but surely being finished. It'll still be a while before I can say anything certain but this project is anything but dead right now, you can find me on IRC in irc.oftc.net #DeathTrap or {{forum|on the forums|root=memberlist|mode=viewprofile|u=32}} if you would like to contribute something, every bit helps.
*'''&lt;sup&gt;[GL]&lt;/sup&gt;''' This wad has been suspended, the regular ZDoom version will continue to be worked on though, once it's finished past a certain point, I'll continue updating the GL version but I figure it'd be better to get the main stuff finished first before moving on to smaller things...
==Sunday, December 19, 2004==
*'''Demo Version!''' (dead link removed)
*I'm extending MAP01, it's too small and too short as it is.
==Wednesday, October 13, 2004==
*Forgot to mention, there are now 2 versions of '''&lt;sup&gt;Death&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;Trap&lt;/sub&gt;''' in progress, a version for ZDoom and one for ZDoomGL which uses ZDGL features like shaders and dynamic lighting. Any updates for the ZDGL version only will be marked '''&lt;sup&gt;[GL]&lt;/sup&gt;''' and updates for the ZDoom version only will be marked '''&lt;sup&gt;[ZD]&lt;/sup&gt;'''. The levels will mostly stay the same though, so the progress above will still apply for both versions.
*'''&lt;sup&gt;[GL]&lt;/sup&gt;''' Started removing sector-based lighting and replacing it with ZDoomGL's dynamic lights, which look better.
==Thursday, September 02, 2004==
*You mean there's a Part 3!? '''You bet!''' (dead link removed)
==Wednesday, Augest 11, 2004==
*Started Progress Log. Giest has one(sort of), why not me?
*To confirm, basically everything is just bare rooms right now so it all needs detailing. I'm planning to send the wad to Bio Hazard if he wants to do the detail since he's great at that. He also  wants to create maps 8 and 9 so I'll let him handle those.
*Updated the status of MAP02. It's not that it's huge, just that I work slow.
*I was thinking about adding shaders for ZDoomGL, but some parts don't look good in GL so I'd have to go back and correct those parts if I want it to be ZDGL Compatible... I'll get around to it. Eventually.
**Update: I just ran through the levels with ZDoomGL and it seems to be fine, no errors that I could see.
*Added Title and Credits screen and music.
'''- End of Log -'''
[[category:Abandoned ZDoom Projects]]</text>
    <sha1>h8omtr5out2wikahbax6nsok1gqtr5j</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>