<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>ZDoom Launcher (dead)</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>1196</id>
  <revision>
    <id>32191</id>
    <parentid>32189</parentid>
    <timestamp>2012-03-22T12:40:11Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>moved [[ZDoom Launcher]] to [[ZDoom Launcher (dead)]]: Moved to let surviving software take the name</comment>
    <origin>32191</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1919" sha1="kpig8ziylmpcfehk3y1z9gf669llnu4" xml:space="preserve">http://members.cox.net/carpenoctre/launchers/zdlaunch/

"ZDoom Launcher is a launcher program for the DOOM Source Code port, 
ZDoom.  The purpose of this launcher is set the command-line options 
for ZDoom by simply clicking what you want and then launching the 
game, instead of typing commands over and over again or making 
multiple batch files or shortcuts to automate the process."

This one has a lot more options than ZDoomer, but ZDoomer worked, and this didn't.
Your mileage will hopefully vary from mine.
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Many ZDoom players post messages in the forum, like:

&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;ZDoomLauncher does not work for multiplayer games. What can I do?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;

Please, note that ZDoom Launcher is a good application to launch singleplayer games,
both the 2.6 and the 2.6a versions, but is broken for multiplayer games.

See these links about what Jeffrey Cuenco, himself, has to say about this:&lt;br&gt;
http://members.boardhost.com/ZDLaunch/msg/142.html&lt;br&gt;
http://members.boardhost.com/ZDLaunch/msg/179.top&lt;br&gt;
http://members.boardhost.com/ZDLaunch/msg/205.top&lt;br&gt;

The end result is this, for multiplayer games, you should use one of the other frontends.

------

NOTE FROM AUTHOR:

My apologies for the dead link and the 2-3 years of silence.... my server at home crashed 
back in 2005 and I never got around to putting it back up; an archive of the website has 
been posted on my ISP's webspace.  In addition, time has been the hardest asset to come by
with regards to updating the launcher, and as a result, though I may release updates from
time to time if I find time to work on it, I will also release the source code so that
others may be able to improve on it and update its feature base to the current ZDoom releases.

-Jeff

P.S. - I will post a news update on the launcher website (which I am currently updating) 
regarding the source code release as soon as I clean things out of it.
[[Category:Dead software]]</text>
    <sha1>kpig8ziylmpcfehk3y1z9gf669llnu4</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>