<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Surge 3</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>1314</id>
  <revision>
    <id>26338</id>
    <parentid>5436</parentid>
    <timestamp>2010-03-28T13:07:31Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>recat</comment>
    <origin>26338</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1876" sha1="ka38k5pr84g06va945llp7tk95ry3t9" xml:space="preserve">Surge is back.  Only this time, it's different...

Remember Surge? It started out as a tribute to Overload: 32 tiny, symmetrical DM maps intended for intense and frantic one-on-one fragfests.  Surge 2 was basically just more of the same, only with a tech and base theme instead of the original's gothic one, and somewhat more detail than before.

Well, all that's been thrown out of the window for the third in the series.

There'll be no more of those symmetrical, tiny or boring looking levels: Surge 3 is all about non-symmetrical, large (4+ players) and great looking maps, with plenty of Skulltag / ZDoom features thrown in to add even more spice to the mix.

Many of the maps are souped up versions of Surge 1 and 2 levels, heavily expanded (in some instances several maps have been combined together) and improved.  A few maps are improved versions or remakes of other previously released maps by NiGHTMARE, such as Morbid DM 1 and 2.  Other levels will be brand new, never-before-seen creations.

The Skulltag / ZDoom features mentioned above include the introduction of an entire arsenal of new weapon.  Currently implemented weapons number over a dozen, and they include a revolver, rifle, machine gun, two flamethrowers, a mine launcher, a dual plasma gun and the UBAW 25,000 - the illegal, budget considerate answer to the BFG 9,000.

Surge 3's levels are being desinged to reflect locations mentioned but never visited in the storylines for projects such as Wrath and Paradox.  Currently created/planned maps include:

-  The admin section of UAC's Mars Headquarters&lt;br&gt;
-  An Interplanetary Mining Corporation (IPMC) outpost&lt;br&gt;
-  A heavily damaged area of a spacestation in orbit of Jupiter&lt;br&gt;
-  The ruins of London, England&lt;br&gt;
-  A strange, deserted hellish outpost in Earth's Antarctic&lt;br&gt;
-  A lunar penal colony&lt;br&gt;
[[category:Abandoned ZDoom Projects]]</text>
    <sha1>ka38k5pr84g06va945llp7tk95ry3t9</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>