<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>ZDoom For Dummies</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>1326</id>
  <revision>
    <id>50791</id>
    <parentid>37218</parentid>
    <timestamp>2023-10-13T11:09:47Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Jekyll Grim Payne</username>
      <id>2175</id>
    </contributor>
    <origin>50791</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1626" sha1="ilaxdk3jysgl2z1zsmfadftd6y1bm7a" xml:space="preserve">[[ZDoom]] is, essentially, an advanced source port for Doom. However, it doesn't just support Doom/Doom II... it also has support for [[TNT: Evilution]], [[The Plutonia Experiment]], [[Freedoom]], [[Blasphemer]], [[Hexen]]/[[Deathkings of the Dark Citadel]], [[Heretic]], [[Strife]], [[Hacx]], [[Chex Quest]]/[[Chex Quest 3]], [[Harmony]], and [[Action Doom 2: Urban Brawl]].

ZDoom's purpose is to allow Doom mappers to be more creative with their work, using scripting. You can also add elements of detail to your levels, such as slopes, mirrors, 3-D floors, colored lighting, deep-water, breakable glass, level scripting through [[ACS]], advanced monsters, and more.

ZDoom also has the ability to use free mouse-look.  Other various options in the options menu allow for toggling the ability to jump, crouch, falling damage, allowing the [[silent BFG trick]], crosshairs, and much more.

ZDoom supports the ability to use any graphics lumps in a wad as a texture or flat.  You're also able to make your own custom enemies via [[ZScript]] ([[DECORATE]] and [[DeHackEd]] are supported).You are even able to make custom weapons (also without DeHackEd).  Furthermore, ZDoom has full DeHackEd support, so you can customize already existing weapons.

Also supported is [[ACS]], an advanced script lump usable in levels as well as with actors. Other important lumps include [[SBARINFO]], a HUD script, [[MAPINFO]], a lump for map names, Hexen-style hubs, and other map settings, and others listed [[special lumps|here.]]

For more on how ZDoom's features work, check out one of the [[WADs created for ZDoom]]

[[Category:Guides]]</text>
    <sha1>ilaxdk3jysgl2z1zsmfadftd6y1bm7a</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>