<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Dreamscape</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>1633</id>
  <revision>
    <id>10508</id>
    <timestamp>2007-01-16T22:55:50Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>MasterOFDeath</username>
      <id>98</id>
    </contributor>
    <origin>10508</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2364" sha1="jfupkbucc5bxlnnqzcne10jjk764jph" xml:space="preserve">Dreamscape is a full 3 episode level conversion by MasterOFDeath. It features some voice acting, heavy scripting, weather effects such as rain and fog, new weapons, and all kinds of cool stuff. There are 9 levels per episode, and not all of those levels take place in the city... 

Anyways the story. 

You are a marine who recently got to go home. Yes, after years of long, hard fighting, you get to go home. You had served your time, you had fought long and hard for years. And you finally get to go home. Or so you thought. 

Turns out a large demon war in your hometown started 3 months ago, and the fighting continues, with the marines losing. Luckily, you live near the southern outskirts of town, and most of the fighting is in the northern side of town, so nothing to do but sit back and listen to the sounds of war that you were once a part of. Normally, it doesn't bother you, but it starts to bring back haunting memories. 

Then, one day, only a couple of weeks after you get to go back home, you skills in combat are needed once again. You receive and email telling you that you need to report to military substation A-2. So, you head outside and walk across the street to the intercity teleport system, which due to war, has been abandoned, so you get a free ride. You go in, only to find out you could only make it to substation A-1, which is currently under fire. Thank god you brought your pistol. You decide to stay there for a while, when something happens. A portal appears out of nowhere in front of you one day. You think its just another prank from one of the new recruits abusing their access to the hologram machine, until you notice, it's not a hologram. You enter the portal. 

Suddenly, you get jerked into it through what almost resembles one of the experimental time slipgates, only to emerge somewhere else... It's not the city, its not Hell, its not anywhere like you have ever seen before... 

In Dreamscape, most of the levels are in the city, but there are times you must enter that alternate dimension... and you thought Cyb's Void was trippy... ;) 

Status - DEAD
''This project died a VERY long time ago. I forgot I had even concieved this project. :P However, I may plan a future project using the same name at some point because I like the name, so this page may be "ressurected". :P''

[[category:Abandoned ZDoom Projects]]</text>
    <sha1>jfupkbucc5bxlnnqzcne10jjk764jph</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>