<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Player sounds</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>1638</id>
  <revision>
    <id>42827</id>
    <parentid>42526</parentid>
    <timestamp>2016-07-03T13:46:33Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>Gez moved page [[Player Sounds]] to [[Player sounds]]: stylistic consistency</comment>
    <origin>42827</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="3800" sha1="tuirn47su4qvgt6g80233z9ih6fo3ke" xml:space="preserve">ZDoom uses special sound names to define the sounds a player makes when performing certain actions. Here is a list of all player sounds.


*&lt;tt&gt;*death&lt;/tt&gt;
::This is the normal death sound for a player. It is played when either none of the conditions for the other death sounds apply or if the sound which is to be played does not exist.

*&lt;tt&gt;*xdeath&lt;/tt&gt;
::This is the extreme death sound. It is played when the player's health upon death is -100 or lower. If this sound does not exist, *gibbed will be played if present and *death if not.

*&lt;tt&gt;*wimpydeath&lt;/tt&gt;
::This sound is played if the action that causes the player's death inflicts less than 10 points of damage. If this sound does not exist, *death is played instead.

*&lt;tt&gt;*crazydeath&lt;/tt&gt;
::This is played if the player's health upon death is between -50 and -100. If this sound does not exist, *xdeath or a replacement is played instead.

*&lt;tt&gt;*burndeath&lt;/tt&gt;
::This is played when the player dies by fire.

*&lt;tt&gt;*gibbed&lt;/tt&gt;
::This is played when a player object calls A_XScream or as a replacement for *xdeath.

*&lt;tt&gt;*splat&lt;/tt&gt;
::This is played when a player dies from [[falling damage]]. If not present the normal death sound logic applies.

*&lt;tt&gt;*pain100&lt;/tt&gt;
*&lt;tt&gt;*pain75&lt;/tt&gt;
*&lt;tt&gt;*pain50&lt;/tt&gt;
*&lt;tt&gt;*pain25&lt;/tt&gt;
::These are the pain sounds which are only played when a player object calls A_Pain. The sound selected depends on the health of the player (*pain25 for less than 25 health and so on.)

*&lt;tt&gt;*grunt&lt;/tt&gt;
::This is played either when the player slides into a wall on an icy floor or lands after falling too far down.

*&lt;tt&gt;*land&lt;/tt&gt;
::This is played when a player lands on a solid floor or thing with a minimum amount of falling speed.

*&lt;tt&gt;*falling&lt;/tt&gt;
::This is played (in the air) as a player is falling down too far. Logically this only makes sense if falling damage is on.

*&lt;tt&gt;*jump&lt;/tt&gt;
::This is played when the player jumps. By default this sound is set to non-existant sounds in all games.

*&lt;tt&gt;*fist&lt;/tt&gt;
::This is the attack sound for Doom's fist. By default it is only defined for the Doom player so if you want to use it in other games you have to define it yourself.

*&lt;tt&gt;*fistgrunt&lt;/tt&gt;
::This is the attack sound for the Hexen Fighter's fist's third punch. By default it is only defined for the Hexen Fighter so if you want to use it in other games you have to define it yourself.

*&lt;tt&gt;*usefail&lt;/tt&gt;
::This is played when the player tries to use a wall that cannot be used.

*&lt;tt&gt;*evillaugh&lt;/tt&gt;
::This is played when the player unmorphs himself using the Tome of Power.  In Heretic it is also used when the player uses the Chaos Device.

*&lt;tt&gt;*weaponlaugh&lt;/tt&gt;
::This is played in Heretic when the player picks up one of the game's weapons.

*&lt;tt&gt;*puzzfail&lt;/tt&gt;
::This is played when the player either tries to use a puzzle item in the wrong place or tries to use a line that requires a puzzle item without that item.

*&lt;tt&gt;*poison&lt;/tt&gt;
::This is played when the player is being poisoned by the poison cloud which is spawned by the Flechette and Hexen's poison shroom.

*&lt;tt&gt;*dive&lt;/tt&gt;
::This is played when the player's head is submerged.

*&lt;tt&gt;*surface&lt;/tt&gt;
::This is played when the player's head moves above water.

*&lt;tt&gt;*gasp&lt;/tt&gt;
::Similar to *surface, but only plays if the player was drowning then surfaces.

*&lt;tt&gt;*taunt&lt;/tt&gt; 
::This is played when the player presses their 'taunt' key. (Only available in [[Skulltag]])

*&lt;tt&gt;*regenerate&lt;/tt&gt; 
::This is played each time health increases due to the effect of the {{Class|PowerRegeneration|regeneration}} powerup.

*&lt;tt&gt;*drainhealth&lt;/tt&gt;
::This is played each time health is gained due to the effect of the {{Class|PowerDrain|drain}} powerup.

==See also==
*[[Predefined sounds]]
*[[SNDINFO|SNDINFO lump]]
[[Category:Editing references]]</text>
    <sha1>tuirn47su4qvgt6g80233z9ih6fo3ke</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>