<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>A Mushroom</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>1681</id>
  <revision>
    <id>45417</id>
    <parentid>38190</parentid>
    <timestamp>2017-06-23T10:47:40Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Voros</username>
      <id>2523</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>Add A_Mushroom example</comment>
    <origin>45417</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2384" sha1="rp2hx8s4z10ibv8peq7xza6vdkncmt9" xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:A_Mushroom}}
'''A_Mushroom''' [(string ''spawntype'' [, int ''amount''[, int ''flags''[, float ''vrange''[, float ''hrange'']]]])]

Shoots the specified amount of missiles high into the air with a mushroom cloud effect, performing a radius attack of the calling actor's {{property|DamageType}} as [[damage type]] and both damage and radius of 128.

The parameters are:
* ''spawntype'': type of projectile to throw. Default [[Classes:FatShot|Mancubus fireballs]].
* ''amount'': the number of thrown projectiles. If 0, then the number is determined by the calling actor's '''damage''' property. Default 0.
* ''flags'': the following flags can be combined by using the {{c|{{!}}}} character between the constant names:
** '''MSF_Standard'''&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; uses the normal ZDoom projectile spawning function, in which the vertical velocity is one component of the projectile's speed. This flag is implied if the {{c|flags}} parameter is undefined or zero.
** '''MSF_Classic'''&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; uses the old Doom function in which the vertical velocity is added to the projectile's speed. Since A_Mushroom by default aims its projectiles at very steep angles, the difference between the standard and classic is very noticeable; the older mode results in a more chaotic-looking, asymmetrical explosion, that spreads much higher and farther.
** '''MSF_DontHurt'''&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; the target of the calling actor is considered to be the shooter of the debris projectiles and won't be hurt by the explosion. Use this flag if A_Mushroom is called from a [[projectile]] and should not hurt its shooter.
* ''vrange'': controls how high the projectiles are aimed, the larger the value, the higher they go. Default 4.0.
* ''hrange'': factor by which the speed of the projectiles is multiplied. Default 0.5.

== Example ==
 ACTOR MushRoomBall
 {
   {{Property|Radius}} 3
   {{Property|Height}} 2
   {{Property|Speed}} 15
   {{Property|FastSpeed}} 22
   {{Property|Damage}} 6
   {{Property|Projectile}}
   +{{Flag|RANDOMIZE}}
   {{Property|RenderStyle}} Add
   {{Property|Alpha}} 0.75
   {{Property|SeeSound}} "imp/attack"
   {{Property|DeathSound}} "imp/shotx"
   States
   {
   Spawn:
     BAL1 AB 2 Bright
     Loop
   Death:
     BAL1 CDE 2 Bright A_Mushroom("PlasmaBall", 10, MSF_DontHurt, 8, 0.1)
     Stop
   }
 }

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mushroom}}

[[Category:Decorate Classic attack functions]]</text>
    <sha1>rp2hx8s4z10ibv8peq7xza6vdkncmt9</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>