<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>A AlertMonsters</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>2662</id>
  <revision>
    <id>44133</id>
    <parentid>41079</parentid>
    <timestamp>2017-03-20T11:20:42Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>removing "new" for GZDoom 2.4.0 release</comment>
    <origin>44133</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1994" sha1="3aaw9z4tc69um7nczkrgv0okvxodd8w" xml:space="preserve">{{codepointer|Monster AI}}
'''A_AlertMonsters''' [(float ''maxrange'' [, int ''flags''])]

==Usage==
This can be used on [[weapon]]s, [[projectile]]s and [[monster]]s:
*For monsters it alerts all monsters in hearing range of the current monster's target.
*For projectiles it alerts all monsters in hearing range of the projectile's shooter.
*For weapons it alerts all monsters in hearing range of the player holding the weapon.

This function does nothing on monsters which already have a target.

===Parameters===
* ''maxrange'': The maximum distance from the calling actor at which monsters can still be alerted. Note that this is a simple distance check to the alerter. The "sound" still travels the normal distance. Default is {{c|0}} (unlimited range)
* ''flags'': The following flags can be combined by using the {{!}} character between the constant names:
** '''AMF_TARGETEMITTER''' — Causes alerted monsters to chase the actor which emitted the alert. Note that the alerter must be alive and has the {{Flag|SHOOTABLE}} flag to be chased (this is standard ZDoom behavior, not a fault of the feature).
** '''AMF_TARGETNONPLAYER''' — Allows a monster to alert others to its own target when that target is not a player. Note that AMF_TARGETEMITTER implies that non-players can be targeted, so there is no need to use both at once.
** '''AMF_EMITFROMTARGET''' — Causes the alert to be emitted from the actor that is being warned about, instead of the calling actor. Note that this is inherently pointless when using AMF_TARGETEMITTER.


'''Note:''' The ''maxrange'' will be foiled if {{c|{{CVAR|C|compat_soundtarget}}}} is true, since it makes monsters rely purely on whether sound was heard in the [[sector]] in which they are, rather than what the monster itself heard.

== Examples ==

The {{Class|StrifeZap1}} actor class uses this function to wake up enemies when the projectile explodes.

 Death:
   ZAP1 A 3 [[A_AlertMonsters]]
   ZAP1 BCDEFE 3
   ZAP1 DCB 2
   ZAP1 A 1
   Stop</text>
    <sha1>3aaw9z4tc69um7nczkrgv0okvxodd8w</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>