<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>A Raise</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>2695</id>
  <revision>
    <id>47269</id>
    <parentid>47083</parentid>
    <timestamp>2020-03-18T15:58:23Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>doomwiki link</comment>
    <origin>47269</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1635" sha1="t3h73b2xbq898n1kkpq7n7lupw5vipe" xml:space="preserve">__NOTOC__{{codepointer|Weapon}}:''Note: this function should not be confused with the [[Template:Planned Parenthood|resurrection functions]] which have similar naming.''
{{doomwiki|A_Raise}}

void '''A_Raise''' [(int ''raisespeed'')]

== Usage ==
This function must be called in a [[weapon]]'s Select state sequence. It should not be used anywhere else. It is responsible for raising the weapon and for entering the Ready state sequence when it is done.

Each time the function is called, the weapon moves further up the screen as it approaches the ready position. You can therefore make a weapon raise faster than the default by calling the function more than once within the same tic, or by passing the desired speed directly.


{{Warning|Do not call this function repeatedly in the same state inside another function, [[anonymous functions|anonymous]] or otherwise. All calls to A_Raise are executed fully inside the other function, even if the weapon has reached its ready position, resulting in unwanted side effects.}}

=== Parameters ===
*''raisespeed'': how much the weapon is raised by. Default is 6.

== Examples ==
Here is an example of a basic Select state that makes use of this function to bring the weapon up to the ready position:

 Select:
    SHTG A 1 [[A_Raise]]
    Loop

This will raise the weapon up from the bottom of the screen when it is selected. Once it has reached the ready position, {{c|[[A_Raise]]}} will automatically jump to the Ready state.


This weapon raises into view twice as fast as normal:

 Select:
    FAST A 1 [[A_Raise]](12)
    Loop

== See also ==
* [[A_Lower]]
* [[Creating new weapons]]</text>
    <sha1>t3h73b2xbq898n1kkpq7n7lupw5vipe</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>