<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>A FireCustomMissile</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>2709</id>
  <revision>
    <id>45025</id>
    <parentid>44343</parentid>
    <timestamp>2017-05-02T12:46:28Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Blue Shadow</username>
      <id>2021</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>Remove {{new}}</comment>
    <origin>45025</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2159" sha1="i2dtwulu2rb0fkdb8gid8avxu658w30" xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:A_FireCustomMissile}}
'''A_FireCustomMissile''' (string ''missiletype'' [, angle ''angle'' [, bool ''useammo'' [, float ''spawnofs_horz'' [, int ''spawnheight'' [, int ''flags'' [, angle ''pitch'']]]]]])

{{WarnDeprecated|[[A_FireProjectile]]}}

==Usage==
Fires a projectile from a {{Class|Weapon}} or a {{Class|CustomInventory}}. Optionally you can specify an angle and a spawn offset. 

If used in a weapon, ''useammo'' specifies whether this attack uses ammo or not. This parameter is irrelevant if used in a custom inventory.

The following ''flags'' can optionally be used. Multiple flags can be combined by separating them with the pipe character '|'.
*'''FPF_AIMATANGLE''' — Alternate autoaim behavior, relevant when playing with [[autoaim]]. Autoaiming is based off of the projectile's trajectory instead of the player's aim. If this flag is set, the engine looks at the horizontal line of fire projected for the projectile, independent of the player's aim. If the horizontal line of fire cuts close enough to a valid target (again ignoring vertical aim), that projectile will fire directly towards that target. If this flag is ''not'' set, the engine looks at the player's horizontal aim. If the horizontal line of fire cuts close enough to a valid target (ignoring vertical aim), the resulting projectile will fire with the vertical angle adjusted to aim directly at the target.
*'''FPF_TRANSFERTRANSLATION''' — Transfer Translation. The projectile fired uses the same translation as the actor that fired it. In most cases, this will be the player.
*'''FPF_NOAUTOAIM''' — Disables autoaim for this attack.

''pitch'' becomes relevant with autoaim off. It adjusts the player's vertical aim by the given angle value, like the ''angle'' parameter affects the horizontal aim. A positive value makes it fire the missile higher than the player's aim, a negative value makes it fire lower.

== Examples ==
   Fire:
      TRIF A 5 Bright '''A_FireCustomMissile'''("RifleBullet",0,1,8,8,0)
      TRIF B 5 Bright
      TRIG A 10
      TRIG B 0 [[A_Refire]]
      Goto Ready

[[category:Decorate Weapon attack functions|FireCustomMissile]]</text>
    <sha1>i2dtwulu2rb0fkdb8gid8avxu658w30</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>