<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Creating simple projectiles</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>2722</id>
  <revision>
    <id>21706</id>
    <parentid>15591</parentid>
    <timestamp>2009-05-17T20:51:51Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>msg</comment>
    <origin>21706</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2057" sha1="j8ufxtejh56abe3jbcp7pxdqynslty6" xml:space="preserve">{{WarnDeprecated|the modern [[DECORATE]] format}}

[[The old DECORATE format]] allows for custom projectiles. The format is basically the same as for normal [[Creating simple decorations|decorations]], except you add the keyword "projectile" before its name, and you get to define the following additional properties: 

* DeathSprite - Sprite used when the projectile "dies". 
* DeathFrames - Animation sequence when the projectile "dies". 
* ExplosionRadius - Distance from the projectile's impact that its explosion can be felt. 
* ExplosionDamage - Amount of explosion damage done at the projectile's impact site. This is separate from Damage, and if you don't specify it, it will be the same as ExplosionRadius. 
* DoNotHurtShooter - Explosion damage does not hurt the thing that shot it. 
* DamageType - Defines the type of damage the projectile inflicts.  See [[custom damage types]]. 
* Speed - How fast the projectile moves when you spawn it with the summon cheat. 
* SpawnSound - Sound the projectile makes when it spawns. 
* DeathSound - Sound the projectile makes when it "dies". 
* Damage - This is the damage the projectile does to whatever it directly hits and is actually a random amount based on the value you specify for it here. The damage calculation is 1d8 * ''n''.
* Doombounce - The projectile will bounce several times, slowly losing height before exploding.
* Hereticbounce - The projectile will bounce once and then explode.
* Hexenbounce - The projectile will bounce forever.

An example follows:

    projectile FooShot
    {
        SpawnNum 255
        Sprite PLSS
        Frames "24:AB"
        DeathSprite PLSE
        DeathFrames "ABCDE"
        Radius 13
        Height 8
        Speed 70
        Damage 1
        NoBlockmap
        NoGravity
        ActivatePCross
        ActivateImpact
        NoTeleport
        SpawnSound "weapons/plasmaf"
        DeathSound "weapons/rocklx"
        ExplosionRadius 1024
        ExplosionDamage 16
        DamageType Ice
        DoNotHurtShooter
    }

[[category:Old Decorate format]]</text>
    <sha1>j8ufxtejh56abe3jbcp7pxdqynslty6</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>