<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Creating new monsters or other complex items</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>2726</id>
  <revision>
    <id>52209</id>
    <parentid>52208</parentid>
    <timestamp>2024-04-02T15:06:37Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Jekyll Grim Payne</username>
      <id>2175</id>
    </contributor>
    <origin>52209</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="4341" sha1="js5rvpbkc463qvu1zflzdermtgh6npx" xml:space="preserve">{{OutdatedGuide|Creating new monsters or other complex items (ZScript)}}

[[Monster]]s are just regular actors that call some specific monster AI action functions:

* [[A_Look]]
* [[A_Look2]]
* [[A_Chase]]
* [[A_FastChase]]
* [[A_VileChase]]
* [[A_ExtChase]]
* [[A_Wander]]

It's these functions that make an actor act like a monster but there's a few more things to observe:

* Use the '''Monster''' [[Actor properties|property]]. This sets up all the necessary flags to make an actor act like a monster.
* A monster's height and radius should be set properly. Unlike decorations it is essential that these values are correct because they are used by the collision detection code which also checks whether a monster has been hit by a weapon.
* A monster should have proper definitions for all standard sounds or it might remain silent in certain situations.
* A monster requires a minimum set of [[Actor states|states]]:
:* '''Spawn''': This should define a looping 'idle' sequence. This sequence has to call [[A_Look]] or [[A_Look2]] repeatedly so that the monster can react to players.
:* '''See''': This defines a looping walking sequence. This sequence has to call [[A_Chase]] or one of its variants repeatedly so that the monster can walk around and do things.
:* '''Melee'''/'''Missile''': This defines a near or far attack sequence. At least one of them is needed so that the monster is able to attack players or other monsters
:* '''Death''': This is called when the monster's health goes below zero.
:You can also define one of the optional special death sequences, a '''Pain''' state which makes the monster react to being attacked or the '''Raise''' state which makes it resurrectable by [[Classes:Archvile|Arch-Viles]] or other monsters capable of doing that.


This is an example of a properly defined monster. It is just an exact replica of Doom's [[Classes:ZombieMan|pistol shooting Zombie]]:
 actor &lt;u&gt;ZombieClone&lt;/u&gt; 3004
 {
   {{Property|SpawnID}} 4
   {{Property|Obituary}} "%o was killed by a zombieman."
   {{Property|Health}} 20
   {{Property|Radius}} 20
   {{Property|Height}} 56
   {{Property|Mass}} 100
   {{Property|Speed}} 8
   {{Property|PainChance}} 200
   {{Property|SeeSound}} "grunt/sight"
   {{Property|AttackSound}} "grunt/attack"
   {{Property|PainSound}} "grunt/pain"
   {{Property|DeathSound}} "grunt/death"
   {{Property|ActiveSound}} "grunt/active"
   {{Property|DropItem}} "[[Classes:Clip|Clip]]" 256
   {{Property|Monster}}
   +{{flag|FLOORCLIP}}
   States
   {
   Spawn:
     POSS AB 10 [[A_Look]]
     loop
   See:
     POSS AABBCCDD 4 [[A_Chase]]
     loop
   Missile:
     POSS E 10 [[A_FaceTarget]]
     POSS F 8 [[A_PosAttack]]
     POSS E 8
     goto See
   Pain:
     POSS G 3
     POSS G 3 [[A_Pain]]
     goto See
   Death:
     POSS H 5
     POSS I 5 [[A_Scream]]
     POSS J 5 [[A_NoBlocking]]
     POSS K 5
     POSS L -1
     stop
   XDeath:
     POSS M 5
     POSS N 5 [[A_XScream]]
     POSS O 5 [[A_NoBlocking]]
     POSS PQRST 5
     POSS U -1
     stop
   Raise:
     POSS KJIH 5
     goto See
   }
 }


If you don't need a complete monster but ony a subset of its functions you can do so. For example to create a shootable item that doesn't act as a monster all you have to do is to remove the '''See''' state, the call to [[A_Look]] in the spawn state and replace the '''Monster''' [[Actor properties|property]] with the appropriate [[Actor flags|flags]]. The one flag you need is '''{{flag|SHOOTABLE}}''' but normally you might want to set a few others as well. This is an example of a shootable decoration:
 actor FloorLamp 10247
 {
   {{Property|Health}} 1
   {{Property|Radius}} 16
   {{Property|Height}} 51
   {{Property|DeathSound}} "misc/glass"
   +{{flag|SHOOTABLE}}
   +{{flag|SOLID}}
   +{{flag|NOBLOOD}}
   states
   {
   Spawn:
     HAWA A -1 Bright
     Loop
   Death:
     HAWA B 11 [[A_Scream]]
     HAWA C 9
     HAWA D -1 [[A_Fall]]
     Stop
   }
 }


Other things are possible as well, for example an actor that reacts to seeing a player but instead of waking up and attacking the player it is doing something else, for example playing a sound:
 actor TriggerSound1 10601
 {
   {{Property|SeeSound}} "ts1"
   +{{flag|NOBLOCKMAP}}
   states
   {
   Spawn:
     TNT1 A 2 [[A_Look]]
     Loop
   See:
     TNT1 A 1
     Stop
   }
 }

[[Category:DECORATE guides]]</text>
    <sha1>js5rvpbkc463qvu1zflzdermtgh6npx</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>