<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Shrill!</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>2822</id>
  <revision>
    <id>26336</id>
    <parentid>10076</parentid>
    <timestamp>2010-03-28T13:06:41Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>recat</comment>
    <origin>26336</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2253" sha1="cqjntr3uxk1cp5gmq8wivxtbp17ogrt" xml:space="preserve">==Last updated==
15th June 2006 12:57

==Storyline==
In the far future, Hell is attempting to invade entire universe once and for all. They've been prepping for the 5th, final invasion, for a hell lot of time. Earth is obviously one of their targets. The player takes the role of a tough marine that escaped his scout ship, which spoted a colossal Hell-Force warship heading towards earth. Unfortunately, instead of the escape pod reaching the hero's destination-the EDF (Earth Defense Forces) destination-a base called "Technoir" in the southern pole, the pod is shot down, sending the player down to earth and crashing in an elsewhere location. As the marine bursts out of the shattered pod he quickly notices the invasion on Earth has already begun. This time, it's WAR!

==Info==
*Shrill is an unknown level-number yet mappack that is being developped, so far, solely by Paul (or Nmn). The idea of this mod is making the player battle against tons of enemies in opened environments, using fast weapons, fast monsters, which equals to lots of Action. Nuts series and Action Doom are my primary inspiration points.

*The name Shrill! isn't official and is still pending.

*The score system is implemented. You recieve points per killing monsters (also by monsters killing monsters, although monster infighting isn't present in Shrill), plus there's the Combo meter. Kill lots of enemies quickly to create combo chains to duplicate points you recieve by the combo ammount, recieving big points, big time! Though, if you get hit while building up a combo, the chain is screwed.

*A basic conversation system (done, but it's non-interactive. I don't plan on making talking a part of the gameplay so it's only for cutscenes) to provide the player with info/story bits on levels.

==Status==
All weapons are done, the cutscenery and scoring system is done, the stock monsters (all) have been modified to reward the player upon their deaths. New monsters are still coming as levels are being built.

Map 01- about 60% done

==Authors==
*Nmn - most of stuff (I'm using a bunch of ripped stuff that will be replaced later so no other credits, for now)

==Do you need help with your mod?==
Nope. But thanks for wondering.

[[Category:Abandoned ZDoom Projects]]</text>
    <sha1>cqjntr3uxk1cp5gmq8wivxtbp17ogrt</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>