<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>The Roner</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>2877</id>
  <revision>
    <id>24225</id>
    <parentid>10075</parentid>
    <timestamp>2009-09-22T19:05:07Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>sortkey, recat</comment>
    <origin>24225</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2705" sha1="krowipbi2190eblrd3jh64rjs2rfzf8" xml:space="preserve">=General info:=
The Roner is a mod for [http://grafzahl.drdteam.org Gzdoom]. The game progress is nonlinear (most levels have several exits that take the player to alternate scenarios). The mod uses 100% new resourecs in video and audio. We're trying our strength at making this an IWAD so people don't have to buy/warez Doom2. You could call it a new game.

=Story:=
You awake from your cryogenic sleep in your crashed space vessel. The cryogenic equipment managed to shield your body of any damage you could have inflicted upon the crash, but the ship is a wreck. Because your stasis has been suddenly terminated you're going to suffer from a termporar amnesia. All electronics in idea have been destroyed, meaning you have no idea who you are, where you are, and you won't find it out right now. Emerging from the ship you see a blue sky and green fields. The same second you'd think to yourself it's earth and it's safe, you turn around, to see a gigantic gas giant behind the atmosphere, very likely, orbitting this planet. Whatever this place is, it certainly isn't Earth. In the distance you see a half-ruined city, like a terran colony of some sort. Appears to have been man-made, as the constructs seem familiar through your hazed memory. It's your decision to explore this place, find someone to enlighten you in your poor situation.
Though, you don't know it yet, a humongous journey has just begun. One that will lead to unimaginable 
results, with you in the epicenter.

=Status:=
The Roner is a rather young mod. It has been worked on and off for a year now, with a large pause between Late October 2005, early January 2006. Since then it is being worked on much heavier. Roner was named Rone, then R One, in the past. The Roner is the final name however.
-most items are done
-some enemies are done
-2 maps are began
-HUD and menus are done
The mod uses Gzdoom's features to create pleasing visuals, whereas most of the regular run and gun gameplay remains.

=Team:=
*Paul Zarczynski (NMN) - graphics, level design, coding

=Help?:=
I'm not directly looking for help but I'd greatly appreciate 
*mappers who can stand Gzdoom and hi-res textures. 
*graphic artists who can model, unwrap, animate (one of those, or better, all of them)
*who can make 2d art-textures, skins etc.
Though I demand quality.

=Updates:=

02.08.06
The team has been shortened. Due to Grubber's business I've decided to remove him from the working crew. ellmo being dormant for almost 2 months now also had to be moved from the team.

31.08.06
Due to my team's occupation, I'm left alone on this project. Pity, but I believe I can manage myself fine.

[[Category:Abandoned ZDoom Projects]]
{{DEFAULTSORT:Roner, The}}</text>
    <sha1>krowipbi2190eblrd3jh64rjs2rfzf8</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>