<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Tattered Ages</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>3004</id>
  <revision>
    <id>26339</id>
    <parentid>10074</parentid>
    <timestamp>2010-03-28T13:07:44Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>recat</comment>
    <origin>26339</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="3914" sha1="83wfems1h57efvtv8phkb6as1lu7pfl" xml:space="preserve">== Project Description ==

 They could have told us life would be difficult.
 As if being born different than anyone else wasn't bad enough, the insatiable hunger not painful enough, the understanding that everything you do and are mean nothing. . . 
 
 My name is Kuriopen Leask, I'm a miner on a Phobos mining colony- a prisoner. There are others like me, scared, alone, completely hopeless. . . Because of what we are, our history and the future of our species has been nearly destroyed. I hold out hope that one day something will happen to set it right, but with the recent cave ins and changes in living 'standards' I'm beginning to wonder if 'it' will happen in time to save us.
 There were rumors around the lower mines about a faction of new resistance fighters that were like us, like all Kattah. They long for peace and a return to the way things should be. But the miles that separate me from them. . . The chain link fences and cell doors. . . Can I really believe in such a fairy tale?
 Irana had taught the generations before us never to trust in such foolishness but if I can't believe in something, can I live with nothing at all?
 So many questions are running around in my mind right now, I only hope that the guards don't find this entry. We thought the Order destroyed us all, they still think it. So what if we did find a way to turn it back on them? What if. . .

 Leask, Kuriopen
 2043/12/10
 0532 Phobos Central Time


 Tattered ages is an RPG set in the grim and visceral world of Shades of Grey (by John Enright). It revolves around a young woman who is a slave in a mine on Phobos, held by a cloak and dagger organization called 'the Order of the Earth Purifiers'. Kuriopen (the player character) is a member of the race that gave the Order a reason to exist, for the utter destruction of the Kattah species. . .
 One evening 'Rio' receives a transmission from a faction back on earth that promises a way to 'return to the old ways' Sympathizers that claim to hold the key to her races' survival. . . Their rebirth. As the situation on Phobos continues to deteriorate Rio begins to consider the options, could she get off the planet? Who could she take? Who can she trust? 


== Features ==

 In depth RPG system, with character motivations and agendas that can be furthered or thwarted by the player's actions/reactions. With a throughly involving storyline written by a professional novelist (or an aspiring one anyway :))

Non linear storyline, each puzzle or quest has multiple ways of solving it or achieving the goals set forth. Actions you take will carry on to other parts of the story and will reflect when you go through it. Goals are clearly defined but the methods of achiving them are up to you.

Story driven action; an actual story unfolds while you play, characters come to light, motivations become defined. The more you play through it the more things come to understanding. Including replays with choices not made, learn different sides of the same story every time you play.

Action; intense firefights and tactical maneuvering or stealth and cut throat tactics are a couple of any number of options available to you.

 The entire project (slated to take place in three 'acts') will take the player from Phobos to Earth to Earth (circa 1200 AD) in their quest to end the Order's existence. With several possible outcomes and a multitude of ways to play the story, where will you stand when its over?


If you would like to check this project out sometime please email me at SirTimberWolf at Gmail.com. I am always looking for help, though I prefer to do the maps myself I would love to find some graphic artists and am willing to consider other mappers provided we share the same vision... (Pompous I know but I think you understand.


== Team ==

 Programming: Travis
 Mapping: SirTimberWolf
 
 More information to follow. . .

[[Category:Abandoned ZDoom Projects]]</text>
    <sha1>83wfems1h57efvtv8phkb6as1lu7pfl</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>