<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Forsaken</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>3357</id>
  <revision>
    <id>26766</id>
    <parentid>26644</parentid>
    <timestamp>2010-05-19T06:16:10Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Mortarion</username>
      <id>1699</id>
    </contributor>
    <origin>26766</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="3877" sha1="4tjdz5ewf1o4l4tz3xek5skvmnfgv46" xml:space="preserve">[[file:FSKN_MAINPIC.png|Forsaken's temporary titlescreen|right|thumb|400px]]
{{Wad
| name = Forsaken - Never more
| author = Team Forsaken
| port = GZDoom
| iwad = Doom2
| status = WIP
| link = [http://forsakendoom.webs.com/ Team forsaken]
}}

== Web Release ==

The greatest battle of all time is nigh, and only a select group of Resistance Fighters can save the planet from Armageddon!
[[file:FSKNcombat.png|Combat in Forsaken|right|thumb|300px]]
Yes, this is it, Forsaken is a huge megawad, with 50 pulse-pounding levels spread across several sagas and a whole salvo of unique weapons at your disposal. Prepare to fight with entire squads backing you through the temperate fields of Schoolcadia, Eerie jungles around the Equator and the dry steppes of Umvarrus. Lock and load, then fight off an unyielding legion of warp-borne Umvarri, and organised armies, highly advanced Schoolcadians, and the shadowy inhabitants of the jungles...

Let loose rounds with a wide arsenal of weapons, such as the accurate Pulse Rifle, the lethal MPLAR, or the reliable ASMC Gauss Rifle. Bring your enemies to their knees and hold off your foes just a while longer...

Can your people count on you?

== Overview ==

Forsaken is a 50 map megawad in progress from Team Forsaken. It combines non-linear city exploration with storyline-driven action in multiple episodes of gameplay, referred to as sagas. Each saga contains a new element to the plot of Forsaken, whether it be a new race of enemies, a weapon, or a quest.
The game also makes use of KSSC scripting and decorate to simulate the actions of NPCs.


== Progress and development ==

=== Forsaken 1.0===
The original forsaken can be considered a learning experience, it’s failure was not unexpected by the team (as the original attempt involved 100 maps, and ripped sprites)
[[file:Hellsreachcity.png|Travel by sea, air, land or even rooftops|right|thumb|300px]]
=== Forsaken 2.0 ===
As of 12/12/08. Forsaken began anew. The newest incarnation of Forsaken is a much more polished machine with custom sprites, weapons and most sounds. In fact, the only thing deemed to time consuming to do custom were textures which were sourced from a variety of sources (notably Shadow warrior, Blood and Skulltag)
==== Combat in Forsaken ====
Enemies in forsaken are capable of sophisicated and deadly tactics, such as the schoolcadian serpiex(equiv. sargeant) and his ability to order advances, retreats and firestorms at will, or the Umvarri soldier's acrobatic assault patterns. Aside from race-specific abilities, all races have the ability to swim(and drown), reload weaponry, issue suppressive fire, and use limited numbers of grenades.


== Team members and attributed tasks ==

=== Mapping ===
[[user:Relinquo]]

Sykesc

[[user:Mortarion]]

=== Sounds ===
[[user:Relinquo]]

Sykesc

[[user:Mortarion]]
[[file:WildernessFSKN.png|Time spent exploring can reveal valuble secrets|right|thumb|300px]]

=== Decorate/KSSC ===

[[user:Relinquo]]

Sykesc

[[user:Mortarion]]

=== Sprites ===

[[user:Mortarion]]

== Media releases ==
Only three pieces of media have been released so far - A low-quality video featuring gameplay which can be seen here [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bBILaAXTbu8 on youtube], a poster featuring a high-res picture of an enemy from the game, and a propaganda poster. both posters are considered to be schoolcadian in origin.
The video gives a brief rundown of common foes in forsaken(although they are not named) an shows off several levels early to midway through the game. The video is almost outdated however as several enemies have been re-sprited since the time of filming.
17 new screenshots have been released to the [http://forsakendoom.webs.com/apps/photos/ official site.]
[[file:FSKNrecruitposter.png|Recruitment Poster|left|thumb|60px]]
[[file:Speechposter.png|Schoolcadian propaganda|right|thumb|100px]]</text>
    <sha1>4tjdz5ewf1o4l4tz3xek5skvmnfgv46</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>