<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>TEAMINFO</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>3525</id>
  <revision>
    <id>37490</id>
    <parentid>25527</parentid>
    <timestamp>2013-12-30T23:00:05Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>/* Skulltag properties */</comment>
    <origin>37490</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="3474" sha1="4mqsk4tqjs0ewvxs2mlsmf4oac7z0xg" xml:space="preserve">TEAMINFO allows a player to define custom teams for team deathmatch play mode. There is no limit of teams you can define meaning it's possible for you to define a wide and exciting variety of teams. The team number depends on their order of introduction in the lump -- by default, blue is 0, red is 1, green is two, and so on.

== Syntax ==

 clearteams // Optional
 Team &lt;Name&gt;
 {
         PlayerColor "RR GG BB"
         TextColor "Color"
         &lt;other properties&gt;
 }

== Commands ==

'''ClearTeams''' - Removes all predefined teams. Remember to place this before you define your own teams!

'''Team &lt;name&gt;''' - Start a team definition, to be contained within curly braces.

== Properties ==
All these properties are valid within a team definition.

'''Name''' &lt;string&gt; - The name of your team to be defined, e.g, "Purple".

'''Game''' &lt;keyword&gt; - The game in which the team is defined. Valid values are "Any", "Chex", "Doom", "Heretic", "Hexen", "Raven" and "Strife".

'''PlayerColor''' &lt;color&gt; - In a hexadecimal format, this property defines the color of the player on said team, e.g, "FF 00 00".

'''TextColor''' &lt;color&gt; - The color of the players' name on the scoreboard, e.g, "RED".

'''Logo''' - The name of the logo drawn on the scoreboard. This feature is not supported by [[Skulltag]].

'''AllowCustomPlayerColor''' - If present, this keyword enables players to use their own custom colors, instead of their team color.

== Skulltag properties ==
Skulltag defines additional properties. They are silently ignored in ZDoom, and have no effect. They are, however, naturally supported by Skulltag's successor [[Zandronum]].

'''RailColor''' &lt;color&gt; - In a hexadecimal format, the color of your team's railgun, e.g "FF 00 FF".

'''FlagItem''' &lt;string&gt; - The actor for your team's flag (in capture the flag).

'''SkullItem ''' &lt;string&gt; - The actor for your team's Skull (in skulltag mode).

'''PlayerStartThingNumber''' &lt;number&gt; - The team start thing number.

'''SmallFlagHUDIcon''' &lt;string&gt; - This icon is shown on the screen next to the name of the player who is holding the flag.

'''SmallSkullHUDIcon''' &lt;string&gt; - This icon is shown on the screen next to the name of the player who is holding the skull.

'''LargeFlagHUDIcon''' &lt;string&gt; - The flag icon on the full screen HUD.

'''LargeSkullHUDIcon''' &lt;string&gt; - The skull icon on the full screen HUD.

'''WinnerPic''' &lt;string&gt; - The picture shown to members of the victorious team after a match.

'''LoserPic''' &lt;string&gt; - The picture shown to members of the defeated team after a match.

'''WinnerTheme''' &lt;string&gt; - The music played to members of the victorious team after a match.

'''LoserTheme''' &lt;string&gt; - The music played to members of the defeated team after a match.

== Examples ==

Here are the defined teams in zdoom.pk3.

&lt;pre&gt;ClearTeams

Team "Blue"
{
	PlayerColor "00 00 FF"
	TextColor "Blue"
}

Team "Red"
{
	PlayerColor "FF 00 00"
	TextColor "Red"
}

Team "Green"
{
	PlayerColor "00 FF 00"
	TextColor "Green"
}

Team "Gold"
{
	PlayerColor "FF FF 00"
	TextColor "Gold"
}

Team "Black"
{
	PlayerColor "00 00 00"
	TextColor "Black"
}

Team "White"
{
	PlayerColor "FF FF FF"
	TextColor "White"
}

Team "Orange"
{
	PlayerColor "FF 80 00"
	TextColor "Orange"
}

Team "Purple"
{
	PlayerColor "FF 00 FF"
	TextColor "Purple"
}&lt;/pre&gt;

Here's another example:

 Team "Assassins"
 {
        PlayerColor "FF 10 00"
        TextColor "DarkRed"
        Logo "ASSALOGO"
 }

[[Category:ZDoom special lumps]]</text>
    <sha1>4mqsk4tqjs0ewvxs2mlsmf4oac7z0xg</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>