<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Great of Heka</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>3559</id>
  <revision>
    <id>28476</id>
    <parentid>26347</parentid>
    <timestamp>2010-11-18T18:08:08Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>Removed about 80% of all that stuff, including all links to broken images. (BMP is no longer supported by this wiki.)</comment>
    <origin>28476</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="3113" sha1="5xgsfcswc5vyfwgysq1kwqdfbezz1pn" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:DUNE.png|thumb|400px|The Adventure begins on level 1: Banana Dune]]

==Inspiration==

Many aspects of this game are inspired by mythology.  Heavily from Greek and Egyptian.  The term "Great of Heka" actually comes from the Egyptian goddess Aset, who has ultimate power.  Heka itself is basically this special power that the ancient Egyptians revered.  It is comparable to magic, ki, atman, etc.  A certain force that, unfortunately, is not romanticized in today's culture.  Other than that, a lot of inspiration for this game comes from the two games Hexen and EarthBound.  It capture's Hexen's action and gameplay while having an artistic and creative style of EarthBound.  However, this is not a knock-off of the two games in any way.  It is a stand-alone original.

==Gameplay==
The physique of the mighty Heka Warriors is a little bit different from your standard DOOM marine.  For instance, they only run at half his speed.  It might sound like a drawback, but it is actually a little bit more realistic and easier to control.  One thing you’ll definitely notice is the jump height.  These guys could give Super Mario a run for his money.  They even emit a cute sound-effect when they take off.  The Heka Warriors have a maximum of 256 HP.  Don’t get too excited.  Attacks are a little bit more brutal so they need all that health.  The Heka Warriors also have another gauge of power.  They possess an energy force known as Heka points, hence their title.  Because of their supernatural power, Heka Points automatically recover at a slow rate, and max out and 999.  The Heka points are used to pay for the Heka attacks (each Heka attack is described in more detail later).  It can also be used for magic spells to do miraculous things like recovering health and teleportation.  Unlike the DOOM marine, whose health instantly boosts up when he grabs a medkit, the Heka Warriors’ health slowly build up one point at a time when they use a power-up.  This is called rolling health, and the speed of the rolling health varies with the game’s difficulty setting.  The difficulty level also changes the intricacy of in-game puzzles.  Someone who plays Nightmare-mode is in for real brain-benders that hardly get any easier in the second playthrough.

[[Image:JARS.jpg|176px]]

In the game you find jars that you can fill and refill with speciffic drinks. The drinks include water, which fully recovers health, latte, which fully recovers heka, and bananamilk, which is a full restore. 

=Screenshot Samples=
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:MOUNTAIN.png|Starlit majesty of a serene mountain landscape.
Image:HYPOSTYLE.png|Can you see the sheep way over there?
Image:OBELISKS.png|Hey there little bananasauros!  Wanna come and play?
Image:HALL.png|Rollout the red carpet!
Image:MISTY.png|OOOoooooo... does it ever end?
Image:REFLECTIVEWATER.png|An oasis of cool water.  OH MY GOD the water is reflective!  And what's this?  You can see the bananas sitting '''under''' the water! (You can tell they're not a reflection because they're not upside-down, like the trees)
&lt;/gallery&gt;

[[Category:Abandoned ZDoom Projects]]</text>
    <sha1>5xgsfcswc5vyfwgysq1kwqdfbezz1pn</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>