<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Wrath and Paradox</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>3675</id>
  <revision>
    <id>26341</id>
    <parentid>14246</parentid>
    <timestamp>2010-03-28T13:08:22Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>recat</comment>
    <origin>26341</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2757" sha1="bdo537u7hvbk91xoe2jnjxr69gspnsi" xml:space="preserve">'''Wrath''' and '''Paradox''' are two separate but strongly connected projects, both set around 15 years after the events of Doom &amp; Doom 2.

While Hellspawn still run rampant across most of the Earth, mankind has settled on numerous locations through the solar system, including the moon, Mars, and a huge space station orbiting Jupiter.  For a time the surviving humans had been living in relative peace and harmony, but after only a few years good old fashioned human nature reasserted itself.  Several separate factions have begun attempting, both covertly and overtly, to gain control of the ragged remants of humanity.

Wrath will consist of several mostly independent levels which deal with some of these factions and conflicts.  For example, it's quickly established that the UAC still hasn't given up on the idea of dimensional travel, which they plan to use for their own personal gain.  In one level the player takes on the role of a "volunteer" who the top brass havee sent to Phobos, to try to find the dimensional rift that leads to Deimos.  He's to travel through it and retrieve certain heavily classified and extremely vital data from the lost base's computer network.

Paradox builds on the storylines that were developed during Wrath.  A former branch of the U.S. military, who've long been in control of the Jupiter space station (and thus a significant portion of mankind), receive a distress signal from a much smaller outpost they have out in the Earth/Mars asteroid field.  The player is part of a team sent to investigate, and what they quickly find out is that Hell isn't the only other dimension who're interested in taking over ours...

The current plan is for Wrath to have around 10 levels and Paradox to have about 20.

Both projects will come with a vast array of new weapons, enemies and decorations, and an enormous texture wad is being used (2250+ as of 05/01/04) to bring this universe to life.

Paradox will feature many previously unreleased maps by some extremely famous current and former community members, including Andy Badorek, Rick Clark, Pablo Diccter, Paul Fleschute, David Gevert (aka DaGGeR), Bjorn Hermans, Michael Niggel and Michael Reid (aka prower).  A large portion of Michael N.'s cancelled Twice Risen TC has also made it's way into project. 

See [http://haunt.8m.com/screens.html here] for screenshots from Wrath, Paradox and Surge 3, and [http://wip.paci-fist.org/?a=listwads&amp;wad=44 here] for more screenshots from Wrath.

Current status of the projects:

Wrath: Levels 33%; Scripting 0%; Textures 100% (barring any additions); Weapons 75%; Music 90%

Paradox: Levels 60%; Scripting 5%; Textures 100% (barring any additions); Weapons 75%; Enemies 5%; Music 90%

[[Category:Abandoned ZDoom Projects]]</text>
    <sha1>bdo537u7hvbk91xoe2jnjxr69gspnsi</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>