<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Temple of the Ancients</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>3697</id>
  <revision>
    <id>25813</id>
    <parentid>14838</parentid>
    <timestamp>2010-02-19T00:00:23Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <origin>25813</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1919" sha1="mkq90ijsy4sl5jnpugbka83lurkz8gl" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:TA_Map5b.jpg|thumb|A Pavilion Outside the Temple]]
{{Wad
| name = Temple of the Ancients
| author = Rex Claussen
| iwad = Doom2
| type = m
| status = Released
| link = [http://doomnexus.drdteam.org/TA_Pix.html Official page on Doom Nexus]
}}

==Description==
Temple of the Ancients is a 5-level hub for [[ZDoom]], set in a variety of environments. You start in a command center, but explore medieval and techno-medieval areas as you uncover the secrets of the Temple of the Ancients. (As someone put it: It is a mission with a Hexen-esque quest feel combined with graphics from the Quake games. Each section of the hub takes place in an entirely different world - from starbase, to the Valley of Fire, to Valhalla.) This can be considered a "partial conversion", as it uses almost all-new textures and weapons graphics.

These levels extensively use Q3A textures, and a few Q1 &amp; Q2 textures. They also feature cool new skies, and scripting. ZDooM features include translucency, laser barriers, underwater environments, true elevators, colored lighting, fog, slippery surfaces (ice), quakes, 3D bridges, etc.

The permanent download location is located on the /idgames archive. (See [[Temple_of_the_Ancients#External_Links|External Links]])

[[Image:TA_Map4a.jpg|thumb|Fog in Valhalla]]

==Features==
The hub structure allows the player to move back and forth between maps, and is in keeping with the mission - figure out what the source of the "infestation" is. This requires achieving sub-objectives beyond merely picking up keys.

There are new weapons graphics, but these work just like DooM2 weapons. The weapons have not been modified through DeHacked (and this mod was created before DECORATE allowed the creation of completely new weapons).

[[Image:TA_Map5.jpg|thumb|A Guard Goes Down at the Temple Gates]]

==External Links==
*{{idgames|id=11029}}
*[http://doomnexus.drdteam.org/TA_Pix.html DooM Nexus]</text>
    <sha1>mkq90ijsy4sl5jnpugbka83lurkz8gl</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>