<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>JtRSpeed</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>3719</id>
  <revision>
    <id>25819</id>
    <parentid>25444</parentid>
    <timestamp>2010-02-19T00:08:33Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <origin>25819</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="4181" sha1="hzlpq1k3x9fb3stnc92a43aemk79irt" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Screenshot_Doom_20080508_201216.png|right|thumb|230px|A screenshot of JtRSpeed, showing the multi-rocket launcher and Gangsta Grosse.]]
{{Wad
| name = JtRSpeed
| author = Juan "JacKThERiPPeR"
| status = Abandoned
| link = {{forum|Forum thread|f=19&amp;t=16759}}
}}

== Progress ==

* Monsters: Half-Done (45%~)
* Weapons: Half-Done (45%~)
* Powerups: Almost Done (75%~)
* Gold System: Just bugfixes (95%~)
* Gore: Done (100%)
* Overall: Half-Done (45%~)

== Description ==

JtRSpeed is a tribute to AEons of Death from DBThanathos, which like in his mod, replaces monsters, weapons, powerups and so much by other and more variate ones. However, it differs from AEoD as well, with features like gold system and sellers and so much I can't think of right now.

== Features ==

* New monsters, weapons, etc...
* Gold system and sellers, and maybe also stealing monsters.
* Nash' Gore Mod implemented

== More info ==
[http://forum.zdoom.org/viewtopic.php?f=19&amp;t=16759 This thread is the epicenter of all information about the project.]
[[Category:Abandoned ZDoom Projects]]

== Update Log ==

'''15/05/2008 - Fixed some bugs, found some more (thanks Ichor)'''&lt;br&gt;
* For the CSDesertEagle I just removed the unnecesary frames.
* +WEAPON.DONTBOB for the Sword and Staff. Does fine when you don't want to modify the sprites, or can't.
* Same than above with the Molotov Cocktails.
* Warcraft Fel Orc was finally removed from Cyberdemon Class Spawn, and will never be spawned again.
* Removed the Skull Wizard, moved the Terminator and Mutant Hitler too.
* Fixed the ammo issue with Blood's Sawed-Off.
&lt;br&gt;
More bugs (copy and paste from Ichor's post):&lt;br&gt;
&lt;i&gt;This is what I've seen so far:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
If you buy the life leech from someone, and then use alt-fire to set it down, it takes the weapon from you, but nothing is dropped. However, it works normally if you get the weapon from an item pickup instead.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Also, those anubis warriors shouldn't be nearly so tall, especially if they're imp class.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The fel orc seems a bit too slow for something so tall that runs, the ground attack does practically no damage (if at all), and when he throws the hammer, it spawns far off center to its right.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Is the insanity rifle supposed to use up ammo so quickly?&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The apprentice has no missile attack, even though he swings the hammers like there was one, and the ground attack seems to explode prematurely when they hit a dead body, and sometimes they explode immediately. The hellsmith's ground attack is the same way.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The aoemonk and blood soul are incredibly annoying, but the skull wizard is much too slow and weak to be considered an arch-vile class.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Homer looks like he's always walking sideways, except when spinning around.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The demoness' attacks are much too low.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The flesh wizard's attack sometimes explode immediately, especially with the imp class (xwizard).&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
The lich's tornados only go out a short distance, and do no damage whatsoever. Plus, he doesn't always face the player when he shoots.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Not a bug actually, but I think the pitlord needs some kind of ranged attack.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
When the dark avatar raises his hands to cast the pale colored spell, there's no attack.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
'''12/05/2008 - Found some bugs, thanks DOOMERO.'''&lt;br&gt;
Sprites:&lt;br&gt;
* CSDesertEagle has a badly placed animation, it looks like it's going to fire, but it doesn't.
* A weapon that is a Sword and a Staff has been cut on one of it's sides.
* The molotov cocktail has badly placed sprites when walking.
* The Mancubus Weapon has an animation that looks like cut over (?)
* The Warcraft Fel Orc has some sprites eaten by the floor, even alive or dead.
* Some weapons have antialiasing.
&lt;br&gt;
Monster Placement:&lt;br&gt;
* In the Arch Vile section there's a very weak mage in his attacks and resistances.
* The Terminator (Mancubus section) is too strong. It would be better for a Cyberdemon.
* Mutant Hitler would be better as a Chaingunner (or a Wolfenstein SS in my opinion).
&lt;br&gt;
Attacks:&lt;br&gt;
* The Alt Fire of the Blood Sawed-Off only wastes 1 shell.
* The Vorpal Blade on 100% doesn't attack with the cut animation.</text>
    <sha1>hzlpq1k3x9fb3stnc92a43aemk79irt</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>