<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>MorphActor</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>3754</id>
  <revision>
    <id>53654</id>
    <parentid>48082</parentid>
    <timestamp>2024-11-11T00:21:05Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>SPZ</username>
      <id>2640</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>Added 2nd link</comment>
    <origin>53654</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="3823" sha1="kv2vgwo7qob0ts4dfmbo3o01gsom8re" xml:space="preserve">__NOTOC__int '''MorphActor''' (int ''tid'' [, str ''playerclass'' [, str ''monsterclass'' [, int ''duration'' [, int ''style'' [, str ''morphflash'' [, str ''unmorphflash'']]]]]])

== Usage ==
This function and its complement [[UnMorphActor]] give the ACS coder direct access to the engine's morph subsystem, instead of having to strategically place DECORATE items and suchlike.

=== Parameters ===
*''tid'': The actor(s) to morph. The activator is used if this parameter is zero.
*''playerclass'': Defines what class to morph a player into. 
*''monsterclass'': Defines what class to morph a monster into. 
*''duration'': Defines the duration of the morphing effects. 
*''style'': Defines the behaviour of the morphing effects.
*''morphflash'': Defines the effect flash actor to spawn when the player morphs. If omitted, the game's default teleport fog is used. 
*''unmorphflash'': Defines the effect flash actor to spawn when the player unmorphs. If omitted, the game's default teleport fog is used.

This function does honor the MRF_WHENINVULNERABLE flag when used on a player, provided that player is also the activator of the function.

Except for ''tid'', the parameters are the same special properties defined by the {{Class|MorphProjectile}} class. They are summarised above; for full details and additional notes, please refer to the {{Class|MorphProjectile}} class.

{{note|for versions of [[ACC]] older than 1.58, all optional arguments must be treated as mandatory. Specify 0 for unused integer arguments and "" for unused string arguments.}}

=== Return value ===
The return value is the number of actors successfully morphed. This also means that for TID = 0, it is also a boolean (0 = failed, 1 = succeeded).

== Examples ==
The following example assumes that a {{Class|cyberdemon}} with the {{Flag|DONTMORPH}} [[actor flags|actor flag]] disabled has a [[TID]] of one. The function call turns it into a pitiful little puppy demon, so you can kill him with ease!

Note that the {{Class|Demon}}'s DECORATE code is reproduced from gzdoom.pk3 because the engine currently requires that all morphed monsters must inherit the {{Class|MorphedMonster}} class, and multiple [[Using inheritance|inheritance]] is not supported; at the moment, you cannot arbitrarily morph one kind of monster into another.
 script 1 (void)
 {
     [[MorphActor]](1, "", "MorphDemon", 1048576, 0, "", "");
 }

 actor MorphableCyberDemon : {{Class|Cyberdemon}} replaces Cyberdemon
 {
     -{{Flag|DONTMORPH}} // The cyberdemon has this flag set, by default. The flag needs to be cleared so the monster can morph.
 }
 
 actor MorphDemon : {{Class|MorphedMonster}}
 {
     {{Property|Game}} Doom
     {{Property|Health}} 150
     {{Property|PainChance}} 180
     {{Property|Speed}} 10
     {{Property|Radius}} 30
     {{Property|Height}} 56
     {{Property|Mass}} 400
     {{Property|Monster}}
     +{{Flag|FLOORCLIP}}
     {{Property|SeeSound}} "demon/sight"
     {{Property|AttackSound}} "demon/melee"
     {{Property|PainSound}} "demon/pain"
     {{Property|DeathSound}} "demon/death"
     {{Property|ActiveSound}} "demon/active"
     {{Property|Obituary}} "%o was killed by a dem... cyberd... well, by something anyway"
     States
     {
     Spawn:
         SARG AB 10 [[A_Look]]
         Loop
     See:
         SARG AABBCCDD 2 Fast [[A_Chase]]
         Loop
     Melee:
         SARG EF 8 Fast [[A_FaceTarget]]
         SARG G 8 Fast [[A_SargAttack]]
         Goto See
     Pain:
         SARG H 2 Fast
         SARG H 2 Fast [[A_Pain]]
         Goto See
     Death:
         SARG I 8
         SARG J 8 [[A_Scream]]
         SARG K 4
         SARG L 4 [[A_NoBlocking]]
         SARG M 4
         SARG N -1
         Stop
     Raise:
         SARG N 5
         SARG MLKJI 5
         Goto See
     }
 }

[[category:ACS Actor functions]]</text>
    <sha1>kv2vgwo7qob0ts4dfmbo3o01gsom8re</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>