<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Action Doom</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>3757</id>
  <revision>
    <id>50400</id>
    <parentid>25763</parentid>
    <timestamp>2023-07-07T10:49:53Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Dynamo</username>
      <id>2607</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <origin>50400</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2570" sha1="e1zxv0zkm487dxljycdz4i22lf4dqe8" xml:space="preserve">{{doomwiki}}[[Image:actiondoom1.png|right|thumb|230px|A screenshot of Action Doom in the test chamber area.]]
{{Wad
| name = Action Doom
| author = Scuba Steve
| iwad = Doom2
| status = Released
| type = m
| link = {{idgames|id=12671}}
| caco = 11
}}
== About ==
Action Doom is meant to try and bring back the run and gun feeling from the old 2D shooters like Contra and Metal Slug. In the tradition of such games there are no bullet weapons, only projectiles. And just like Contra every enemy and subsequently you, all have but one hit point, aside from bosses and mini bosses.

To make the game feel more 2D and less frustrating, you will never be attacked from behind, and the level is entirely linear.
== Story ==
The year is 2174 and the Union Aerospace Corporation is in over its head.  On a remote island in the Gulf of Mexico, the United States Government funded the construction of the top secret UAC Site 4 Labs.  They were to be in charge of the work the government was unwilling to show the public. Originally, the base was constructed to investigate extra terrestrial lifeforms buried deep beneath the surface of the earth. Recently however, scientists and army officials together have begun teleportation experiments... into other dimensions.  Using this newfound portal technology, the United States Government has created a gateway into Hell itself.

As if things couldn't get more convoluted, the story doesn't end there.  Now, never content to just sit idle, scientists at UAC Site 4 have begun genetically altering demons brought back from hell, with the DNA from the Aliens found at the crash site.

It has been a week since any contact has been made with Site 4, and the government has only one option left, the men and women of the most elite government task force known as I.M.P.S.E.  It's up to you to discover what happened to the UAC Installation.

== Reception ==
By far, Action Doom is one of the most recognized WADs ever created. Before the WAD was released it had a comedic website showing a few screenshots and artwork. The website jokingly tried to advertise Action Doom as a separate game, despite being a patch WAD. The website and teasers gained the WAD a huge amount of hype before it was finally released. It received many positive reviews from pretty much every Doom website out there. Currently it has over 300 votes on [[Doomworld]]'s idgames with a 4 star rating and is still getting positive comments today. The WAD also received a [[Cacoward]].

== External Links ==
* [http://action.mancubus.net/actiondoom/ Official Website]</text>
    <sha1>e1zxv0zkm487dxljycdz4i22lf4dqe8</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>