<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Claustrophobia: The Walls Close In</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>3780</id>
  <revision>
    <id>50460</id>
    <parentid>25939</parentid>
    <timestamp>2023-08-10T10:37:01Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Dynamo</username>
      <id>2607</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <origin>50460</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2757" sha1="9t46shcd890tgqhu8xq2xhjelixzzyh" xml:space="preserve">{{doomwiki}}[[Image:ClaustScreenshot1.png|right|thumb|230px|A screenshot of MAP03 when you reach hell.]]
{{Wad
| name = Claustrophobia: The Walls Close In
| author = Virgil The Doom Poet
| iwad = Doom2
| type = m
| status = Released
| link = {{idgames|id=12364}}
}}
== Description ==
Claustrophobia: The Walls Close In is a 4 level [[WAD]] which uses lots of [[ZDoom]] features, mainly extensive use of [[ACS]]. The WAD is split up into 4 huge levels with lots of monsters and story elements. It is one of the few WADs to have cutscenes, memorable characters and insane boss fights. The boss fights are truly a sight to be hold, casting annoucned spells, altering the arena for attacks, spawning monsters for you to fight, etc. It has some of the most advanced use of ACS and considering there is no use of DECORATE to create the new bosses, they are probably the best boss fights ever seen in ZDoom to date. The name of the WAD comes from the many battles that you have in the levels, as most of them are very cramped and full of enemies.

== Story ==
After surviving the hellspawn-overrun castle (see "Dark Castle" - dark_c.zip), you barely escaped back to your own time. Everything on Earth seemed fine, no satanic signs, no zombies anywhere.  However, the base that contained the gate which sent you back through time had a different story.  After sending you to the entrance of the hell-ridden castle, the gate became destabilized. At first, it seemed like just another magnetic storm, but then a creature stepped through. You arrived back at another location, so the base's events didn't reach you until the day after your victory. You were awakened by a phonecall at 3:25 in the morning: "Get your ass over to the nearest military installation on the double!  We've got a situation..." After explaining the 'situation', you were briefed.  You were to lead a squad of SEALs into the rebuilt base on Deimos.  You were to scout the area and to report back with information about what the military would be dealing with.  As you went into the main entrance, it for some
reason shut behind you and your squad.At first, there was only one loss.  Around half an hour later, the SEALs started dropping like flies. They came out of nowhere. 16 veteran soldiers, including you, went in.  An hour later, only 2 others were left.  These 2 survivors then disappeared in a series of shrieks in a poorly lit hallway.  You somehow managed to escape from the dark, clawed shapes.  You ran.  Then you ran some more. You stumbled upon an door, managed to open it and tripped right into the claws of an imp. All you have left is a pistol.  Screw finding information. You're scared, confused, and, most of all, pissed off. Might as well start by taking it out on the imp.</text>
    <sha1>9t46shcd890tgqhu8xq2xhjelixzzyh</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>