<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>NeoDoom</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>3784</id>
  <revision>
    <id>51630</id>
    <parentid>49484</parentid>
    <timestamp>2024-02-04T12:36:52Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Dynamo</username>
      <id>2607</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>I have spoken with Scuba Steve, who ran the Cacowards back then, and he looked through his notes and told me he did not know about NeoDoom's existence back in 2006. So this is unfounded speculation that I'm removing.</comment>
    <origin>51630</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2214" sha1="reyrfldodj23j6vn7l8f15c0zrxntcb" xml:space="preserve">{{doomwiki}}[[Image:Neodoom-5.png|right|thumb|230px|One of the many industrial maps of NeoDoom.]]
{{Wad
| name = NeoDoom
| author = Daniel
| iwad = Doom2
| type = m
| status = Released
| link = {{idgames|id=14359}}
}}
== Description ==
NeoDoom is a 32 map megawad for ZDoom. It has a load of new weapons, monsters, textures and music. The maps span from Tech bases, forests, beaches, cities, Egyptian temples and hell. The monsters vary from monsters from the Monster Resource Wad to original incarnations of bosses and enemies from [[Hexen]] and Duke Nukem. The weapons and inventory items are plentiful and are occasionally dropped by monsters, giving a sort of RPG feel to it.

Oddly enough it is compatible with Legacy and DoomsDay, although the new weapons and monsters will not be present.


== About NeoDoom ==
This mod follows the traditional Doom mission story line, with 32 leves divided into three episodes. The first one have an industrial-like feeling, mostly with zombie human enemies, then, some passage levels will get the player to the second episode, played on a City. Finally, the last episode is made by various kinds of places, such as ancient temples, medieval castles, alien spaceships and the hell itself. The last secret level also has a special theme.

This is the first megawad that is compatible with the most popular source ports (and probably the unique) until 2004: ZDoom, Doom Legacy and Doomsday Engine, and it also can run also in source ports that have DeHackEd support. Nowadays, the main Doom scene is taken by ZDoom, GZDoom and Skulltag and their improvements, fact that requires a major update to this megawad.

== Reception ==
NeoDoom had mixed reviews from players. Many enjoyed the WAD for it's level variety, powerful weapons and tough creatures. It is still played over Co-op today on [[Skulltag]]. People criticized it for the maps being too "standard", and the amount of weapons and items made it too cumbersome. Doomers also complained about some of the monsters, mainly the Vixens, being way overpowered. Finally many people had a problem with some of the "stolen" material.

== External Links ==
*[http://www.brdoom.com/daniel/projetos_english.htm Official Website]</text>
    <sha1>reyrfldodj23j6vn7l8f15c0zrxntcb</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>