<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Scourge</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>3789</id>
  <revision>
    <id>29759</id>
    <parentid>29755</parentid>
    <timestamp>2010-12-09T22:33:25Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Phobus</username>
      <id>790</id>
    </contributor>
    <origin>29759</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1831" sha1="mamtpkda8zgui26sp9rvvc98n9tjfvj" xml:space="preserve">{{Wad| name = Scourge
| author = [[User:Phobus|Phobus]]
| iwad = Doom2
| type = m
| status = Released
| link = [http://www.phobus.servegame.com/doom/ph_scrge.zip Download from Phobus's site]
}}

== Description ==

[[Image:ph_ScourgeScreenMAP01.png|right|thumb|230px|Scourge goes from humble beginnings...]]

Phobus' first released wad, it showcases a lot of [[vanilla Doom]] style gameplay with a few hints at [[ZDoom]] involvement. For the main 21 levels this is largely just jumping and areas which make use of [[freelook]], but for the secret level this includes slopes and particle fountains, plus a decorate monster. The wad also features a CREDMAP (not an official lump) which uses [[ACS]] scripting and more [[DECORATE]] monsters.

The earlier levels are generally quite amateur and show little more than basic editing skills, but play surprisingly well. Later levels are better and better, with maps 18, 19, 20 and 21 being larger, more aesthetically pleasing, more complex and generally better.
[[Image:ph_ScourgeScreenMAP20.png|right|thumb|230px|...to a much darker and grander end.]]
Features:

* 23 maps (21 main levels, a secret map and CREDMAP)
* A MAPINFO driven storyline
* New TITLEPIC and INTERPIC
* Decorate monster (the Armoured Baron) plus other uses of decorate
* Minor use of ZDoom features throughout the series
* "Old school" gameplay for the most part

Suitable for single play, although co-op and deathmatch starts are included for up to 4 players in every map, it was never really intended. All levels completable from a pistol start.

Made with:

DEU2, Doom Builder, MSPaint and XWE

More info and more screenshots are available on Phobus' webpage for Scourge, linked below.

== External links ==
* [http://www.phobus.servegame.com/doom/ph_scrge.html Phobus' webpage for Scourge]
* {{idgames|id=14192}}</text>
    <sha1>mamtpkda8zgui26sp9rvvc98n9tjfvj</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>