<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Zharkov Goes to the Store</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>3812</id>
  <revision>
    <id>25839</id>
    <parentid>14810</parentid>
    <timestamp>2010-02-19T11:20:17Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <origin>25839</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1422" sha1="iewca0hxewhe61tx9satheb9tc2u7jr" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Zharky-1.png|right|245px|thumb|The Raynor-666 Projectile Launch System in action during Consumer Rush Hour]]
{{Wad
| name = Zharkov Goes to the Store
| author = Xaser
| iwad = Doom2
| type = w
| status = Released
| link = {{idgames|id=15194}}
}}

== Description ==
''"An epic tale of deception and innocence - 6/5" --Anonymous Reviewer, /idgames Archive''
[[Image:Zharky-2.png|right|245px|thumb|Missile walls provide an excellent counter for demon Ambushes. Bombs away!]]

From the mind of the ever-insane Xaser comes the most zany, epic tale in the Doom universe, '''Zharkov Goes to the Store'''. Take control of the half-crazed and starving Zharkov as he fights the legions of hell, his inner demons, and his uncontrollable hunger. The line between reality and fiction blurs as his journey takes him to the very center of Hell itself.

Strictly speaking, '''Zharkov Goes to the Store''' is a weapon modification, but certainly not a typical one. Brandish a fiendish arsenal of wacky weaponry including rice guns, missile walls, projectile rainers, ricochet guns, rock throwers, and Zharkov's signature Reality-Bending Kung-Fu. Complete with an optional epic do-it-yourself soundtrack and some of the most insane effects this side of Mars, Zharkov is a must-have for anyone with a thirst for weaponry or a hunger for humor.

[http://www.doomworld.com/idgames/index.php?id=15194 Go to the Store], Zharkov. Destiny.</text>
    <sha1>iewca0hxewhe61tx9satheb9tc2u7jr</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>