<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Zero Tolerance</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>3873</id>
  <revision>
    <id>50360</id>
    <parentid>42367</parentid>
    <timestamp>2023-07-07T10:13:10Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Dynamo</username>
      <id>2607</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <origin>50360</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2135" sha1="rui8dli5tv43lquu8yy9qxwql4dapff" xml:space="preserve">{{doomwiki|Zero Tolerance (gameplay mod)|Zero Tolerance}}[[Image:Zp-zerot1.png|right|245px|thumb|ZEROT's protagonist, the Prototype, features both a deadly arsenal and a snazzy new Heads-up Display.]]
{{Wad
| name = Zero Tolerance
| author = Zero Prophet (Setzer)
| iwad = Doom2
| status = Released
| type = w
| link = {{idgames|id=15321}}
}}

== Description ==
'''Requires ZDoom development versions or GZDoom'''
[[Image:Zp-zerot2.png|right|245px|thumb|Tear away at enhanced demons using monster machine guns, face-melting fusion cannons, and much, much more!]]

After many months of work and even more months of delay, Zero Prophet's debut, '''Zero Tolerance'', smashes into the ZDoom scene with surprising force. Aimed at being not just a weapon mod but a full-blown gameplay enhancement, Zero Tolerance puts the player in the role of the Prototype, an enhanced killing-machine in a world gone wrong. Bring forth a deadly arsenal of sci-fi weaponry including flak guns, photon pistols, cluster bombs, bouncing plasma, and much, much more than one can shake a BFG at.

Additionally, the mod sports a deadly cast of new enemies and enhanced, familiar foes. Blow 'em to shreds and be amazed at Nash's gruesomely-satisfying enhanced gore effects as enemies literally fly apart in a sea of red. Keep track of your status with the Prototype's signature Heads-up display, and give those baddies the beating they deserve!

As a 'bonus feature', the mod also includes a well-written backstory, set in the timeframe of the events of the original Doom. Experience the "first invasion" through the eyes of a failed government experiment unwillingly thrust into mankind's greatest catastrophe.

'''Zero Tolerance''' is a blast to play both alone and in co-op. Grab a friend and blow the opposition to shreds with double the firepower! Compatible with a huge variety of wads and recommended for both team and solo ventures, Zero Prophet has crafted a simply unforgettable Doom experience.

What are you waiting for? [http://www.doomworld.com/idgames/index.php?id=15321 Download Zero Tolerance] now and give those demons a taste of their own fury!</text>
    <sha1>rui8dli5tv43lquu8yy9qxwql4dapff</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>