<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>FMOD Ex</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>3916</id>
  <revision>
    <id>45232</id>
    <parentid>45228</parentid>
    <timestamp>2017-05-05T22:38:29Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>better cat</comment>
    <origin>45232</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2089" sha1="6o7qdc1gtx11anjl7bsh6gn4vchp96m" xml:space="preserve">{{warning|Since GZDoom 3.0, FMOD Ex is no longer available. The following information apply only to old versions and are only kept for historical purposes.}}
{{wikipedia}}
'''FMOD''' is a commercial audio library made by Firelight Technologies that plays music files of diverse formats on many different platforms. It is used in games and software applications to provide audio functionality. FMOD supports a range of audio formats and numerous different operating system platforms. 

FMOD comes in two versions, FMOD and FMOD Ex. FMOD Ex is the designation given to the 4.x series of the library, whilst FMOD alone refers to version 3.75 of the library, which lacks much of format/platform support added in FMOD Ex. [[ZDoom]] used FMOD since the 1.23-beta development versions (which would actually become 2.0.0), and updated to FMOD Ex with v2.3.0.

FMOD is available under multiple license schemes. It is available free of charge for non-commercial applications. FMOD may be used commercially under a number of different license types, such as "Commercial License" for standard commercial development, "Shareware/Hobbyist License" for single hobbyist programmers, and "eDistributed Console Games". for budget console game. Each license contains different restrictions, conditions and costs.

Successful compilation and execution of ZDoom is possible with all versions from 4.22 to 4.28 and 4.34 or later.  The 4.26 series was recommended for a long time due to issues the newer reverb engine and changes to 3D positional sound handling.  These issues were fixed for ZDoom 2.8.  The following versions of FMOD Ex are notable:
* 4.24.16 - Last version to support the G3 processor. This is used for PowerPC builds of ZDoom.
* 4.28.07 - Last version built for Solaris.
* 4.36.23 - Due to a change in compiler, this is the final version to support Windows 98, Me, NT4, or 2000. This is used for the 2.8 Windows builds.
* 4.44.58 - Last version to support G4/G5 PowerPC Macintoshes.

==External links==
* [http://www.fmod.org/ FMOD homepage]
[[Category:Documentation for removed features‎]]</text>
    <sha1>6o7qdc1gtx11anjl7bsh6gn4vchp96m</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>