<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Classes:CustomMonsterInvasionSpot</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>4053</id>
  <revision>
    <id>33152</id>
    <parentid>21493</parentid>
    <timestamp>2012-06-25T15:15:55Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Esum</username>
      <id>2010</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>/* Examples: */ the Editor number (DoomEdNum) used in the example was outside the range 1-32767</comment>
    <origin>33152</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2504" sha1="8yu06ihy910mbdn9av9d0vacjmum658" xml:space="preserve">{{Actor|
| type = Internal
| name = Invasion Monster Spawner
| class = CustomMonsterInvasionSpot
| game = Skulltag
}}
&lt;u&gt;CustomMonsterInvasionSpot&lt;/u&gt; is the base class for custom Invasion monsters. By inheriting from it you can create spawn spots for new [[DECORATE]] monsters.


==== Using in [[DECORATE]] ====
The &lt;u&gt;CustomMonsterInvasionSpot&lt;/u&gt; base class only needs one property for it to work, which is dropitem.

:*'''dropitem''' ''class''
::The class of the monster you want the Invasion spot to spawn. Can be used more than once to spawn more than one monster picked at random.

===== Examples: =====
Example of a single custom invasion spot:

 actor MyMonsterSpot : CustomMonsterInvasionSpot 12345
 {
 dropitem "MyMonster"
 }
Example of a random custom invasion spot:

 actor MyRandomMonsterSpot : CustomMonsterInvasionSpot 12346
 {
 dropitem "MyMonster"
 dropitem "MyOtherMonster"
 dropitem "Cacodemon"
 }

==== Using in a map editor ====
CustomMonsterInvasionSpot, like all invasion spots, take 5 special arguments. Monsters that aren't spawned due to lack of room (other actors) will be spawned when there is room. It is '''vital''' that you place invasion spawn spots in areas where there are no walls blocking the monster's spawn, as the wave will not end until all monsters are spawned and killed.

:*'''Start Spawn Number'''
::The number of things spawned in the first wave they appear.
:*'''Spawn Delay'''
::The spawn delay in seconds between spawning things.
:*'''Round Spawn Delay'''
::The delay in seconds from the start of the wave before spawning things.
:*'''First Appear Wave'''
::The wave that the things start spawning in.
:*'''Max Spawn Number'''
::The maximum number of monsters that can be spawned by this spot.

=== Invasion Formula ===
On any given wave, the number of monsters that will be spawned is determined by this formula:
: '''(Difficulty Modifier ^ Wave Age) * Starting Amount'''
:: The difficulty modifier is 1.25 for ''I'm too young to die'' and ''Hey, not too rough'', 1.5 for ''Hurt me plenty'', and 1.6225 for ''Ultra-Violence'' and ''Nightmare!''.
:: Wave age is determined by using the current wave and substracting First Appear Wave (with a minimum of 0).
:: The starting amount is the value given in the first argument, Start Spawn Number.
The given value is then limited to Max Spawn Number.

== See Also ==
[[Classes:CustomPickupInvasionSpot|CustomPickupInvasionSpot]] - Custom Invasion Spot used for pickups.&lt;br&gt;
[[Classes:Skulltag|Skulltag Classes]]</text>
    <sha1>8yu06ihy910mbdn9av9d0vacjmum658</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>