<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>BOTINFO</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>4153</id>
  <revision>
    <id>40561</id>
    <parentid>19671</parentid>
    <timestamp>2015-12-14T03:34:37Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Minigunner1024</username>
      <id>1555</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>Rearranged rail colors to match the order of Zandronum's railcolor cvar.</comment>
    <origin>40561</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2632" sha1="90685zm22cmf3vgv2rsonecaj98zpco" xml:space="preserve">{{STFeature}}
'''BOTINFO''' is a lump used to define bots in [[Skulltag]]. Bots are defined between closing and opening braces, like so:

 ''{''
 ''Properties...''
 ''}''

=== Properties ===
The following properties can be used when defining a bot.

*'''name'''
:The name of your bot. Can be used with print color codes.
*'''script'''
:The bot script to use with the bot. Bot scripts give bots certain properties, such as making them slower or taunt more often. (Check _BOTLUMP for the predefined scripts)
*'''chatfile'''
:The path and filename to the Bot's chat file usually in \bots\chatfiles\. Long filenames may cause a crash.
*'''gender'''
:The gender of your bot. Can be ''male'', ''female'' or ''neither''.
*'''color'''
:The skin color of the bot in "RR GG BB" format.
*'''railcolor'''
:The color of the bot's [[Classes:Skulltag|Railgun]]. Possible values are blue, red, yellow, black, silver, gold, green, white, purple, orange, and rainbow.
*'''skin'''
:The skin of the bot, either defined in [[S_SKIN]] or [[SKININFO]].
*'''class'''
:The prefered Class of the bot. For [[Hexen]] it can be Random, Fighter, Cleric or Mage. Custom [[Classes:PlayerPawn|player classes]] are supported too.
*'''revealed'''
:Determines if the bot is 'hidden' from selection in the 'Select bots' list in Skirmish. Can be true or false.
*'''favoriteweapon'''
:The bot's favorite weapon. The bot will usually try to get their weapon first.
*'''chatfrequency'''
:How often the bot will say things from chatfile or chatlump. Value can be 1 to 100.
*'''chatlump'''
:An alternative to chatfile, which is instead a lump inside the wad file.
*'''accuracy'''
:How accurate the bot is with hitscan weapons. Value can be 0 to 4.
*'''intellect'''
:How "smart" the bot is. Smarter bots will be able to predict where to fire projectile weapons and hit dodging players better. Values can be 0 to 4. (The incorrect spelling "intelect" also works)
*'''evade'''
:How well the bot can dodge projectiles. Values can be 0 to 4.
*'''anticipation'''
:How well the bot can anticipate shots from hitscan weapons. Value can be 0 to 4.
*'''reactiontime'''
:How well the bot can react to what is happening (being shot at etc). Value can be 0 to 4.
*'''perception'''
:How well the bot knows where his enemies are. Value can be 0 to 4.

== Examples ==
 {
 name = "\clSIR VANQUISHABLE"
 script = HUMANBOT
 chatlump = MYBOT1
 gender = male
 color = "BF 77 00"
 railcolor = "red"
 skin = "Doomcrate"
 class = "fighter"
 revealed = true
 accuracy = 3
 intelect = 1
 evade = 4
 anticipation = 1
 reactiontime = 3
 perception = 2
 chatfrequency = 100
 favoriteweapon = "shotgun"
 }</text>
    <sha1>90685zm22cmf3vgv2rsonecaj98zpco</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>