<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>ANCRINFO</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>4220</id>
  <revision>
    <id>28198</id>
    <parentid>19791</parentid>
    <timestamp>2010-11-16T02:08:12Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Jpalomo</username>
      <id>1715</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>Cleaning up</comment>
    <origin>28198</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="5427" sha1="jqgj8i2onft7pkanvo0y61d53t2eip0" xml:space="preserve">{{STFeature}}
ANCRINFO remaps sounds defined in [[SNDINFO]] to announcer entries.  The format of the lump is as follows:
 {
    name = "My Announcer"
    // entryname = sndinfo/sound
 }

There are no required entries nor are does the parser check for specific entries.  The following is a list of announcer entries that are used somewhere by Skulltag.
 accuracy - Awarded the "Accuracy" medal.
 assist - Awarded the "Assist" medal.
 blueflagdropped - When the blue flag has been dropped. 
 blueflagreturned - When the blue flag is returned to it's original location.
 blueflagtaken - When someone takes the blue flag.
 blueleads - When the blue team takes the lead.
 bluescores - When the blue team scores (CTF, Skulltag etc.)
 blueskulldropped - When the blue skull has been dropped.
 blueskullreturned - When the blue skull is returned to it's original location.
 blueskulltaken - When someone takes the blue skull.
 capture - Awarded the "Capture" medal.
 defense - Awarded the "Defence" medal.
 domination - Awarded the "Domination" medal.
 doomsphere - Picked up a [[Classes:Skulltag|Doom Sphere]].
 drain - Picked up a [[Classes:Skulltag|Drain Rune]].
 excellent - Awarded the "Excellent" medal.
 fight - "Fight!" after the countdown before the game starts.
 firstfrag - Awarded the "First Frag" medal.
 fisting - Awarded the "Fisting" medal.
 fiveminutewarning - Five minutes of the current game remain.
 gaurdsphere - Picked up a [[Classes:Skulltag|GuardSphere]].
 haste - Picked up a [[Classes:Skulltag|Haste Rune]].
 highjump - Picked up a [[Classes:Skulltag|High jump Rune]].
 impressive - Awarded the "Impressive" medal.
 incredible - Awarded the "Incredible" medal.
 invisibility - Picked up a [[Classes:Skulltag|Invisibility Sphere]].
 invulnerability - Picked up a [[Classes:InvulnerabilitySphere|Invulnerability Sphere]].
 llama - Awarded the "Llama" medal.
 megasphere - Picked up a [[Classes:Megasphere|Mega Sphere]].
 mostimpressive - Awarded the "Most Impressive" medal.
 nextroundin
 one - "One". Countdown to the game.
 onefragleft - When a player has one frag left to win the game.
 oneminutewarning - One minute of the game remains.
 partialinvisibility - Picked up a [[Classes:BlurSphere|Partial Invisibility Sphere]].
 perfect - Awarded the "Perfect" medal.
 possessionartifactdropped - When the possesion artifact is picked up in the Possesion gamemode.
 possessionartifactpickedup - When the possesion artifact is droped up in the Possesion gamemode.
 precision - Awarded the "Precision" medal.
 preparetofight - "Prepare to fight!" Before a game begins, usually after another has ended.
 prosperity - Picked up a [[Classes:Skulltag|Prosperity Rune]].
 rage - Picked up a [[Classes:Skulltag|Rage Rune]].
 redflagdropped - When the red flag has been dropped.
 redflagreturned - When the red flag is returned to it's original location.
 redflagtaken - When the red flag has been taken.
 redleads - When the red team takes the lead.
 redscores - When the read team scores (Skulltag, CTF etc.)
 redskulldropped - When the red skull has been dropped.
 redskullreturned - When the red skull is returned to it's original location.
 redskulltaken - When the red skull has been taken.
 reflection - Picked up a [[Classes:Skulltag|Reflection Rune]].
 regeneration - Picked up a [[Classes:Skulltag|Regeneration Rune]].
 resistance - Picked up a [[Classes:Skulltag|Resistance Rune]].
 soulsphere - Picked up a [[Classes:Soulsphere|Soul Sphere]].
 spam - Awarded the "Spam" medal.
 spread - Picked up a [[Classes:Skulltag|Spread Rune]].
 strength - Picked up a [[Classes:Skulltag|Strength Rune]].
 tag - When you score in the Skulltag gamemode
 teamsaretied - When the score becomes tied in team games (Skulltag, CTF etc.)
 termination - Awarded the "Termination" medal.
 terminator - Picked up the [[Classes:Skulltag|Terminator Sphere]].
 theenemyhastheflag - When your team's flag is taken in the Capture The Flag Gamemode.
 three - "Three". Countdown for the game to start.
 threefragsleft - When a player has three frags remaining.
 timefreeze - Picked up a [[Classes:Skulltag|Time Freeze Sphere]].
 totaldomination - Awarded the "Total Domination" medal.
 turbosphere - Picked up a [[Classes:Skulltag|Turbo Sphere]].
 two - "Two". Countdown before the game begins.
 twofragsleft - When a player has two frags remaining.
 victory - When you successfully beat your opponent in a duel.
 votefailed - The current vote failed.
 votenow - A new vote started.
 votepassed - If the vote was sucessful.
 welcometoctf - Welcome message at the start of a CTF game.
 welcometooneflagctf - Welcome message at the start of a one flag CTF game.
 welcometost - Welcome message at the start of a SkullTag game.
 whiteflagreturned - When the white flag is returned in the One Flag CTF gamemode.
 youaretiedforthelead - When you have the same amount of frags as the leader.
 youfailit - Awarded the "[[Exclamation mark|You fail it]]" medal.
 youhavetheflag - When you pick up the Enemy flag/ White flag in Capture the flag/One Flag CTF.
 yourskillisnotenough - Awarded the "Your skill is not enough" medal.
 yourteamhastheflag - When someone on your team picks up the Enemy flag/White flag in Capture the flag/One Flag CTF.
 youvelostthelead - When you were in the lead but another player has taken it.
 youvetakenthelead - When you overtake the leader in frags.
 youwin - When you win the game.

== Examples ==
{{noexamples}}</text>
    <sha1>jqgj8i2onft7pkanvo0y61d53t2eip0</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>