<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Hell doom</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>4999</id>
  <revision>
    <id>26757</id>
    <parentid>19689</parentid>
    <timestamp>2010-05-17T03:02:06Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>MithranDenizen</username>
      <id>1713</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>Spelling corrections.</comment>
    <origin>26757</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1485" sha1="1483xfu4zb3phi6q484h7tj1b3w9m5r" xml:space="preserve">Hell Doom is a wad currently in work by user Bobvorn. It contains new weapons, new monsters, and new levels. This wad will work with ZDoom. All the weapon slots are used by multiple weapons. The original weapons are included for people who like the things like the plasma rifle and BFG. A couple of weapons will be used from the weapon resource wad also. The graphics are not the greatest, done mostly in Microsoft Paint. I am not a very good artist so that would explain it.


== Weapons ==

Currently there are 5 new weapons added.

Slot 1
    Knife (simple melee weapon. Kills weaker opponents in 1 hit.)
    Hammer (Another simple melee weapon. Kills weaker opponents in 1 hit.)
Slot 2
    Wand (Kills every opponent in 1 hit)
    Serious Bomb (From the weapon resource wad this thin kills everything in a good sised vicinity.)
Slot 5
    Cannon (Stronger than the rocket launcher. Uses rockets for ammo.)
    Jump Punch (Launch yourself across great distances with this normal melee punch.)


== Levels ==

There are currently 3 levels created. Not insanely good texturing, but they have a good feel to them.


== Monsters ==

I have only redone the imp skin currently and it is a stickman now. Kind of stupid but it is fun to see his head blow open.


== Download ==

The 3 levels that I have created so far are downloadable here.
[http://files.filefront.com/helldoomwad/;11622991;/fileinfo.html]

This project has currently been abandoned.

[[Category:Abandoned ZDoom Projects]]</text>
    <sha1>1483xfu4zb3phi6q484h7tj1b3w9m5r</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>