<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Weapon properties</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>5092</id>
  <revision>
    <id>52951</id>
    <parentid>51869</parentid>
    <timestamp>2024-08-22T06:22:20Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Blue Shadow</username>
      <id>2021</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>remove {{new}}</comment>
    <origin>52951</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="4626" sha1="4hyfgiwccof3u66crh46e2o0trkzws1" xml:space="preserve">&lt;onlyinclude&gt;* '''{{LE|Weapon.AmmoGive}}''' ''amount''
* '''{{LE|Weapon.AmmoGive1}}''' ''amount''
:The amount of primary ammo you receive from this weapon.
* '''{{LE|Weapon.AmmoGive2}}''' ''amount''
:The amount of secondary ammo you get from picking up the weapon.
* '''{{LE|Weapon.AmmoType}}''' ''type''
* '''{{LE|Weapon.AmmoType1}}''' ''type''
:The type of primary ammo the weapon uses. This must be a valid [[Classes:Ammo|ammo type]].
* '''{{LE|Weapon.AmmoType2}}''' ''type''
:The type of secondary ammo the weapon uses.
* '''{{LE|Weapon.AmmoUse}}''' ''amount''
* '''{{LE|Weapon.AmmoUse1}}''' ''amount''
:The amount of primary ammo the weapon uses per shot.
* '''{{LE|Weapon.AmmoUse2}}''' ''amount''
:The amount of the secondary ammo that the weapon uses per shot. Normally secondary ammo is used by the secondary attack but if the {{Flag|WEAPON.PRIMARY_USES_BOTH}} flag is set the primary attack will use both types of ammo for each attack.
* '''{{LE|Weapon.MinSelectionAmmo1}}''' ''amount''
:A weapon with this property will not be auto-switched to if the available amount of ammo for the ''primary'' attack is less than the value specified. The weapon can still be switched to manually, however.
* '''{{LE|Weapon.MinSelectionAmmo2}}''' ''amount''
:A weapon with this property will not be auto-switched to if the available amount of ammo for the ''secondary'' attack is less than the value specified. The weapon can still be switched to manually, however.
* '''{{LE|Weapon.BobPivot3D}}''' (''x'', ''y'', ''z'') {{Zscriptfeaturesmall}}
:{{moreinfo}}
:Default is (0.0, 0.0, 0.0).
* '''{{LE|Weapon.BobRangeX}}''' ''amount''
:Range multiplier for horizontal bobbing.
:Default is 1.0.
* '''{{LE|Weapon.BobRangeY}}''' ''amount''
:Range multiplier for vertical bobbing.
:Default is 1.0.
* '''{{LE|Weapon.BobSpeed}}''' ''amount''
:Bobbing speed multiplier. Affects how quickly the bobbing motion occurs.
:Default is 1.0.
* '''{{LE|Weapon.BobStyle}}''' ''type''
:The type of bobbing to use. Possible values include {{c|Normal}}, {{c|Inverse}}, {{c|Alpha}}, {{c|InverseAlpha}}, {{c|Smooth}}, and {{c|InverseSmooth}}.
:*{{c|Normal}} is the default value and corresponds to the bobbing motion used in all old Doom-engine games.
:*{{c|Alpha}} is the bobbing motion used in the {{dw|alpha}} versions of ''[[Doom]]''.
:*{{c|Smooth}} is a smoother version of the normal style.
:*{{c|Inverse*}} types mirror the motion vertically compared to the non-inverse version. InverseAlpha lowers the weapon sprite while bobbing; the others raise it.
* '''{{LE|Weapon.KickBack}}''' ''amount''
:How far attacks by this weapon push the enemy back. Damage is also a factor in kickback.
* '''{{LE|Weapon.DefaultKickBack}}'''
:Weapons with this property have a kickback value which is specified by the {{c|defkickback}} [[MAPINFO/GameInfo definition|MAPINFO property]].
* '''{{LE|Weapon.ReadySound}}''' ''sound''
:The sound the weapon plays in its ready state.
* '''{{LE|Weapon.SelectionOrder}}''' ''value''
:Defines the place in the weapons list when ammo runs out. Lower numbers have higher priority.  The standard [[:Category:Doom_II_weapons|Doom II weapons]] range from 100 for the [[Classes:PlasmaRifle|Plasma Rifle]] to 3700 for the [[Classes:Fist|Fist]].
* '''{{LE|Weapon.SisterWeapon}}''' ''weapontype''
:Defined weapon is also given when flagged weapon is picked up. Used primarily for [[Classes:ArtiTomeOfPower|Tome Of Power]] attacks but it can also be used to create weapons with 2 distinct attack modes. Several Strife weapons use this.
* '''{{LE|Weapon.SlotNumber}}''' ''value''
:Default slot for this weapon. For mods that want to add new weapons without completely redoing the player's arsenal. For other ways to assign weapons to slots, see [[weapon slots]].
* '''{{LE|Weapon.SlotPriority}}''' ''value''
:Selection order within slot for this weapon. This is a floating-point value. Higher numbers mean higher priority.
* '''{{LE|Weapon.UpSound}}''' ''sound''
:The sound played when the select state is called.
* '''{{LE|Weapon.WeaponScaleX}}''' ''value''
:The horizontal scale multiplier of the weapon's HUD sprite.
:Default is 1.0.
* '''{{LE|Weapon.WeaponScaleY}}''' ''value''
:The vertical scale multiplier of the weapon's HUD sprite.
:Default is 1.2.
* '''{{LE|Weapon.YAdjust}}''' ''amount''
:Shifts the HUD sprites vertically when the status bar is off. ''Note: positive y values shift the weapon down.''
* '''{{LE|Weapon.LookScale}}''' ''amount''
:Multiplier for the player's look sensitivity. Operates identically to the look sensitivity for FOV scaling, but without changing the FOV.&lt;/onlyinclude&gt;
[[Category:Editing references]]</text>
    <sha1>4hyfgiwccof3u66crh46e2o0trkzws1</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>