<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>A KillSiblings</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>5113</id>
  <revision>
    <id>46802</id>
    <parentid>45058</parentid>
    <timestamp>2019-07-16T06:02:00Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Quaker540</username>
      <id>2135</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>Replaced the deprecated action function</comment>
    <origin>46802</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="3690" sha1="cdk97qa2shw0k8rm2rdkfhzrr1dqkzg" xml:space="preserve">{{codepointer|Monster AI}}
'''A_KillSiblings''' [(string ''damagetype'' [, int ''flags'' [, string ''filter'' [, string ''species'' [, int ''src'' [, int ''inflict'']]]]])]

==Usage==
Called by monsters to kill the monsters that were spawned by the same master (other than the caller). Currently the only function that sets the necessary information is [[A_SpawnItemEx]]. Optionally, a damagetype parameter can be given. Note that damage inflicted by this codepointer is not affected by damage factors.

Monsters spawned with [[A_SpawnProjectile]] are not affected by this. [[A_SpawnProjectile]] was never designed to spawn monsters.

==Parameters==
*''damagetype'' - If the actor dies, the actor will enter a death state based on damagetype if present (or pain state if using NODAMAGE).
*''flags'' - The following flags can be combined using the &lt;tt&gt;|&lt;/tt&gt; character between name constants:
**'''KILS_FOILINVUL''' - Kills monsters and/or missiles that have the INVULNERABLE flag.
**'''KILS_KILLMISSILES''' - Causes missiles that are affected to enter their death state. Note that this follows the INVULNERABLE and NODAMAGE rules for monsters.
**'''KILS_NOMONSTERS''' - Don't target monsters with this function. Alone, it makes the function do nothing, but can be combined with KILS_KILLMISSILES to only affect missiles.
**'''KILS_FOILBUDDHA''' — the ''{{Flag|BUDDHA|buddha}}'' effect is ignored when attempting to kill the actor.
**'''KILS_EXFILTER''' — inverts the case of the class name filter; the calling actor's siblings are only killed if their class name does not match the value passed to ''filter''.
**'''KILS_EXSPECIES''' — inverts the case of the [[species]] filter; the calling actor's siblings are only killed if their species does not match the value passed to ''species''.
**'''KILS_EITHER''' — the calling actor's siblings are killed if either of their class name or [[species]] matches the values passed to ''filter'' and ''species'', respectively.
*''filter'': the actor class to kill. The calling actor's siblings are only killed if their class name matches the specified filter class. Default is {{c|"None"}}.
*''species'': the actor [[species]] to kill. The calling actor's siblings are only killed if their species matches the specified species filter. Default is {{c|"None"}}.
* ''src'': Indicates the [[Actor pointer|actor pointer]] responsible for dealing the damage. A monster dealing the damage should use AAPTR_DEFAULT, and missiles should use AAPTR_TARGET (so monsters can identify missiles belonging to their owners and give proper credit for the kill). Default is AAPTR_DEFAULT.
* ''inflict'': The actor doing the actual damage. By changing this, the actor's flags upon the pointed actor are taken into account instead of the calling actor's own.

== Examples ==
The following is a variant of the {{Class|DoomImp|doom imp}}, a monster spawned by a different monster using the master/child flag. If it gets killed with an attack with the "Curse" [[damage types|damage type]], its death state triggers [[A_KillSiblings]], killing all of the other monsters spawned by the same master.
 ACTOR SoldierImp : {{Class|DoomImp}}
 {
   States
   {
   Pain.Voodoo:
     TROO H 2 [[A_Pain]]
     TROO H 50
     Goto See
   Pain.Curse:
     TROO H 2 [[A_Pain]]
     TROO H 2 [[A_DamageSiblings]](15)
     Goto See
   Death:
     TROO I 8 [[A_DamageMaster]](-25)
     TROO J 8 [[A_Scream]]
     TROO K 6
     TROO L 6 [[A_NoBlocking]]
     TROO M -1
     Stop
   Death.Curse:
     TROO I 8 [[A_KillMaster]]
     TROO J 8 [[A_Scream]]
     TROO K 6 [[A_KillSiblings]]
     TROO L 6 [[A_NoBlocking]]
     TROO M -1
     Stop
   }
 }


--------
{{Planned Parenthood}}</text>
    <sha1>cdk97qa2shw0k8rm2rdkfhzrr1dqkzg</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>