<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Doom: Evil Unleashed (Lysander)</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>5357</id>
  <revision>
    <id>37662</id>
    <parentid>31236</parentid>
    <timestamp>2014-02-13T04:16:42Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Deded007</username>
      <id>1392</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>template edit</comment>
    <origin>37662</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1502" sha1="6reltk2lsd82z92jrd5qpxgn4valvmq" xml:space="preserve">{{Wad| name = Doom: Evil Unleashed
| author = Lysander
| status = Abandoned
| iwad = Doom
}}

== Description ==

This mod is the combination of the original concept of Doom (as seen in the Doom Bible), Doom Alpha, Doom 3, and my own touches. I intend to hopefully have most of the new content my own, instead of many of the projects out there, that "borrow" resources from other wads.

== Story ==

The year is 2145. The Union Aerospace Corporation (UAC) is leading the way in space travel, technology, and exploration. You, one of the first recruits in UAC's Marine Force (created as a defense of possible outside alien threats) arrive on Mars. When you arrive, you (lucky you) are chosen for a routine recovery mission of a scientist who had been fired from the UAC due to inappropriate erratic behavior, showing up late/not at all for duty and cussing out his superiors. The scientist apparently has continued working on a project that had been shut down. Your job is to go down to the decommissioned underground facility, drag him out by his ear, and throw him out and send him packing to Earth.

Unfortunately, it looks as though it may already be too late to contain his mess...  

== Features ==

* '''RPG Elements''' - Health items, artifacts, NPC interaction/dialogue
* '''Doom Alpha Weapons''' - Rifle, Machinegun, The Unmaker and more
* '''Chilling Environments''' - Unused sound effects for Doom 3 by Trent Reznor
* '''Full Game''' - Explore the Mars UAC base, the depths of Hell, and more!</text>
    <sha1>6reltk2lsd82z92jrd5qpxgn4valvmq</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>