<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>A SorcBallOrbit</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>5475</id>
  <revision>
    <id>37080</id>
    <parentid>23721</parentid>
    <timestamp>2013-08-31T20:06:57Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <origin>37080</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="4540" sha1="k4dtg5u70wyw9d77imfs2o68prwjqtw" xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:A_SorcBallOrbit}}
'''A_SorcBallOrbit'''&lt;br /&gt;
(no parameters)

This is part of the {{Class|Heresiarch}}'s attack function. This codepointer can only work correctly if it is called by an actor of type {{Class|SorcBall}} which has an actor of type Heresiarch in its &lt;tt&gt;target&lt;/tt&gt; field. (Projectiles use this field to store not what actor they were fired at, but which actor did fire them. The calling actor's &lt;tt&gt;target&lt;/tt&gt; field is supposed to be its parent actor.)

In the following, "ball" refers to the calling actor and "parent" to the calling actor's target. This codepointer makes use of several fields in the ball and its parent:

{| {{prettytable}}
! colspan="2"| Parent fields
|-
|&lt;tt&gt;special1&lt;/tt&gt;||Angle of the first ball
|-
|&lt;tt&gt;StopBall&lt;/tt&gt;||which type of ball to stop: {{Class|SorcBall1}}, {{Class|SorcBall2}} or {{Class|SorcBall3}}
|-
|&lt;tt&gt;args[0]&lt;/tt&gt;||Defense time
|-
|&lt;tt&gt;args[1]&lt;/tt&gt;||Number of full rotations since stopping mode
|-
|&lt;tt&gt;args[2]&lt;/tt&gt;||Orbit speed to reach when accelerating or decelerating
|-
|&lt;tt&gt;args[3]&lt;/tt&gt;||Movement mode, see below
|-
|&lt;tt&gt;args[4]&lt;/tt&gt;||Current ball orbit speed
|-
! colspan="2"|Ball fields
|-
|&lt;tt&gt;special1&lt;/tt&gt;||Previous angle of ball (for woosh)
|-
|&lt;tt&gt;special2&lt;/tt&gt;||Countdown of rapid fire ({{Class|SorcFX4}})
|}



If the ball has no parent, puts the ball in its pain state.

Otherwise, makes the calling actor orbits around its target. Depending on the value of the parent's &lt;tt&gt;args[3]&lt;/tt&gt; field, several other effects might happen, see "orbit modes" below.

=== Orbit modes ===

* 0: The ball decelerates to orbit more slowly: the parent's &lt;tt&gt;args[4]&lt;/tt&gt; field is decreased if it hasn't yet reached the value of the parent's &lt;tt&gt;args[2]&lt;/tt&gt; field, otherwise the parent's &lt;tt&gt;args[3]&lt;/tt&gt; field is set to 5.
* 1: The ball accelerates to orbit more quickly: the parent's &lt;tt&gt;args[4]&lt;/tt&gt; field is increased if it hasn't yet reached the value of the parent's &lt;tt&gt;args[2]&lt;/tt&gt; field, otherwise the parent's &lt;tt&gt;args[3]&lt;/tt&gt; field is set to 5 and if the &lt;tt&gt;args[4]&lt;/tt&gt; field has reached the value of 25, the balls stop their orbit, the parent's &lt;tt&gt;args[1]&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt&gt;[3]&lt;/tt&gt; fields are set to 0 and 3 respectively, and the &lt;tt&gt;StopBall&lt;/tt&gt; field is set to  {{Class|SorcBall2}} (about 80% chance if &lt;tt&gt;args[0]&lt;/tt&gt; is 0), {{Class|SorcBall3}} (otherwise, about 80% chance if the parent's health is reduced to half or less) or {{Class|SorcBall1}} the rest of the time.
* 2: If possible, stops the rotation and sets the parent's &lt;tt&gt;args[3]&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt&gt;args[4]&lt;/tt&gt; fields to 3 and 0 respectively. Otherwise, orbits normally. An actor of type {{Class|SorcBall1}} will update the parent's &lt;tt&gt;special1&lt;/tt&gt; field accordingly.
* 3: If the parent is alive and its &lt;tt&gt;StopBall&lt;/tt&gt; corresponds to the ball's type, puts the parent in its Attack1 state. Otherwise, do nothing. Further effects depends on the ball's type; see "attack modes" below.
* 4: Do nothing &amp;mdash; this is also the default (in)action for any value not in the 0&amp;mdash;6 range.
* 5: Orbits normally
* 6: Decrements the ball's &lt;tt&gt;special2&lt;/tt&gt; field, if it becomes negative then sets the parent's &lt;tt&gt;args[3]&lt;/tt&gt; field to 4 and, if alive, puts the parent in its Attack2 state.

=== Attack modes ===

* {{Class|SorcBall}}: Sets the parent's &lt;tt&gt;args[3]&lt;/tt&gt; field to 4. As this is a base type, SorcBall does nothing else.
* {{Class|SorcBall1}}: Makes the parent plays the "SorcererSpellCast" sound on its voice channel. About 80% of the time, the ball's &lt;tt&gt;args[4]&lt;/tt&gt; field is to 128 and its &lt;tt&gt;special2&lt;/tt&gt; field to 18; and the parent's &lt;tt&gt;args[3]&lt;/tt&gt; field is set to 6.&lt;br /&gt;
The rest of the time, puts the parent in its Attack2 state.
* {{Class|SorcBall2}}: Parent plays the sound "SorcererSpellCast" and goes in its Attack2 state. A {{Class|SorcFX2}} is spawned at the ball's horizontal position and vertically 45 units from the parent's feet; its &lt;tt&gt;target&lt;/tt&gt; field is set to the parent. The parent gains the REFLECTIVE and INVULNERABLE flags and its &lt;tt&gt;args[0]&lt;/tt&gt; is set to 255.
* {{Class|SorcBall3}}: Parent plays the sound "SorcererSpellCast" and goes in its Attack2 state. If the parent's health has been reduced to 1/3 of its starting value, spawns two {{Class|SorcFX3}}, otherwise spawn only one. Any spawned actor has its &lt;tt&gt;target&lt;/tt&gt; field set to the parent.

This codepointer is restricted to {{Class|SorcBall}} and actors inheriting from it.
[[Category:Decorate Hexen functions]] [[Category:Decorate Restricted functions]] {{DEFAULTSORT:SorcBallOrbit}}</text>
    <sha1>k4dtg5u70wyw9d77imfs2o68prwjqtw</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>