<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Claws of the Enraged Beast</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>5558</id>
  <revision>
    <id>29769</id>
    <parentid>25918</parentid>
    <timestamp>2010-12-09T22:39:58Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Phobus</username>
      <id>790</id>
    </contributor>
    <origin>29769</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1966" sha1="i8xdl7u7bqcww4qgxkqw0jrygxl8wke" xml:space="preserve">{{Wad|
| author = [[User:Phobus|Phobus]]
| iwad = Doom2
| type = s
| status = Released
| link = [http://www.phobus.servegame.com/doom/ph_quik4.zip Download from Phobus's site]
}}

== Description ==

[[Image:ph_Quick4Screen.png|right|thumb|230px|The TITLEPIC, showing how Slaughter! mode earnt its name]]

[[Scars of the Wounded Prey]] has been Phobus' hardest released project for quite a while on the hardest difficulty. Consequently, he felt it needed one-upping, and with Claws of the Enraged Beast, this has been acheived. A more lethal level, combined with improved visuals, more non-linearity and an overall better quality combine to create a map that can be played through in a variety of different ways, in two very different difficulty modes and either alone or with a friend.

Gameplay is either a massive slaughter with limited but adequete supplies, or a well stocked series of battles against lower numbers of generally tougher foes - either way, there are approximately three main different routes to the main objective and then on to the exit, and a variety of weapon layouts depending on the route taken. Various optional areas and secrets increase non-linearity and replayability - likewise, trying to speed run the map will also provide new challenges.

Features:

* 1 large, non-linear map
* Mid-level usage of ZDoom features (accentuate, rather than dominate)
* THE hardest gameplay Phobus has ever implemented on the harder of the two difficulties
* Very high attention to detail, aesthetics and texturing (attempted "essel-standard")
* TITLEPIC and low-quality version of Team17's StuntGP Soundtrack Track 8

Suitable for single play and 2 player co-op.

Made with:

Doom Builder, XWE, MSPaint, Sound Recorder

More info can be found on Phobus' webpage for Claws of the Enraged Beast, linked below.

== External Links ==
* [http://www.phobus.servegame.com/doom/ph_quik.html Phobus' webpage for Claws of the Enraged Beast]
* {{idgames|id=15841}}</text>
    <sha1>i8xdl7u7bqcww4qgxkqw0jrygxl8wke</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>