<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>MBF</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>5578</id>
  <revision>
    <id>27812</id>
    <parentid>27053</parentid>
    <timestamp>2010-10-02T17:13:39Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <origin>27812</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1967" sha1="41lyfq49a3p3izuc2iozx5nwd34vgt6" xml:space="preserve">{{Doomwiki}}'''MBF''', short for '''Marine's Best Friend''', is a port based on [[Boom]] in which Lee Killough, in addition to fixing Boom bugs, added many innovations, such as new codepointers, a "beta mode" emulating Doom's press-release beta, an improved AI (enemies are optionally capable of avoiding hazards such as crushers, and act more tactically, coming to the help of their wounded allies, backing off of melee, and avoiding too many to attack the same target so as to reduce the chance of infighting happening), and the {{Class|MBFHelperDog|helper dogs}} that gave this port its name.

Other features include:
* Linedef types 271 and 272 to transfer the line's upper texture to tagged sectors as sky; available as one of the effects of [[Static_Init]]
* Various bouncing behaviors, different from those of Heretic and Hexen, available through the {{Property|BounceType}} property
* The {{Flag|TOUCHY}} flag
* Many codepointers: [[A_Detonate]], [[A_Die]], [[A_Mushroom]] have been integrated to ZDoom. Others can be replicated differently: A_Face and A_Turn with [[A_SetAngle]], A_LineEffect with a direct call to an [[action special]], A_RandomJump with [[A_Jump]], A_Scratch with [[A_CustomMeleeAttack]]. [[A_Turn]] and [[A_LineEffect]] are also available but only for compatibility.
* Support for embedded [[DeHackEd]] lumps

MBF was released under both the original Doom Source License and the GPL. This dual-licensing allowed [[ZDoom]] to borrow or adapt code from MBF. Several [[compatibility options]] allow to use MBF's behavior on a few points.

MBF served as a base for [[SMMU]]. Both [[PrBoom]] and [[Eternity Engine]] support most of MBF's features. A Windows version is maintained by James Haley of Eternity.

== External links ==
*[http://www.archonrealm.com/doom/mbf.htm Old MBF FAQ Page]
*{{idgames|id=9895||MBF}}
*{{idgames|id=9896||MBF source code}}
*[http://mancubus.net/svn/winmbf/ WinMBF repository]

[[category:Non-ZDoom source ports]]</text>
    <sha1>41lyfq49a3p3izuc2iozx5nwd34vgt6</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>