<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Thing Damage</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>566</id>
  <revision>
    <id>53478</id>
    <parentid>49027</parentid>
    <timestamp>2024-11-01T10:30:17Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>TheMisterCat</username>
      <id>1636</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>Note added for clarity over behaviour when activator damages self</comment>
    <origin>53478</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1685" sha1="5ni4ws1dp8jij3vmbl3fadyn6be5wco" xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:Thing_Damage}}
{{Special|119|tid, amount, mod|Thing|Damage}}

== Usage ==

Damages the specified actor.

=== Parameters ===

* ''tid'': [[TID]] of the thing you want to damage.
* ''amount'': The amount of damage the thing will receive.
* ''mod'': Means of death. Determines the obituary message that will appear if a player is killed. Relevant damage types for the means of death are found on the [[Damage_types]] page.

Similar to [[DamageThing]], but it hurts actors by [[TID]] rather than whoever activates it. Note that if TID is 0, this behaves similarly to '''DamageThing''', but using 0 as the amount will not force death.

There are some newer built-in damage types for which no MOD code exists and custom damage types are identified by names; neither can be used with this special. If you want to attach this special outside a script, e.g. to a line or a thing, but need to use a damage type that is recognized by the game by name, but is not listed above, set the line/thing special to run a script instead and use the [[Thing_Damage2]] [[ACS]] function in the script.

See [[Damage types]] for a list of means-of-death.

== NOTE ==
Please note that if the activator of the action is the same as the actor having damage applied to them, this will always count as a suicide, disregarding the damagetype assigned (will just display 'player killed self' message) - Please ensure if you have a damagetype assigned and want it to display the correct obituary, that you have reassigned the activator, or the activator is otherwise not the same as the damaged thing.

== Examples ==

 Script 1 {{SType|Enter}}
 {
    [[Thing_Damage]](0, 20, {{const|MOD_RAILGUN}});
 }</text>
    <sha1>5ni4ws1dp8jij3vmbl3fadyn6be5wco</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>