<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Thing ChangeTID</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>569</id>
  <revision>
    <id>43784</id>
    <parentid>40495</parentid>
    <timestamp>2017-01-26T22:28:36Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Arkore</username>
      <id>2094</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>Adding another useful example with an important observation note.</comment>
    <origin>43784</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1666" sha1="m9a2otfkow201waubv5cjvpw90skgqk" xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:Thing_ChangeTID}}
{{Special|176|oldtid, newtid|Thing|TID}}

* ''oldtid'': The current [[TID]] of the thing whose TID will be changed.
* ''newtid'': The new TID that the thing will be changed to.

If ''oldtid'' is zero, then whatever activated the script will have its TID changed to ''newtid''. If ''oldtid'' is non-zero, then everything with the TID ''oldtid'' will have their TID changed to ''newtid''.

==Examples==
One of the primary uses for this special is to give a player a TID using a script like this:

 script 100 enter
 {
     Thing_ChangeTID (0, 1337+PlayerNumber());
 }

This will give player 1 the TID 1337, player 2 the TID 1338, player 3 the TID 1339, and so on.

Use this script for multiplayer levels:

 script 256 respawn
 {
     Thing_ChangeTID(0, PlayerNumber()+256);
 }
 
 script 257 death
 {
     Thing_ChangeTID(0, 0);
 }
 
 script 258 enter
 {
     Thing_ChangeTID(0, PlayerNumber()+256);
 }

This will give player 1 the TID 256, player 2 TID 257, etc. It will cause each player not to have a TID during death.

Use this script for multiplayer levels and players to retain their TID during death:

 script 256 respawn
 {
     Thing_ChangeTID(0, 0);
     Thing_ChangeTID(0, PlayerNumber()+256);
 }
 
 script 258 enter
 {
     Thing_ChangeTID(0, PlayerNumber()+256);
 }

This will give player 1 the TID 256, player 2 TID 257, etc. It will cause each player to keep their TID during death.

For multiplayer, it is very important to change the player's TID to 0 in DEATH or RESPAWN.  Otherwise, there will be multiple players (corpses) using the same TID, which will eventually result in a crash.

==External links==
* {{oldref}}</text>
    <sha1>m9a2otfkow201waubv5cjvpw90skgqk</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>