<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Legacy of Suffering</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>5788</id>
  <revision>
    <id>50388</id>
    <parentid>31702</parentid>
    <timestamp>2023-07-07T10:38:11Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Dynamo</username>
      <id>2607</id>
    </contributor>
    <origin>50388</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1546" sha1="i9c85gebwwp86n8x9ws1ys7sqi1jljx" xml:space="preserve">{{doomwiki}}{{cleanup}}
[[Image:LOS1.png|right|thumb|230px|Screenshot]]
[[Image:LOS2.png|right|thumb|230px|Screenshot]]
[[Image:LOS3.png|right|thumb|230px|Screenshot]]
{{Wad| name = Legacy Of Suffering
| author = Logan MTM
| port = GZDoom
| iwad = Doom2
| type = m
| status = Released
| link = {{idgames|id=15942}}
| caco = 16
}}
== Synopsis ==

The date is November 15th, 2145. On a remote moon base, the Union Aerospace Corporation - UAC, performs its secret military experiments when the most destructive force in the universe is unleashed. It doesn't take too long for it to reach for the small Moon base.

John Logan, one of 4 super soldiers existent, finds himself forced to figth a battle which his blood already waited for. Armed to the teeth, John sets out in search for answers and an epic confrontation with hellspawn forces.

== Quotation ==

''"This is shaping up to be one of the best mods for Doom that I have seen. It is absolutely jam packed with new features and things to make the player go WOW! but these do not take over and the game remains very playable. Seriously, the look, the layout, the playability, the "wow" factor, everything is stunning. It oozes quality everywhere. I think that people are going to be blown away by it. You've kept the project reasonably quiet and you aren't a modder with a well known track record (I think) so something this good "just appearing" (as far as most people are concerned) will be a real treat. I'm not a gambling man, but I'd put money on a Cacoward being given to this project."''</text>
    <sha1>i9c85gebwwp86n8x9ws1ys7sqi1jljx</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>