<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Helping the wiki</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>5859</id>
  <revision>
    <id>50756</id>
    <parentid>50278</parentid>
    <timestamp>2023-10-08T17:21:22Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Jekyll Grim Payne</username>
      <id>2175</id>
    </contributor>
    <origin>50756</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1637" sha1="r171vrfiwtg6dih73a5pslt4arvrfyg" xml:space="preserve">You want to help the wiki and you do not know where to begin? Here are a few suggestions:

{{note|Due to relentless spambot activity, account creation had to be disabled. Sorry. You can obtain an account by contacting one of the [[Special:ListUsers|wiki admins]] on another platform (ZDoom forums, Doomworld forums, Discord channel, etc.) with an email address at which the wiki software can send you your temporary password.}}

How to help:

* Follow [[Wiki documentation guide]] when editing or adding new pages.
* Create pages for ZDoom mods! Don't forget to follow the [[WAD Page Guidelines]], though. Or write articles and upload screenshots for the mods that have just the wad template and no true article.
* Clean up the pages that [[:Category:Cleanup|need to be updated]].
* Don't forget to use the [[Useful templates|handy templates]] that make maintenance easier.
* Add an accurate description to the actor pages that [[:Category:Actors which need a description|need a description]].
* Update the class pages! They often contain outdated information. Most importantly, add [[ZScript]] definitions to actor pages that still only have [[DECORATE]] ones. The most up-to-date code can be found on [https://github.com/ZDoom/gzdoom/tree/e7a79b0d448759b8cfe51e325f8a0b36cf340041/wadsrc/static/zscript GZDoom GitHub repository].
* If an external link is dead or broken, report it in the article's talk page or in the {{forum|ZDoom wiki thread|t=20573}}.
* Likewise, if the information in an article is lacking or hard to find.
* Just browse around and fix grammar and spelling mistakes where you can see them.

[[Category:Wiki guides]]</text>
    <sha1>r171vrfiwtg6dih73a5pslt4arvrfyg</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>