<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Eternal Doom IV: Return From Oblivion</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>6019</id>
  <revision>
    <id>50398</id>
    <parentid>46259</parentid>
    <timestamp>2023-07-07T10:44:04Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Dynamo</username>
      <id>2607</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <origin>50398</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1747" sha1="i3krtte0tw738x64hqswimp96d6vr9g" xml:space="preserve">{{doomwiki}}[[Image:RFO_01.JPG|thumb|EDIV: RFO: An epic 7-map hub]]

{{Wad| name = Eternal Doom IV: Return From Oblivion
| author = '''TeamTNT''': Esa 'Espi' Repo, Chris Couleur, Ty Halderman, Rex Claussen
| iwad = Doom2
| status = Released
| link = {{idgames|id=15193}}
| type = m
| caco = 15
}}

== Description ==

[[Image:RFO_02.png|thumb|Vast, expansive spaces]]
Dubbed a "7-map teaser" by TeamTNT, these maps were intended as a demo for what was to be a much larger project, but development never went any further. All maps are medieval-themed and generally very large compared to typical Doom maps, with non-linear layout featuring multiple paths. They feature castle and fortress architecture, fighting on an epic scale, and magnificent vistas. 

[[Image:RFO_03.png|thumb|Exquisite Gothic architecture]]
Maps 08-10 can be played in any order within the hub, and powerups &amp; enemies are different in any given map depending on whether you play it first or play it after entering from another map. This provides additional replay value.

Note that the [[MAPINFO]] featured in the mod does not define an episode. You will need to use the {{c|{{CCMD|D|map}} map08}}, type the {{c|idclev08}} cheat code, or use the {{param|warp 08}} command line parameter to start playing on the mod's first map.

==Features==
These levels feature the graphic, music, and sound resources of TeamTNT's Eternal Doom III, and enemies from the Monster Resource Wad (ZDoom community effort). Maps are vast and expansive, and Map27 features "solid" bridges and other ZDoom portal constructs.

== External links ==
* {{idgames|id=15193}}
* [http://www.teamtnt.com/ Team TNT website]
* [http://doomnexus.drdteam.org/RFO_Pix.html Additional screenshots on the Doom Nexus]</text>
    <sha1>i3krtte0tw738x64hqswimp96d6vr9g</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>