<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>BOSS</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>6033</id>
  <revision>
    <id>28094</id>
    <parentid>26979</parentid>
    <timestamp>2010-10-27T16:37:38Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <origin>28094</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1866" sha1="f0ta99e5ozmjr6yxcnj3mo0ziz0grhu" xml:space="preserve">{{Wad
 | name = BOSS
 | author = C30N9
 | iwad = Doom2
 | type = s
 | status = Released
 | link = [http://www.filefront.com/16749481/Boss.zip Download from File Front]
 }}

== About ==
[[Image:Zdoom Boss Arach.png|right|thumb|230px|Master Arach fight.]]
BOSS is a single level wad including a [[TITLEMAP]] shown instead of the main screen. It's about a player accessing through the map normally meeting two custom bosses. One is encountered as Sub-Boss and the another is the final boss.

== Story ==
You start in a room that is empty (furniture was removed of that room) near a base for marines. A marine was looking to a water view but suddenly imps spawn and kill him. You wonder what was that (text displayed). You search the room but you'll encounter a mirror. You see from that mirror that water had became lava and monsters are teleporting to the earth. Then the player starts playing.

== Features ==
* A TITLEMAP shown at the start
* Simple ACS Scripting
* Music remixes used as a boss fight
* New 3 monsters

== Music ==
* The Ultimate Challenge.mid (D_ULTIM.mid) used as the TITLEMAP music
* Waltz of the demons.mp3 used as the normal map music (MAP01)
* I Sawed the demons remix.mp3 by dark luke, used as the first boss fight
* Gothic Sandy.mp3 by Mazedude, used as the second boss fight

== Non-Standard Monsters List ==
* Paingasm - a green Cacodemon, can be found alone or summond by the dark cardinal (below)
* Master Arach - double stretched size Arachnotron
* The Dark Cardinal - a black Cyber-Demon floating with green fire taken from [http://www.realm667.com Realm667]

== Gameplay ==
It's only for one player with no deathmatch starts.

== Extra Information ==
[[Image:Boss old intro.PNG|right|thumb|230px|Old TITLEMAP for BOSS.]]
BOSS used an older TITLEMAP which showing monsters fighting each other, but now it's replaced with 4 Cyber-demons.</text>
    <sha1>f0ta99e5ozmjr6yxcnj3mo0ziz0grhu</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>