<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Sound options</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>6113</id>
  <revision>
    <id>46247</id>
    <parentid>45968</parentid>
    <timestamp>2018-10-03T00:05:15Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Wohlstand</username>
      <id>2594</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>Added libADLMIDI and libOPNMIDI into the list of available synthesizers</comment>
    <origin>46247</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2955" sha1="6wh0rsjexujjh8r3bcctkucgqywzhpv" xml:space="preserve">{{menutrail|Main menu|Options menu}}
[[File:SoundOptions.png|thumb|The sound options menu in [[Chex Quest 3]].]]
The '''sound options''' menu gives an interface to consult and modify several sound and music playback settings. Its [[MENUDEF]] name is {{c|SoundOptions}} and it can be summoned with the {{c|{{CCMD|O|menu_sound}}}} console command.

*'''{{LE|Sound volume}}''' (0&amp;mdash;1, by 0.05 increments)
:{{c|{{CVAR|S|snd_sfxvolume}}}}
:Allows to change the volume at which in-game sound effects are played. 0 is mute, 1 is full volume.
*'''{{LE|Menu volume}}''' (0&amp;mdash;1, by 0.05 increments)
:{{c|{{CVAR|S|snd_menuvolume}}}}
:Allows to change the volume at which menu-mode sound effects are played. 0 is mute, 1 is full volume.
*'''{{LE|Music volume}}''' (0&amp;mdash;1, by 0.05 increments)
:{{c|{{CVAR|S|snd_musicvolume}}}}
:Allows to change the volume at which the music is played. 0 is mute, 1 is full volume.
*'''{{LE|MIDI device}}'''
:{{c|{{CVAR|S|snd_mididevice}}}}
:ZDoom allows you to choose which [[MIDI device]] to use for [[music format|MUS and MIDI]] playback. In addition to any device provided by the OS, the following choices are available:
:*[[TiMidity++]]
:*[[OPL synth emulation]]
:*[[libADL]]
:*[[libOPN]]
:*[[GUS]]
:*[[FluidSynth]]
:After having changed the MIDI device, use the '''Restart sound''' command (see below) for the change to take effect.
*'''{{LE|Underwater reverb}}''' (On/Off)
:{{c|{{CVAR|S|snd_waterreverb}}}}
:ZDoom applies a reverb effect while the player avatar in under water. This can be turned off with this option.
*'''{{LE|Randomize pitches}}''' (On/Off)
:{{c|{{CVAR|S|snd_pitched}}}}
:Enables or disables the sound pitch randomization that Doom used to have until {{dw|Versions_of_Doom_and_Doom_II#v1.4|v1.4}}.
*'''{{LE|Sound channels}}''' (8&amp;mdash;256, by 8 increments)
:{{c|{{CVAR|S|snd_channels}}}}
:Selects how many sounds can be played at once. The maximum in [[vanilla Doom]] was 8, but ZDoom allows for a lot more. If the value is too low, audio glitches may happen when several sounds are played simultaneously as the older channels are freed before the sound finished playing.


*'''{{LE|Sound in Background}}''' (On/Off)
:{{c|{{CVAR|S|i_soundinbackground}}}}
:Controls whether or not to let the sound and music to continue playing in the background if the program's window loses focus.


*'''{{LE|Restart sound}}'''
:{{c|{{CCMD|O|snd_reset}}}}
:Calls a [[console command]] to reset the sound system. Some options do not take effect immediately when changed and need this to be applied.

*'''{{LE|OpenAL options}}'''
:Opens the [[OpenAL options]] menu.


*'''{{LE|Advanced options}}'''
:{{c|{{CCMD|O|menu_advsound}}}}
:Opens a [[Advanced sound options|submenu]] allowing to fine-tune the sound configuration settings.
*'''{{LE|Module replayer options}}'''
:{{c|{{CCMD|O|menu_modreplayer}}}}
:Opens a [[Module replayer options|submenu]] allowing to configure the [[module replayer]].
[[Category:Menus]]</text>
    <sha1>6wh0rsjexujjh8r3bcctkucgqywzhpv</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>