<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>ZDoom Strife Dialog Format</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>6119</id>
  <revision>
    <id>46339</id>
    <parentid>46338</parentid>
    <timestamp>2018-12-13T02:40:03Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Thekins</username>
      <id>987</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>Additional tweaks, fixes and content</comment>
    <origin>46339</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="3051" sha1="2e5p20mr9vxghwgyu5n2kykf0dgg1vg" xml:space="preserve">The '''ZDoom Strife Dialog Format''' is a variant of the [[Universal Strife Dialog Format]]. It is not a proper USDF dialect since it changes the semantic of the '''actor''' field from an integer into a string corresponding to the [[classes|actor class name]], resulting in a type mismatch in a strict parser. This deviation from the standard was deemed necessary to avoid forcing modders to use the {{Property|ConversationID}} property on all actors, which would also require redefining any standard actor without this property.

==Changes from USDF==
* '''Namespace:''' This ''must'' be set to "ZDoom" to switch from USDF to ZSDF.
* '''Actor:''' Now uses a class name instead of a mobj ID.
* '''Drop:''' Now uses a class name instead of a mobj ID.
* '''Item:''' Now uses a class name instead of a mobj ID.
* '''GiveItem:''' Now uses a class name instead of a mobj ID.

== New Fields ==
=== Conversation ===
* '''ID''': Allows you to still use a {{property|ConversationID}}.
* '''Class''': Override the default conversation menu class for this conversation.

=== Page ===
* '''Goodbye''': Specify a unique replacement for the default randomised Strife "Thanks, bye!" end-conversation option.
* '''Userstring''': Not used by default, but can be used to pass page-specific data to be interpreted by a custom conversation menu class.

=== Choice ===
* '''SpecialName:''' Allows the scripter to specify a special to call by name, instead of by number.

==== Require ====
A Choice block with a Require block will only become visible once the player has at least a specific amount of a specific inventory item.

* '''Item:''' The class name of the inventory item.
* '''Amount:''' The amount of that item needed for the choice to appear.

==== Exclude ====
A Choice block with an Exclude block will only become visible once the player has ''less than'' a specific amount of a specific inventory item.

* '''Item:''' The class name of the inventory item.
* '''Amount:''' The amount of that item needed for the choice to be removed from the conversation.

==Examples==

This script will let you trade your {{class|shotgun}} for a {{class|chaingun}}.

 namespace = "ZDoom";
 
 conversation
 {
     actor = "{{class|ChaingunGuy}}"; // Not a number!
     page
     {
          name = "Chaingun Guy";
          dialog = "I have a cool chaingun! I want a shotgun though...";
          choice
          {
              text = "Deal!";
              giveitem = "{{class|Chaingun}}";
              nextpage = 2;
              nomessage = "No shotgun, no chaingun!";
              cost
              {
                  item = "{{class|Shotgun}}";
                  amount = 1;
              }
          }
     }
     page
     {
          name = "Chaingun Guy";
          dialog = "I love this!";
     }
 }

==See also==
* [[DIALOGUE]]
* [[Universal Strife Dialog Format]]

==Forum threads==
* {{forum|t=26823|USDF branch question}}

==External links==
* [https://github.com/coelckers/gzdoom/blob/master/specs/usdf_zdoom.txt ZSDF specifications]
[[Category:Features]]</text>
    <sha1>2e5p20mr9vxghwgyu5n2kykf0dgg1vg</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>