<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>MAPINFO/Intermission definition</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>6180</id>
  <revision>
    <id>54198</id>
    <parentid>47161</parentid>
    <timestamp>2025-02-08T18:00:11Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Inkoalawetrust</username>
      <id>2604</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>Documented new cutscene sub-block.</comment>
    <origin>54198</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="6745" sha1="1zkftigv3j68ywkkj1hsioopdwipljj" xml:space="preserve">An Intermission definition begins with the keyword "intermission" followed by a name.

An intermission is composed of different sub-blocks, which each define a "step". When a step is finished, the intermission goes to the next step, until the end is reached. The '''Link''' properties allows to go to a different intermission instead. The '''GotoTitle''' step effectively ends the intermission.

==Intermission commands==
'''Intermission''' ''name'' { ''properties'' }
:Defines an Intermission block. 

==Intermission properties==
The following properties are supported within an Intermission definition:
{{list|Property|Description|content=
{{-|Link {{=}} &lt;name&gt;
|Links to another intermission after the end of this intermission.}}
{{-|Cast {}
|Defines a cast block as a step for the intermission. See below for cast properties.}}
{{-|Fader {}
|Defines a fader block as a step for the intermission. See below for fader properties.}}
{{-|GotoTitle {}
|Goes to the title screen. This effectively ends the intermission and the game.}}
{{-|Image {}
|Defines an image block as a step for the intermission. See below for image properties.}}
{{-|Scroller {}
|Defines a scroller block as a step for the intermission. See below for scroller properties.}}
{{-|TextScreen {}
|Defines a text screen block as a step for the intermission. See below for text screen properties.}}
{{-|Wiper {}
|Defines a wiper block as a transition between two steps in the intermission. See below for wiper properties.}}
{{-|Cutscene {} {{git|206c229}}
|Defines a cutscene block that plays a video as a step during the intermission. See below for cutscene properties.}}
}}

===Generic properties===
The following properties are supported within any sub-block:
{{list|Property|Description|content=
{{-|Background {{=}} &lt;image&gt;[, &lt;tile&gt;]
|Defines which image lump to use as the background for this intermission step. Optional parameters can be given. If ''tile'' is non-zero, the image is displayed at its resolution and tiled on the screen. If 0 or omitted, the image is stretched.}}
&lt;!-- {{-|CDMusic {{=}} &lt;track&gt;[, &lt;CDID&gt;]
|Defines which music to use during this step of the intermission if an audio CD is available in an optical drive. A CD ID can be given optionally to only play the track if the CD is the one expected.}} --&gt;
{{-|Draw {{=}} &lt;image&gt;, &lt;x&gt;, &lt;y&gt;
|Draws the specified image using the specified offsets. Coordinates for offsets range from (0, 0) for the top-left corner to (319, 199) for the bottom-right corner.}}
{{-|DrawConditional {{=}} &lt;condition&gt;, &lt;image&gt;, &lt;x&gt;, &lt;y&gt;
|As Draw, but specifies a condition for the drawing. Possible conditions include {{Class|PlayerPawn|player class}} names or '''Multiplayer'''.}}
{{-|Music {{=}} &lt;song&gt;[, &lt;order&gt;]
|Defines which music to use during this step of the intermission. For [[music format]]s which support sub-songs, an optional parameter allows to choose which to play.}}
{{-|Sound {{=}} &lt;sound&gt;
|Defines a sound to be played upon entering this intermission step.}}
{{-|Time {{=}} &lt;length&gt;
|Defines how long this step of the intermission should last. A positive value is an amount in seconds; a negative value is an amount in [[tic]]s.}}
}}

===Cast properties===
The following properties are supported within a cast sub-block:
{{list|Property|Description|content=
{{-|CastClass {{=}} &lt;name&gt;
|Defines which [[actor]] [[class]] to use for this cast call.}}
{{-|CastName {{=}} &lt;string&gt;
|Defines the string that is displayed during the cast call. If the string starts with a '''$''' character, it is interpreted as an identifier to a [[LANGUAGE]] string.}}
{{-|AttackSound {{=}} &lt;label&gt;, &lt;offset&gt;, &lt;sound&gt;
|Defines which sound to play at which moment of which attack. ''Label'' must be either "Melee" or "Missile", ''offset'' must be a positive or null value, and ''sound'' must be a logical sound name as defined in [[SNDINFO]].}}
}}

===Fader properties===
The following properties are supported within a fader sub-block:
{{list|Property|Description|content=
{{-|FadeType {{=}} &lt;type&gt;
|Defines how the fade proceeds. Possible types are '''FadeIn''' (default) and '''FadeOut'''.}}
}}

===Image properties===
Image sub-blocks have no additional properties.

===Scroller properties===
The following properties are supported within a scroller sub-block:
{{list|Property|Description|content=
{{-|Background2 {{=}} &lt;lump&gt;
|Defines the picture used for the destination screen.}}
{{-|InitialDelay {{=}} &lt;length&gt;
|Specifies how long to wait before scrolling begins. A positive value is an amount in [[tic]]s, a negative value is an amount in seconds. Default delay is '''0'''.}}
{{-|ScrollDirection {{=}} &lt;type&gt;
|Defines how the scroll proceeds. Possible directions are '''Up''', '''Down''', '''Left''' and '''Right''' (default).}}
{{-|ScrollTime {{=}} &lt;length&gt;
|Specifies how long it takes for the scroll to end. A positive value is an amount in [[tic]]s, a negative value is an amount in seconds. Default time is '''640'''.}}
}}

===TextScreen properties===
The following properties are supported within a text screen sub-block:
{{list|Property|Description|content=
{{-|Position {{=}} &lt;x&gt;, &lt;y&gt;
|Defines the position of the text. Default is (-1, -1), which means to use the values specified in the [[MAPINFO/GameInfo definition|GameInfo]] block.}}
{{-|Text {{=}} &lt;line&gt;[, [other line[, ...]]
|Use the specified text for the content of the text screen. An unlimited amount of parameters can be given, each will be its own line.}}
{{-|TextColor {{=}} &lt;value&gt;
|Specifies the color to use for the text. See the [[TEXTCOLO]] lump for more information about text colors. Default color is '''Untranslated'''.}}
{{-|TextDelay {{=}} &lt;length&gt;
|Specifies the delay to use when drawing the text. A positive value is the length in [[tic]], a negative value is the length in seconds. Default delay is '''10'''.}}
{{-|TextLump {{=}} &lt;lump&gt;
|Tells to use the given lump as the source of the text displayed by the text screen.}}
{{-|TextSpeed {{=}} &lt;value&gt;
|Specifies the speed at which the text is written on the screen. Default speed is '''2'''.}}
}}

===Wiper properties===
The following properties are supported within a wiper sub-block:
{{list|Property|Description|content=
{{-|WipeType {{=}} &lt;type&gt;
|Defines how the [[screen wipe]] proceeds. Possible types are '''Crossfade''', '''Melt''', '''Burn''' and '''Default''' (default).}}
}}

===Cutscene properties===
The following properties are supported within a cutscene sub-block:
{{:Cutscene MAPINFO properties}}

==Examples==
Example of a cast sub block using the Nitrogolem from Heretic: 
 Cast
 {
   CastClass = "MummyLeader"
   CastName = "Nitrogolem"
   AttackSound = "Missile", 1, "mummy/head"
   AttackSound = "Melee", 1, "mummy/attack2"
 }

[[Category:MAPINFO|Intermission]]</text>
    <sha1>1zkftigv3j68ywkkj1hsioopdwipljj</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>