<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Mouse options</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>6586</id>
  <revision>
    <id>37799</id>
    <parentid>35572</parentid>
    <timestamp>2014-03-31T10:18:47Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <origin>37799</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="3541" sha1="0du2ahuqhy7189z9wwqui93kf3tgmja" xml:space="preserve">{{menutrail|Main menu|Options menu}}
[[File:MouseOptions.png|thumb|The mouse options menu in [[Harmony]].]]
The '''mouse options''' menu allows as expected to change mouse-related settings. Its [[MENUDEF]] name is &lt;tt&gt;MouseOptions&lt;/tt&gt; and it can be summoned with the {{c|{{CCMD|O|menu_mouse}}}} console command.
*'''{{LE|Enable mouse}}''' (Yes/No)
:{{c|{{CVAR|C|use_mouse}}}}
:None of the other settings matter if this is set to "no".
*'''{{LE|Enable mouse in menu}}''' (No/Yes/Touchscreen-like)
:{{c|{{CVAR|C|m_use_mouse}}}}
:Allows to drive the menus with the mouse. If set to "touchscreen-like", the selection is not changed by a mouse-over.
*'''{{LE|Show back button}}''' (Off/Upper left/Upper right/Lower left/Lower right)
:{{c|{{CVAR|C|m_show_backbutton}}}}
:Displays a "back" button in the selected corner if set to a value other than "off". Clicking this button goes back up a menu, same as hitting the "escape" key with the keyboard.
*'''{{LE|Cursor}}''' (Default/Simple arrow/Doom/Heretic/Hexen/Strife/Chex/System cursor)
:{{c|{{CVAR|R|vid_cursor}}}}
:Selects the aspect of the cursor. Note that the cursor display is actually handled by the system and therefore subject to certain specific limitations; notably it cannot be larger than 32x32.


*'''{{LE|Overall sensitivity}}''' (0.5&amp;mdash;2.5, by 0.1 increments)
:{{c|{{CVAR|C|mouse_sensitivity}}}}
:Adjusts the movement speed of the cursor as compared to the movement of the actual mouse device.
*'''{{LE|Prescale mouse movement}}''' (No/Yes)
:{{c|{{CVAR|C|m_noprescale}}}}
:Prescaling increases precision of slow movement and speed of fast movement.
*'''{{LE|Smooth mouse movement}}''' (Yes/No)
:{{c|{{CVAR|C|smooth_mouse}}}}
:If this is set to "yes", abrupt changes in mouse moves are compensated for to result in a fluider movement. The effect is only noticeable if the mouse has a very low update rate.


*'''{{LE|Turning speed}}''' (0.0&amp;mdash;2.5, by 0.1 increments)
:{{c|{{CVAR|C|m_yaw}}}}
:Adjusts how fast the player viewpoint will turn horizontally when driven by mouselook.
*'''{{LE|Mouselook speed}}''' (0.0&amp;mdash;2.5, by 0.1 increments)
:{{c|{{CVAR|C|m_pitch}}}}
:Adjusts how fast the player viewpoint will turn vertically when driven by mouselook.
*'''{{LE|Forward/Backward speed}}''' (0.0&amp;mdash;2.5, by 0.1 increments)
:{{c|{{CVAR|C|m_forward}}}}
:Adjusts how fast the player pawn will move forward or backward when driven by mousemove.
*'''{{LE|Strafing speed}}''' (0.0&amp;mdash;2.5, by 0.1 increments)
:{{c|{{CVAR|C|m_side}}}}
:Adjusts how fast the player pawn will move laterally when driven by mousemove.


*'''{{LE|Always mouselook}}''' (On/Off)
:{{c|{{CVAR|C|freelook}}}}
:If set to "on", mouse movement during the game always correspond to [[free look|a change of the viewpoint]]. If set to "off", the mouse will instead cause the player avatar to move unless the "mouse look" key is held. (See [[customize controls]] about the mouse look key.)
*'''{{LE|Invert mouse}}''' (On/Off)
:{{c|{{CVAR|C|invertmouse}}}}
:When the mouse is inverted, a forward movement of the device is translated into a backward/downward movement of the cursor, player avatar or viewpoint.
*'''{{LE|Lookspring}}''' (On/Off)
:{{c|{{CVAR|C|lookspring}}}}
:If set to "on", and "always mouselook" is off, then releasing the "mouse look" key instantly centers the viewpoint on the horizontal.
*'''{{LE|Lookstrafe}}''' (On/Off)
:{{c|{{CVAR|C|lookstrafe}}}}
:When set to "on", lateral mouse movements result in the player avatar strafing instead of looking left and right.

[[Category:Menus]]</text>
    <sha1>0du2ahuqhy7189z9wwqui93kf3tgmja</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>