<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Automap</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>6598</id>
  <revision>
    <id>36290</id>
    <parentid>31754</parentid>
    <timestamp>2013-05-09T10:12:30Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Illdo</username>
      <id>108</id>
    </contributor>
    <origin>36290</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1840" sha1="5snoqkmls8rkyvljhas7mqe764dig8c" xml:space="preserve">{{doomwiki}}
The automap is a top-down representation of the level, created from the [[linedef]]s seen by the player. The [[ZDoom]] automap differs from the original from [[vanilla Doom]] on the following points:
* Lines within the player's field of view become marked as visible on the map even if the player is in automap mode
* The default automap function keys (arrow keys, +, -, f, g, etc.) can be modified
* An overlay mode is available
* The automap can be made to rotate so that the top corresponds to the direction the player is facing, rather than north
* The automap can be textured, though this require the presence (or run-time generation) of [[GL node]]s
* The colors for lines and things can be customized freely; it is possible to give different colors to secret lines or different types of things
* The map [[cheat code|cheat]] ("iddt" or equivalent) has a third level, available by typing type &lt;tt&gt;am_cheat 3&lt;/tt&gt; in the [[console]], which shows the things' bounding boxes as well
* The same cheat can optionally show keys with a different shape than a triangle to make them easier to find
* The [[AUTOPAGE]] background from [[Heretic]] and [[Hexen]] can be disabled
* Additional level information can be shown, such as the current kill/items/secrets tallies
* Lines marked as being hidden can be made to show nonetheless with the &lt;tt&gt;am_showalllines&lt;/tt&gt; [[console variable]]

Most of these features can be changed from the dedicated menu or through console variables.

==Troubleshooting==
* If on Windows systems the automap lines are thick and blurry, this is because your graphic drivers do not support antialiasing for lines. Set the {{CVAR|R|vid_hwaalines}} console variable to false for a workaround.

==See also==
* [[Automap options]]
* [[CVARs:Automap]]
* [[Map arrow]]
[[Category:Features]][[Category:Glossary]]</text>
    <sha1>5snoqkmls8rkyvljhas7mqe764dig8c</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>