<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>SECRETS</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>6603</id>
  <revision>
    <id>40027</id>
    <parentid>33618</parentid>
    <timestamp>2015-05-21T16:13:52Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Marrub</username>
      <id>2058</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>clarity, grammar, typos</comment>
    <origin>40027</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2090" sha1="agwdwmfc43nwzjbyp7gbgu0wdoowez8" xml:space="preserve">'''SECRETS''' lets you create a list of hints to help you find the [[secret]]s hidden in a level. This works with a special [[console command]], &lt;tt&gt;secret&lt;/tt&gt;, which will print these hints in different colors depending on their status; those that are found are in green, and the undiscovered ones in red.

Since all maps are listed in the same [[lump]], each map has a ini-style section header in its name. A hint begins with the &lt;tt&gt;$&lt;/tt&gt; character, followed by either an &lt;tt&gt;s&lt;/tt&gt; for a [[sector]] or a &lt;tt&gt;t&lt;/tt&gt; for a {{class|SecretTrigger|trigger}}. Then there is the sector number or trigger [[TID]], as appropriate, followed by a semi-colon &lt;tt&gt;;&lt;/tt&gt; and anything after is the hint text. 

Each section may also contain lines without any secret info associated to them. Such lines will be printed yellow.

==Example==
These hints are for the first three levels of [[Doom II]]:
 [MAP01]
 $s41;#1 In the northernmost room, you see two switches; a near one on your right, and a far one on your left.
 The one on the right opens a small area to the northeast with some armor and health. 
 $s8;#2 In the center room just south of the exit, there is a lift to the west. Go up the lift and hit space
 on the wall to the west, revealing a few imps and a switch which opens a door leading outside in the southeast
 corner of the center room, 
 $s17;#3 Outside are some imps and a shotgun. 
 $s57;#4 Once you hit the switch at the top of the lift, jump down onto the platform just east of the lift
 This will open a room with a rocket launcher to the north and east (#4).
 $s28;#5 A room with two imps and a stimpack, behind a hidden door on the south side  of the east wall of the
 center room. 
 
 [MAP02]
 $s79;#1 Just southwest of the red keycard (at the top of the steps) lies a room with blue armor. 
 
 [MAP03]
 $s67;#1 In the main room, south of the two sets of stairs and the rocket launcher, is a small outcropping with
 a ledge. You can make it over the ledge if  you run southeast at the right angle from the raised area west of
 the stairs. 

[[Category:ZDoom special lumps]]</text>
    <sha1>agwdwmfc43nwzjbyp7gbgu0wdoowez8</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>