<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Free look</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>6671</id>
  <revision>
    <id>32805</id>
    <parentid>29744</parentid>
    <timestamp>2012-05-08T14:21:04Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <origin>32805</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1948" sha1="236bjlc99zyd2j9sg9qb5asdbo7262c" xml:space="preserve">{{doomwiki}}'''Free look''' (or in a single word '''freelook''') is the ability [[ZDoom]] offers of looking up and down. Although [[Doom]] and other games directly based on Doom such as [[Chex Quest]] or [[Hacx]] did not feature free look, this was implemented in [[Heretic]], [[Hexen]] and [[Strife]] through a method known as '''[[Y-shearing]]''': the render is still performed horizontally by the engine, but the area rendered is moved away from the camera. The use of this method in vintage 2.5D engines can be identified by the simple fact that vertical lines (that is to say, the walls) remain vertical on the screen, as in {{wp|link=Perspective_(graphical)#Two-point_perspective|two-point perspective}}. This effect is often called a distortion as it does not correspond to natural perceptions. Y-shearing is also limited, in that greater the angle of the pitch from the horizontal, the larger the area to render becomes. Looking up 90° up or down with this method would be an infinite task, and is therefore not possible.

Freelook also affects how the [[sky]] is projected, resulting in the need for [[sky stretching]].

Polygonal engines, such as the [[OpenGL]] renderer offered by some [[source port]]s, allow a true free look, including straight up and down, without distortion. However, looking at extreme angles will still cause problems for the engine, notably with [[sprite]] rendering, since sprites remain strictly 2D. This issue can be addressed through [[OpenGL preferences#Sprite billboard|billboarding]], but it is merely a choice between two imperfect solutions.

Freelook can be enabled or disabled from the [[gameplay options]] menu or in a [[MAPINFO]] [[map definition]]. If enabled, it is generally used with mouse look (the [[mouse options#Always mouselook|always mouselook]] option corresponds to the &lt;tt&gt;freelook&lt;/tt&gt; [[console variable]]), but it is also possible to use keyboard look instead.

[[Category:Glossary]]</text>
    <sha1>236bjlc99zyd2j9sg9qb5asdbo7262c</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>