<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Exit Secret</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>671</id>
  <revision>
    <id>44668</id>
    <parentid>35127</parentid>
    <timestamp>2017-04-03T17:48:47Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>xlat</comment>
    <origin>44668</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2455" sha1="4hpmw75ibcj6zkyjtp6r8605y7ifwv2" xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:Exit_Secret}}
{{Special|244|pos|Exit}}
* ''pos'': Corresponds to destination player start spot arg0

==Usage==

Teleports the player to the secret map defined for this map in [[MAPINFO]] and to the player start spot whose arg0 matches ''pos''. Note that on standard Doom 1 maps, ZDoom will only use this special on maps E1M3, E2M5, E3M6 and E4M2. In Doom 2, only maps MAP15 and MAP31 will be affected by its use. This can be overridden by the use of MAPINFO.

Note that the map will not immediately exit as soon as this command is encountered; instead, a flag will be set that causes the map to exit during processing of the next [[tic]]. Therefore, if there are any further commands in the ACS script it is present in, they will be executed up until the first delay. To ensure that the script halts immediately at this command, make it the final command within its script or put a &lt;code&gt;[[terminate]]&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;[[delay]](1)&lt;/code&gt; command immediately after it.

==Examples==

It is possible to make an exit that is both normal and secret, and only goes to the secret level based on some condition, for example: How many ''tokens'' were collected&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; ''tokens'' being some sort of predefined thing that can be picked up, be it a [[DECORATE]] item or a standard doom item.

 int tokens = 0;
 
 script 1 (void)
 {
 	if (tokens == 5)
 		'''Exit_Secret'''(0);
 	else
 		[[Exit_Normal]](0);
 }
 
 script 7 (void)
 {
 	tokens++;
 	[[PrintBold]](d:tokens, s:"/5 collected!");
 }

The first script exits the level. If the player has all five tokens, the next level will be the secret level. Otherwise they will have missed it and are sent to the next level.

The script numbered 7 is set activate upon each of the token's specials. That is, make their thing special to be [[ACS_Execute]] and the arguments to be (7, 0, 0, 0, 0). When a thing is picked up, its special is activated, so these five items will add to the token count and allow the secret level to be reached.

== Conversions from linedef types ==
The following Doom map format types can be converted as Exit_Secret:
{| {{prettytable}}
!Type!!Conversion!!Trigger
|-
|{{icon|Doom}} 51:S1 Exit (Secret) || Exit_Secret (0) || Player Use
|-
|{{icon|Heretic}} 105:W1 Exit (Secret) || Exit_Secret (0) || Player Cross
|-
|{{icon|Doom}} 124:W1 Exit (Secret) || Exit_Secret (0) || Player Cross
|-
|{{icon|Boom}} 198:G1 Exit (Secret) || Exit_Secret (0) || Attack Hit, Missile Cross
|}</text>
    <sha1>4hpmw75ibcj6zkyjtp6r8605y7ifwv2</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>