<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Technophobia Overdose</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>6753</id>
  <revision>
    <id>29991</id>
    <timestamp>2010-12-26T22:14:44Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>page</comment>
    <origin>29991</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1688" sha1="2ztgkun8fyza52dfmd63b9nf1m9f4xr" xml:space="preserve">[[File:Technophobia01.png|thumb|Huge façade, tiny courtyard.]]{{wad
|author = [[User:§-Morpheus-§|Remmirath]]
|iwad = Doom2
|type = s
|status = Released
|link = {{idgames|id=15631}}
}}
[[File:Technophobia02.png|thumb|The main generator.]]
'''Technophobia Overdose''' is Remmirath's first solo mod (earlier works were contributions to team-based mods, such as the [[Ten Community Project]]. As such, it was also developed as a way to learn many tricks of [[ZDoom]] modding, which can be apparent in the way some features are used, in a single area, seemingly just so as to be used, rather than because they would logically fit in the level. The level architecture also suffers a bit from this "completed tutorial" effect, featuring sometimes gratuitous detailing that does not make much sense. The custom monsters, however, are used correctly; better employed in fact than some of the stock monsters.

''Technophobia Overdose'' presents you with a vast "techbase" complex where you will have to find all three keycards, recover a five-digit passcode, start secondary generators, and disengage the master lock just so as to escape from it. The gameplay is relatively easy and rather linear, with however a few high points. Overall, ''Technophobia'' is good source of inspiration and examples for mapping techniques, but the gameplay itself is rather average. If taken as a playable tech demo, it is a rather enjoyable creation; and it is certainly a good way to quickly survey and experiment a few of the features available in ZDoom mapping.

[[File:Technophobia03.png|thumb|Detailing is often very intricate.]]
==Forum threads==
* {{Forum|t=19273|Development thread}} on the ZDoom forum</text>
    <sha1>2ztgkun8fyza52dfmd63b9nf1m9f4xr</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>