<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Secret</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>6787</id>
  <revision>
    <id>52903</id>
    <parentid>47766</parentid>
    <timestamp>2024-08-16T08:18:22Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <origin>52903</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2369" sha1="2qr7nc9uavt5vwjbl3i56rdphlojla0" xml:space="preserve">{{doomwiki}}
A '''secret''' is something, usually a [[sector]] but sometimes an [[actor]] or a scripted event, which is tallied on the [[intermission]] screen.

[[Vanilla Doom]] secrets are always sectors with the [[sector special]] 9. [[Boom]] added a "secret flag" in the sector special allowing to combine it with other effects by adding the value 128 to said other effect. In [[UDMF]] and [[Hexen format]], the secret flag for sectors is instead 1024, this change was required to support more sector special types.

Sector-based secrets are triggered when the player is standing on the ground; this is handled by the same function that also handles other sector effects applying to the player, such as [[damaging floor]]s. For the same reason, if a control sector of a non-solid 3D floor is marked as secret, entering the volume of the 3D floor will trigger the secret.

[[ZDoom]] allows scripted secrets with the {{Class|SecretTrigger}} actor. The secret is considered found when the secret trigger is activated, generally by a script. A {{Class|SectorAction}} effect can be used to run the script that will in turn activate the SecretTrigger.

More recently was added the ability to mark [[things]] as secret in UDMF by setting its "countsecret" spawn flag to true. It is also possible, but not advised, to give actors the {{Flag|COUNTSECRET}} flag, which will make them always secret wherever they are placed. Things marked as secret with either of these methods will be found when picked up; so only [[inventory]] [[actor]]s should ever be flagged as secret.

A [[SECRETS]] [[lump]] can be provided in a mod to help find secrets. The {{c|secret}} [[console command]] will list the secrets declared for this level in this lump, if any, and will also color-code those found in green and in red those not found.

==Secret sound==
When discovering a secret, ZDoom will play the "misc/secret" sound. ''[[Strife]]'' provides a sound for this, {{c|DSYEAH}}, but the other classic games do not and ZDoom maps this sound to its own {{c|DSSECRET}} sound lump. This sound was created by [[User:Marisa Heit|Randi]] from {{forum|p=25591|samples from a forgotten MOD file}}.

==Secret message==
The string displayed when a secret is found has the identifier {{c|SECRETMESSAGE}}. Its default value, "A secret is revealed!", comes from the game ''Blood''.
[[Category:Glossary]]</text>
    <sha1>2qr7nc9uavt5vwjbl3i56rdphlojla0</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>