<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Configuration file</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>6804</id>
  <revision>
    <id>52684</id>
    <parentid>52683</parentid>
    <timestamp>2024-05-19T12:35:48Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Jekyll Grim Payne</username>
      <id>2175</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>/* Windows */</comment>
    <origin>52684</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1812" sha1="14wixany58ba5oy8ljnhudyyvcfnh6u" xml:space="preserve">{{stub}}

The '''configuration file''' used by [[ZDoom]] and [[GZDoom]] is an INI file that contains configuration settings for ZDoom/GZDoom. It is frequently referred to as just '''zdoom.ini'''/'''gzdoom.ini''' or '''the ini file''' when the context is clear.

The {{param|-config}} [[command line parameter]] lets you use a different configuration file from the one used by default.

== Windows ==
=== Name ===
The configuration file is named {{c|gzdoom-&lt;username&gt;.ini}} (or {{c|zdoom-&lt;username&gt;.ini}} for [[ZDoom]]) where {{c|&lt;username&gt;}} is the username of the player in their operating system.

=== Location ===
[[ZDoom]] is a {{wp|Portable_application|portable application}}, so its ini file is stored in the game's folder. This is true for [[GZDoom]] before 4.9.0 as well.

Starting with '''4.9.0''' [[GZDoom]] comes in portable and non-portable variants, which affect where the ini file is stored:
* Portable: same as ZDoom, the ini is stored in GZDoom's folder.
* Non-portable: the ini is placed in &lt;code&gt;Documents/My Games/GZDoom&lt;/code&gt; by default. A portable ini can be created forcefully, by first creating a file called {{c|gzdoom_portable.ini}} in GZDoom's folder. If you still have an old INI in your folder, GZDoom will ask what to do with it, you can either move it to the user folder or convert to a portable install.

This was done to bring handling in line with current guidelines and to make it easier for commercial games that often get installed into a folder without write access.

The &lt;tt&gt;.ini&lt;/tt&gt; extension may be hidden if the default setting of letting the Explorer hide known file extensions is kept.

== Linux ==

The default location of the configuration file is &lt;tt&gt;/home/&lt;user&gt;/.config/zdoom/zdoom.ini&lt;/tt&gt;.

[[Category:ZDoom]]
[[Category:GZDoom]]
[[Category:Technical aspects]]</text>
    <sha1>14wixany58ba5oy8ljnhudyyvcfnh6u</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>