<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>StrParam</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>6964</id>
  <revision>
    <id>45949</id>
    <parentid>45948</parentid>
    <timestamp>2018-03-20T18:22:53Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Matt</username>
      <id>135</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>/* Usage */ - hopefully this will make this page show up on a search for "acs string"</comment>
    <origin>45949</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1982" sha1="19ngnj3lkxsx0555e9n79980fgm1yac" xml:space="preserve">int '''StrParam'''(''item(s)'');

==Usage==

'''StrParam''' will create a new string formatted based upon the same method for [[print]] or [[log]]. This string will only exist for 1 tic, so a [[delay]] will nullify it. As of revision {{rev|4295}}, strings generated by '''StrParam''', [[GetCVarString]] and [[GetUserCVarString]] will last for as long as they need to, rather than for 1 tic.

This can be used to concatenate multiple ACS strings.

==Return Value==

The return value is the string table index of the new string.

{{WarnIndeterminate|If string [[Print#Cast_type|cast types]] l, k, or n are used, the resulting string may vary based on client settings. Typically this will not cause issues unless the result in combined with some other [[:Category:ACS String operations|string operation]] and that is used to affect the playsim.}}

==Example==

 str mapname = "hangar";
 
 script 3 enter
 {
 // you can also assign it to a variable,
 // but its contents are only valid until this tick ends if you are
 // using a version prior to revision 4295
     int keyObject = strparam(s:mapname, s:"key"); // would create "hangarkey"
     if (CheckInventory(keyObject))
     {
         TakeInventory(keyObject, 1);
     }
     else
     {
         print(s:"You require ", s:keyObject);
         terminate; // after ending the script, you cannot expect the value in keyObject to point to a valid string anymore
                    // on versions prior to r4295
     }
     ACS_Execute(120,0,10);
     // ACS_Execute will not execute code during this tick.
     // keyObject will not exist anymore when it starts running script 120.
     // if you are using a version prior to r4295
 
     delay(1); // now a tick will pass. any dynamic strings generated before this delay will be invalid once execution resumes on
               // versions prior to r4295
     /*
         no keyObject here on pre-r4295
     */
 }

[[category:ACS HUD functions]] [[category:ACS String operations]]</text>
    <sha1>19ngnj3lkxsx0555e9n79980fgm1yac</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>