<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>The Stick Figure</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>7007</id>
  <revision>
    <id>38468</id>
    <parentid>37832</parentid>
    <timestamp>2014-11-02T03:09:31Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Lightman68</username>
      <id>1725</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <origin>38468</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="3253" sha1="lzg3in2w8agneyqtgedwiebclj0ptdx" xml:space="preserve">{{Wad
 | name = The Stick Figure
 | author = Lightman68
 | iwad = Chex3
 | status = Abandoned
}}



&lt;nowiki&gt;Zdoom version is 2.3.1&lt;/nowiki&gt;


----

'''This WAD has discontinued in development.'''

----


== Description ==
'''The Stick Figure''' is a total doom conversion modified from Chex Quest 3's resources. The WAD contains its own Sprites, Textures, Flats, Music, and Maps. The player is a stick figure that needs to kill all enemies and the "Boss" in order to save stickkind. The player would be killing his own people, but hypnotized by the "Boss". Levels are mostly based on escaping a prison, followed by rushing through urban county areas, and infiltrating the "Boss"'s Base.

== Story ==
You have been caught not being under control by a certain robot. This robot is a high-class robot. Scientists and Technicians programed the robot to take orders. Once the scientists have made sure it was ok, they tested it out. The high-class robot worked fine. But 3 mad scientists were curious. The 3 sabotaged the robot, and programed it to give out orders, but it malfunctioned. The robot sent out a massive psychic wave across a huge landscape, and all who were caught in it were in the robots control. It's control. The Nightmare's control...

== Pictures ==

[[File:File-Screenshot_Chex_20110810_162750.png]]
&lt;nowiki&gt;An enemy stick figure hurting the player&lt;/nowiki&gt;

----
[[File:File-Screenshot_Chex_20110630_104209.png]]
&lt;nowiki&gt;The player shooting enemies in E1M4&lt;/nowiki&gt;

----

== Development ==
This WAD is not finished yet, so some Chex Quest 3 textures still are in it. Some Doom stuff was copied and put in this WAD, but soon, the WAD will have its own un-copied stuff.

== Completed ==
Episode 1 of this WAD is complete and playable. A demo might release for people to test out.

'''E1M1:''' "''The Jail''"

'''E1M2:''' "''Breaking Out''"

'''E1M3:''' "''Sewer Pipes''"

'''E1M4:''' "''Refinery''"

'''E1M5:''' "''Stronghold''"
== Latest Pictures ==
While the author has been modifying and editing this WAD further, here are some screenshots that show how the wad has changed.

[[File:File-Screenshot_Chex_20110827_150440.png]]
&lt;nowiki&gt;The Weapons have been changed, and so did the player's HUD&lt;/nowiki&gt;

----
[[File:File-Screenshot_Chex_20110827_150446.png]]
&lt;nowiki&gt;Here, the same enemy stick figure is being shot at by the player&lt;/nowiki&gt;

----
[[File:File-Screenshot_Chex_20110827_150507.png]]
&lt;nowiki&gt;The enemy stick figure is shot to death by the player&lt;/nowiki&gt;

----

== Player HUD ==
[[File:File-stats.png]]
== Demo Pictures ==
[[File:E1M1.png]]&lt;nowiki&gt; *E1M1&lt;/nowiki&gt;

[[File:E1M2.png]]&lt;nowiki&gt; *E1M2&lt;/nowiki&gt;

[[File:E1M3.png]]&lt;nowiki&gt; *E1M3&lt;/nowiki&gt;

[[File:E1M4.png]]&lt;nowiki&gt; *E1M4&lt;/nowiki&gt;

[[File:E1M5.png]]&lt;nowiki&gt; *E1M5&lt;/nowiki&gt;

----

== Latest Information ==
- HUD bars have been shortened half size

- E1M5 has it's own music now

- Pain &amp; Death sounds added from All out War 2 WAD

- Maps Enhanced

- Some sounds are not from the author

- Player has original doomplayer sounds

- Enhanced Pain/Death Actions

- New Blood Physics

----

- DEMO PUBLISHED

----

- Better Texture Graphics

- Highly detailed Weapon sprites.

- E1M1 Is now unplayable. It was replaced with a quick clip.

----

- WAD DISCONTINUED

----</text>
    <sha1>lzg3in2w8agneyqtgedwiebclj0ptdx</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>