<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Half Life total Conversion</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>7064</id>
  <revision>
    <id>38203</id>
    <parentid>38202</parentid>
    <timestamp>2014-08-25T04:00:31Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <origin>38203</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1940" sha1="97oot439l2rqv4lwb1vg7y2kky07wj0" xml:space="preserve">{{Wad
 | name = Half Life Total Conversion (aka Half Life: Doom Edition)
 | author = Gabriel "Fellowzdoomer" Schlegel
 | iwad = Doom2
 | type = t
 | status = Abandoned
 | link = None
 }}

== Description ==
Half Life Total conversion -- or Half Life: Doom Edition -- Is exactly what the title\subtitle says!
After making it up to Chapter 15 of Half Life -- Xen -- I got an idea...Sure, someone  tried to make a Half Life Doom Mod, but it didnt quite have that feeling to it.

== Features ==

•New Weapons

•New Enemies

•New Textures

•New Everything! Except 3D Floors


I managed with some ACS to make the following

•Checking what the player decided on the GMAN Level

•Saying the name of a chapter when you advance

•The "Science Gone Wrong" Part actually wipes you out and takes -6 health away

•And Many More!

==Episodes==

As of currently there'll be 3 episodes:

•Half-Life TC

•Half-Life 1 And A ½ - After G-MAN sends you on your way, Gordon Freeman gets stuck between Black Mesa and Citadel 17. Just smack in the middle of them both and the Combine and Military are chasing you.

•Eli is Alive - This is more of a Half-Life 2 Episode 3 thing. After Alyx Vance grieves the death of her dad, Eli Vance, Gordon Freeman and Alyx Vance go to Antarctica to dish out revenge. But Eli really is alive. Just in a coma. When G-MAN revives him, an accidental experiment blows him way back to before the Great Black Mesa Accident. Worse, Eli must be unseen or else it'll affect the future and his life. But the Military seem obsessed with capturing Eli and young Alyx, but what the Military - and Alyx - don't get - or understand - is that once they're all captured, the Military,  Alyx and the world'll end thus killing all of humanity.

== Progress of Sunday, August 24, 2014==
Due to recent events of mine, this project has gone dead. I only have an Android phone now, so until I get a computer, this project is dust.</text>
    <sha1>97oot439l2rqv4lwb1vg7y2kky07wj0</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>