<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>StatusBar</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>7137</id>
  <revision>
    <id>32003</id>
    <timestamp>2012-03-06T14:36:04Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>page creation</comment>
    <origin>32003</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1972" sha1="rw35qixsy65i32trvjjq27c1tf5lmjb" xml:space="preserve">{{sbarinfo|&lt;stbar&gt; [, &lt;flags&gt;...] [, &lt;alpha&gt;]}}
Begins the drawing routine for the specified [[status bar]].  Valid values for {{c|stbar}} are:
;None:Draws where there is supposed to be no status bar. Should be used sparingly.
;Fullscreen:[[ZDoom]]'s fullscreen [[HUD]].
;Normal:Standard status bar.
;Automap:Used for ''[[Hexen]]''-style [[automap]] status bars.
;Inventory:Inventory bar drawn over the Normal status bar.
;InventoryFullscreen:Inventory bar drawn over the fullscreen HUD.
;PopupLog:''[[Strife]]''-style popup for the log.
;PopupKeys:''Strife''-style popup for [[key]]s.
;PopupStatus:''Strife''-style popup for health and accuracy statistics.

{{c|Flags}} are as follows: 
;forcescaled:Forces the status bar to be scaled even if the user has scaling off.  This flag is ignored on the Inventory and InventoryFullscreen bars.
;fullscreenoffsets:[[Image:Sbarinfo sheet.png|thumb|200 px|right|FullScreenOffset reference sheet]]Changes the coordinate system to be relative to a corner of the screen. Using positive or negative values will change which side of the screen the offset is from: a positive x value is from the left, a negative one is from the right; a positive y value is from the top, and a negative one from the bottom. For example, a y coordinate of 32 will position the bar 32 pixels from the top of the screen, while a y coordinate of -32 will position it 32 pixels from the bottom.
:For any coordinate on a bar using fullscreenoffsets, you may add "center" to the coordinate to center it along that axis.  For example "-16 + center" on an X coordinate would mean 16 pixels left of center.  Due to current limitations "+ center" must come after the integer value.
:'''Note:''' Using fullscreenoffsets breaks the Height parameter and makes it seem too tall in most cases. Because of this, it is not recommended to use fullscreenoffsets on "Normal" status bars.
{{c|Alpha}} is a value from 0.0 to 1.0 with 0.0 being invisible and 1.0 being opaque.</text>
    <sha1>rw35qixsy65i32trvjjq27c1tf5lmjb</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>