<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>DrawNumber</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>7140</id>
  <revision>
    <id>45089</id>
    <parentid>44481</parentid>
    <timestamp>2017-05-02T14:06:12Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Blue Shadow</username>
      <id>2021</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>Remove {{new}}</comment>
    <origin>45089</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="3649" sha1="jo3pyip12152x9vgsv301ghuhlj3e3h" xml:space="preserve">{{sbarinfo|&lt;size&gt;, &lt;&lt;nowiki&gt;font&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;, &lt;color&gt;, &lt;value&gt;, [flags, ...,] &lt;x&gt;, &lt;y&gt; [, &lt;fontspacing&gt;] [, &lt;low_color&gt;, &lt;low_value&gt; [, &lt;high_color&gt;, &lt;high_value&gt;]]}}
Draws a number at the specified location. The first argument specifies the size of the number in digits (Doom's statusbar is set to size 3, for three-digit numbers). The [[font]] must be a ZDoom font or defined in [[FONTDEFS]].  The font will be translated to {{c|color}}, which can be a color defined in [[TEXTCOLO]]. {{c|Fontspacing}} will put the specified amount of pixels between each character (default is 0).  If a {{c|low_color}} is provided, then that color will be used if the value is less than or equal to {{c|low_value}}.  If a  {{c|high_color}}} is provided then that color will be used when the value is greater than or equal to {{c|high_value}}.

For value, you can either supply a constant number, an inventory item, or one of the following:
;Health:The player's current health level.
;Accuracy:Amount of accuracy upgrades received.
;Armor:The amount of armor the player is currently carrying.
;ArmorClass:Draws the {{Class|HexenArmor|''Hexen'' armor class}} of the player.
;Ammo1:The amount of primary ammo for the current weapon.
;Ammo2:The amount of secondary ammo for the current weapon.
;Frags:The number of frags the player has achieved.
;Keys:The number of keys picked up.
;Kills:The number of monsters that have been killed.
;Monsters:The total number of monsters in the map.
;Items:Number of items picked up.
;TotalItems:Total number of items in the map.
;SavePercent:Indicates the percentage of damage absorbed by armor.
;Secrets:Number of secrets found.
;Score:Current player score (see [[ACS actor properties|APROP_Score]] and {{Class|ScoreItem}})
;Stamina:Amount of stamina upgrades received.
;TotalSecrets:Total number of secrets in the map.
;AirTime:The player's remaining air supply (in seconds) when underwater.
;Ammo &lt;AmmoType&gt;:The amount of the specified ammo the player is holding.
;AmmoCapacity &lt;AmmoType&gt;:The maximum amount of the specified ammo the player can hold.
;Ammo1Capacity:The maximum amount of primary ammo the player can hold for the current weapon.
;Ammo2Capacity:The maximum amount of secondary ammo the player can hold for the current weapon.
;PowerupTime &lt;[[Classes:PowerupGiver|PowerupGiver]]&gt;:Displays the amount of time left for a given powerup.
;GlobalVar &lt;num&gt;:Prints the specified global variable in acs.
;GlobalArray &lt;num&gt;:Prints the value in a global array with the index of the playernumber.
;IntCvar &lt;num&gt;: Prints the cvar specified. Can be a server/user int or bool.

{{c|Flags}} are:
;alignment({left|center|right}):Changes the alignment of the string.
;fillzeros:Fills the number up to size with zeros.  If the number is negative the negative sign will take the first digit's position and the size will be changed accordingly.
;whennotzero:Only draws the number if the value is not zero.
;drawshadow[(&lt;xOffset&gt;, &lt;yOffset&gt;)]:Draws a translucent shadow effect under the number. If offsets are not given, it defaults to two pixels to the right and two pixels down.
;interpolate(&lt;speed&gt;):Interpolates the value drawn.
;dontcap:Draws the lower digits of the number instead of capping.
;prefix(value, pad):Prefixes the number with the specified strings.  The value part can be anything that drawstring accepts, but the pad must be a string.  When not using a constant for the value part drawstring's caching functionality is disabled.

Also keep in mind that for DrawNumber and [[DrawString]], text will be right-justified, so coordinates specified should be the ''rightmost'' portion and not the leftmost like with images.</text>
    <sha1>jo3pyip12152x9vgsv301ghuhlj3e3h</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>