<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Polymost</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>7189</id>
  <revision>
    <id>49042</id>
    <parentid>47723</parentid>
    <timestamp>2022-03-06T19:51:10Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Hirogen2</username>
      <id>12</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>add name of the new 3point renderer</comment>
    <origin>49042</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1778" sha1="og5h6ghdvjefnogf20bkfh9dn8jdqae" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Polymost01.png|right|thumb|230px|Wireframe mode.]][[Image:Polymost02.png|right|thumb|230px|Solid colors mode.]]'''Polymost''' is a software and OpenGL renderer developed by {{wp|Ken Silverman}} as a replacement for the [[Build]] engine. From December 2004 to February 2005, Randy worked on adding the software rendering parts of Polymost to [[ZDoom]]. After remaining a decade in unfinished form, it was removed in 2014 ({{cs|bbc3b69}}), so ZDoom 2.7.1 is the last released version of ZDoom containing this feature. GZDoom 3.0 added a new software-based 3-point renderer (without the [[Y-shearing]] when looking up and down), [[SoftPoly]].

The Polymost renderer in ZDoom could only render world geometry, either in wireframe or in solid colors. It could be tested by setting {{c|r_polymost}} to 1 (wireframe), 2 (solid colors with wireframe) or 3 (solid colors without wireframe) in the console. 

Note that:
#It was overlaid on the software renderer output. In wireframe mode, it was still playable; but in solid colors mode, the polygons masked the normal view entirely, rendering actors invisible.
#Since it was part of the software renderer, if you use the [[OpenGL]] renderer from [[GZDoom]] or [[Skulltag]], this would have had no effect.

The two screenshots illustrate the difference between Doom's horizontal projection and the true 3D perspective of polymost.

[[Image:Polymost03.png|right|thumb|230px|Global tilt angle.]]One other console variable affected the polymost rendering: {{c|gtang}}. It corresponded to the global tilt angle, in {{wp|radian|radians}}. Positive values tilted the angle clockwise, negative values tilted it counter-clockwise. With an approximation of π (positive or negative), the projection was upside-down.

[[Category:Nostalgia]]</text>
    <sha1>og5h6ghdvjefnogf20bkfh9dn8jdqae</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>