<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Poison</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>7211</id>
  <revision>
    <id>32500</id>
    <timestamp>2012-04-28T15:25:05Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>page creation</comment>
    <origin>32500</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2982" sha1="6mq6w70oj411ccp2jk7w37eq1unjoca" xml:space="preserve">There are several types of '''poisons''' in [[ZDoom]]. 

Attacks from [[monster]]s or [[weapon]]s can cause poison damage. Such damage is not inflicted in one go, but drain the victim's health over a period of time. Standard poison damage, as used in ''[[Hexen]]'' ({{Class|CWeapStaff|serpent staff}}, {{Class|PoisonCloud|poison cloud}}) only affects the player, and monsters are instead hurt by normal damage from these attacks; however it is possible in ZDoom to create poison damage that affects monsters in the same way as players, with the {{Property|PoisonDamage}} property on a [[projectile]] or [[puff]]. The flags {{Flag|ADDITIVEPOISONDAMAGE}} and {{Flag|ADDITIVEPOISONDURATION}} can also be used. While poisoned, a player's screen is affected by a greenish [[palette flash]], the intensity of which depends on the severity of the poison.

Certain [[sector type]]s originating from ''[[Strife]]'' can also cause poisoning. Instead of regularly inflicting damage while the player is inside as others [[damaging floor]]s do, sector types 105 and 116 increase a player's "hazard counter", by two or four points respectively, for every tic that player remains in the poisoning sector. This hazard counter is itself decreased by one point every tic until it reaches zero (so, while a player remains in a poison sector, the counter actually increases by one or three points). Once the hazard count reaches 560 (after 16 seconds of accumulation in type 105, or 5 seconds and 12 [[tic]]s in type 116), the player is inflicted five points of slime damage every 32 tics. This damage will persist as long as the hazard count remains above 560, so a severely poisoned player can suffer from damage even after exiting the poisoning sector. Protective items such as the {{Class|RadSuit}} or {{Class|EnvironmentalSuit}} protect against this poisoning effect. While poisoned, a player's screen is affected by a greenish [[palette flash]] using the same color as the ''[[Doom]]'' RadSuit blending.

''Strife'' also features a {{Class|StrifeCrossbow2|crossbow}} that shoots poisoned bolts. This does not correspond to an actual poison as far as the game system is concerned; instead the {{Class|PoisonBolt}} instantly kills any non-boss enemy with blood. Enemies with the {{Flag|NOBLOOD}} flag are entirely immune, and enemies with the {{Flag|BOSS}} flag (but not NOBLOOD) are merely inflicted 50 points of normal damage.

==See also==
* [[A_PoisonBagInit]]
* {{Flag|ADDITIVEPOISONDAMAGE}} and {{Flag|ADDITIVEPOISONDURATION}} flags
* {{Class|ArtiPoisonBag}} and specifically {{Class|ArtiPoisonBag1}}
* {{Class|CWeapStaff}} and {{Class|CStaffMissile}}
* [[Damage types]] and [[custom damage types]]
* {{Class|PoisonBolt}}, {{Class|PoisonBolts}} and {{Class|StrifeCrossbow2}}
* {{Class|PoisonCloud}}
* {{Property|PoisonDamage}} and {{Property|PoisonDamageType}} properties
* {{Class|PowerIronFeet}} and {{Class|PowerMask}}
* {{Class|ZPoisonShroom}}


[[Category:Features]][[Category:Glossary]]</text>
    <sha1>6mq6w70oj411ccp2jk7w37eq1unjoca</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>