<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>A ShedShard</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>7321</id>
  <revision>
    <id>32698</id>
    <parentid>32683</parentid>
    <timestamp>2012-05-05T21:28:48Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Blzut3</username>
      <id>413</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>Missing function protocol</comment>
    <origin>32698</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1663" sha1="enovmo6lzhxvn0axygjbb1q53gqhj80" xml:space="preserve">{{Codepointer|r=Hexen|Spawn}}
'''A_ShedShard'''&lt;br&gt;
(''no parameter'')&lt;br&gt;

Creates new {{Class|FrostMissile}}s if the calling actor's {{c|special2}} counter is greater than zero. The direction in which these new missiles will be spawned depend on {{c|special1}}, used as a flag array:
*1: Left
*2: Right
*4: Up
*8: Down
If {{c|special1}} is 15, four new missiles will be created. In any case, the newly-created missiles will have their {{c|special2}} set to one less than the calling actor's, and their first argument set to 2 or 0 depending on whether the calling actor's {{c|special2}} is 3 or not. The spawned missiles share the calling actor's {{c|target}}. Other aspects depend on the spawned missile's direction:

;Left and right:
:A new missile is created at the calling actor's position, going at a horizontal angle of 5° in the appropriate direction. The new missile's {{c|special1}} is set to only left or right, as appropriate. Its vertical velocity is the same as the calling actor's, but its horizontal velocity depends on the calling actor's {{c|special2}}, using this formula:
::''velocity = 20 + 2 * ({{c|special2}} - 1)''

;Up and down:
:A new missile is created eight map units above or below the calling actor. The new missile's {{c|special1}} is set to up or down as appropriate, as well as left and right if the calling actor's {{c|special2}} is an even number. Its vertical velocity is the same as the calling actor's, but its horizontal velocity depends on the calling actor's {{c|special2}}, using this formula:
::''velocity = 15 + 2 * ({{c|special2}} - 1)''

This codepointer is restricted to {{Class|FrostMissile}} and derived classes.</text>
    <sha1>enovmo6lzhxvn0axygjbb1q53gqhj80</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>