<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Earthquake</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>7423</id>
  <revision>
    <id>44237</id>
    <parentid>41173</parentid>
    <timestamp>2017-03-20T13:09:03Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>removing "new" for GZDoom 2.4.0 release</comment>
    <origin>44237</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1875" sha1="tlrwgpldpuiquuhto5zvtcup7ajhj76" xml:space="preserve">'''Earthquakes''' are a feature introduced to the Doom engine by ''[[Hexen]]''. However, the implementation in [[ZDoom]] predates the release of Raven Software's source code, and as a result the earthquake code in ZDoom is completely different from its equivalent in ''Hexen''.

Earthquakes can be created with the following functions:
* [[A_QuakeEx]] (decorate) or [[QuakeEx]] (ACS)
* [[A_Quake]] (an [[action function]]: can only be used in [[DECORATE]])
* [[Radius_Quake]] (an [[action special]]: can be used anywhere)
* [[Radius_Quake2]] (an [[ACS function]]: can only be used in [[ACS]])

Earthquakes shake the [[player]]'s [[camera]]. Every [[tic]], they inflict 1d8 damage to actors within their damage radius and thrust them in a random direction with a force equal to half their intensity.

Earthquakes also play a continuous sound as long as they are rumbling. By default, this sound is the one defined in [[SNDINFO]] as "world/quake"; however both [[A_Quake]] and [[Radius_Quake2]] allow to specify a different sound.

The camera shaking effect is subject to {{c|{{CVAR|R|r_quakeintensity}}}}.

Earthquakes can be manipulated to shake along the axis relative to the player with [[A_QuakeEx]], can be scaled up and/or down to cause intensifying effects, and can have intensities set on each individual planes for maximum customizability.

Earthquakes can be set to a different type of quake, using sine waves instead of random jittering. These can be controlled further with the use of [[A_QuakeEx]]'s parameters to adjust the number of waves per second, allowing more realistic quakes to be defined. Unlike the regular quakes, these also operate based on the current in-game tic to preserve the current offset. These quakes are always overridden by the newest wave quake generated after it.

[[Category:Features]][[Category:Glossary]][[Category:Technical aspects]]</text>
    <sha1>tlrwgpldpuiquuhto5zvtcup7ajhj76</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>