<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>UniqueTID</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>7461</id>
  <revision>
    <id>40890</id>
    <parentid>37725</parentid>
    <timestamp>2016-02-06T06:52:49Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Jpalomo</username>
      <id>1715</id>
    </contributor>
    <origin>40890</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1745" sha1="deo7r3gq32pwmqbmq8u7j8iyn291qvc" xml:space="preserve">__NOTOC__


int '''UniqueTID''' ([int tid[, int limit]])

== Usage ==
Returns a new [[TID]] that is not currently used by any actors.

=== Parameters ===

* ''tid'': Starting value from which to check. It has two modes of operation:
#If tid is non-zero, then it checks TIDs one-by-one starting at the given tid until it finds a free one. 
#If tid is zero, then it returns a completely random TID.
* ''limit'': Specifies the number of attempts to make to find a free TID. If limit is non-zero, then it will only check that many times for a free TID, so it might not find a free one. If no free TID is found, 0 is returned. If limit is zero, then the search is effectively unlimited.

=== Return value ===
0 if no free TID is found, a positive value corresponding to an unused TID otherwise.

== Examples ==

This example is part of the code that can be used to see through the "eyes" of a missile(akin to Unreal Tournament's Redeemer)
It is called in the Spawn state of the missile.
 script "CameraRocket" (void)
 {
      int MissileID = [[UniqueTID]](); // Get a random TID, it is sure that it will not use an already used one.
      [[Thing_ChangeTID]](0, MissileID); // Set that TID to the fired missile
      [[SetActivatorToTarget]](MissileID); // Use the target to select the player who fired this missile
      [[ChangeCamera]](MissileID, 0, 0); // Set the camera for the player
      [[SetPlayerProperty]](0, ON, PROP_Frozen); // Don't let the player move
      [[Thing_ChangeTID]](MissileID, 0); // Remove the TID from the missile, as it is no longer needed.
 }
Note that the above function does not include turning of the missile based on the view angle or unfreezing the player when it explodes.

[[category:ACS Information functions]]</text>
    <sha1>deo7r3gq32pwmqbmq8u7j8iyn291qvc</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>