<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Russian Overkill</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>7521</id>
  <revision>
    <id>50370</id>
    <parentid>36898</parentid>
    <timestamp>2023-07-07T10:23:20Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Dynamo</username>
      <id>2607</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <origin>50370</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2045" sha1="qov3386zbw2pfj9eiu2ze9gystrapk4" xml:space="preserve">{{doomwiki}}{{wad
| author = PillowBlaster
| year = 2012
| iwad = Doom2
| caco = 19
| category = "Best Gameplay Mod"
| status = Released
| link = {{forum|t=29915|Russian Overkill}} and {{forum|t=32978|Reinforcements from Moldova}}
| type = w
}}

'''Russian Overkill''', sometimes called RO for short, is a mod by PillowBlaster, designed primarily in mind with GZDoom. Primary function of RO is providing users with multiple weapons that are usually slighlty humorous, absurdal, and last but not least powerful. According to PillowBlaster, balancing wasn't considered while the mod was created.

As of June 25th, 2013, mod is considered content complete and any further updates will probably be bugfix-based.

== Features ==

RO contains slightly less than 50 weapons, varying in their unusuality as well as in performance. It should be noted however that RO weapons are in general more powerful than most powerful guns available in typical Doom mod. Default gun spawners are taken over to release RO's native weapons. In addition to these, mod contains multiple inventory items, designed to work in similar vein to weapons, that is to be more powerful than one could expect.

Moreover RO contains custom difficulty levels, for players not considering easy stroll through their maps fun, as well as special co-op patch restricting individual players to subsets of weapons.

== Development history ==

RO was initially released on the zDoom forum on June 4th, 2011, at the moment featuring umphteen weapons. After some improvements on the base mod, PillowBlaster decided to release so-called expansion pack '''Reinforcements from Moldova''', replacing the current set of weapons with different one while featuring the same gameplay style (this mod required original RO to run). After a break and an episode with '''Sickle Pack''' containing ideas scrapped from both RO and Moldova expansion for varying reasons, a new version of RO was released, containing new set of weapons sized similarly to old ones and contents of both old sets.

{{cleanup}}</text>
    <sha1>qov3386zbw2pfj9eiu2ze9gystrapk4</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>