<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Cursed Maze</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>7535</id>
  <revision>
    <id>48846</id>
    <parentid>36047</parentid>
    <timestamp>2021-11-06T18:57:35Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Redneckerz</username>
      <id>2602</id>
    </contributor>
    <origin>48846</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2972" sha1="6dhd7ksuomtr8bgvcyzie6a9j9ohyk6" xml:space="preserve">[[File:CursedMaze01.png|thumb|A screenshot of an area of first map on Cursed Maze]]
{{Wad
| name = Cursed Maze
| port=  GZDoom 
| author = Lucas "ibm5155"
| iwad = Stand-alone
| status = Released
| type = m
| link = [http://www.mediafire.com/?3xiqowryzb5v9j4 Download from official link]
}}

== Description ==
:'''Cursed Maze''' is an independent game developed with the [[ZDoom]] engine, created as a school project which presents a simple history but a different gameplay.

:The project had four revisions. The 2.0, released December 17, 2012 was the latest, and it is the most important too, because it adds, as well as change, many other things in the game, like voice-overs for scientists in both English and Portuguese, removal of music tracks that had legal problems, skill difficulty balance, and using new custom monsters in-place of the original, yet modified, [[Doom]] ones. 

It is based off GZDoom 1.6.0 (r1418) / ZDoom 2.6.0 (r3730), and it includes QEffectsGL, a third party graphic enhancer with a custom .ini file to bring bloom and SSAO effects.

:In 2015, a version of the game appeared for the GLOOME engine, released July 8, 2015. GLOOME is a derivative of GZDoom 1.8.10.

==Gameplay==
:Basicaly, it is a dark maze where you need to kill six to eleven ghouls. The higher the difficulty setting, the more difficult the maze becomes to see and the more monsters to face.
[[File:CursedMaze02.png|thumb|A screenshot of one of the monsters]]
:
:There are three monsters in the game. The first one is the ''Ghouldemon'', a dark creature with green eyes. it is easy to kill, but look out, sometimes it "cuts the maze" to get you. The second one is the ''Ghoulpain''. It is like the Ghouldemon, but with a light face and red eyes. It is too dangerous when you are in little areas. The third monster is the ''Ravishing''. This is the most dangerous of the three. It can easily gets you, and has some powers that will scare you when you know what they are.

==Credits==
* MUISIC COMPOSER
:*  ray: Author of Happy Time Circus 2 mod
:*   Kevin MacLeod

* SOUND EFFECTS
:*   daveincamas: for Ghoul Chain sound
:*   NoiseCollector:for Sonar sound
:*   farbin: for Drop Chain sound
:*   ibm5155:for Ghoul and scientists sounds
:*   perkristian:for Super shotgun, pistol and player sounds
:*   Slave2theLight:for Zombie sounds
 
* TEXTURE EDITOR
:*   harryboam: author of slimes texture
:*   DaniJ: author of skinface texture
:*   Stanley: author of sloppy texture
:*   Chilvence: author of all SFLR textures
:*   ibm5155: for eye/flicker effect, menus and ghouls textures

==External Links==
:[http://www.mediafire.com/?3xiqowryzb5v9j4 Cursed Maze 2.0] (GZDoom version with QEffectsGL)
:[http://www.mediafire.com/download/6dhim6a8ya4f6px Cursed Maze 2.0 alpha 5] (GLOOME version)
:[http://ibm5155.webs.com/cursed-maze Official site (Portuguese)]
:[http://forum.zdoom.org/viewtopic.php?t=33757 Project's thread on the ZDoom forums]
[[Category:WADs created for ZDoom]]</text>
    <sha1>6dhd7ksuomtr8bgvcyzie6a9j9ohyk6</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>