<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>The Dark Portal</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>7633</id>
  <revision>
    <id>37159</id>
    <parentid>37143</parentid>
    <timestamp>2013-09-15T14:07:47Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <origin>37159</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="5600" sha1="9zr0z1upnr5yj6lu82n8bbnm0u5rf2v" xml:space="preserve">{{delete|Not a ZDoom mod, so outside of this wiki's scope.}}
{{wad
|author=Carl Lewis a.k.a. Roots and Steve Noble
|type=m
|port=
|iwad=Hexen
|status=Released
|link=
|category = "also recommended"
|ru=1
}}

This is the first Hexen hub replacement ever made. Many  pain-staking  hours of production have been used to perfect the  workmanship  in  these five handcrafted  levels.  only  the most  advanced  players  will  tough  out  the challenges that we throw at them; so, are you up to our challenge?

Story: 
The Wastelands Part 1: The Dark Portal               
The day breaks to the night's firm grasp; the sun yields to its everlasting power and tranquility,  the time of rest is near. The time is of ancient; medieval philosophy rule the land, whilst its
kings  lay  siege to  foreign   realms  for  sheer  conquest  and  annihilation.  Within the courtyards  of a peaceful kingdom,  you prepare yourself as a  royal knight of valor and honor;  training for the day one such land lays siege to your home. The beliefs of superstition and  magic are prevalent here,  though pure evidence of its existence can  not be found nor proven.  But this night is different;  you  can  feel  a  strange  presence  in  the air-- a presence of  absolute evil and  vile destruction.  You cautiously make way  for  home,  feeling as  if some  supernatural  force is watching your every move.  Upon the arrival to your cottage,  you quickly store away your belongings,  making way for bed.  After a time that seemed forever,  sleep finally  overcomes your thoughts and you drift off, away from this world.
 
In your dreams,  you have a  vision of  a world lying  in total chaos and despair, where sorcery, magic, and corruption prevails; a world whose people are enslaved  by a power-hungry leader known
only as  Lord  Korax.  As his  legions  of  warriors protect  his castle,  Korax's cabinet  of Wizards  has gathered  in his throne room, using black  magic to open a  gateway to Earth.  The vision
fades as a being walks  and stands before you  in your dreams. He is a  profit dressed  in  elaborate  robes;  obviously  from  the wastelands you just saw. He speaks to you in a low whisper, as if
not to be heard by anyone else. 

"If you do not  stop Korax,  your people  will be destroyed and your world will be lost for all time.", says the stranger. &lt;br/&gt;
"Who are you?", you ask quizzically.&lt;br/&gt;
"I am of the alliance-- We are the only ones left, brave enough to stand against Korax's evil reign."&lt;br/&gt;
"Who is this Korax you speak of?"&lt;br/&gt;
"Korax is absolute evil.  He is using our people and our powers for his  plans to  conquer and pillage.  Even as we  speak, he is draining the life essences from my body and my people; he using our power to conquer other worlds. Your world is next."&lt;br/&gt;
"Why Me?  You are a sorcerer who has great magic! Why can't you free your own people? I am nothing."&lt;br/&gt;
"It has  been prophesied for  generations of a liberator not of this world. You are that liberator. You are our only hope left in our dying world. Help us, or we will be lost to the enemy for all time; and so will your world when Korax's gate is  fully established! My power grows weak, as I am using the last ounce of my strength to contact you; I haven't much time"&lt;br/&gt;
"How can I defeat an entity of such great power?"&lt;br/&gt;
"When you wake up, there will be a  wizard's staff next to your bed,  use it  against all  your foes. We have  hidden the greater weapons, so that they will not  fall into the hands of the enemy. &lt;br/&gt;
Farewell chosen one. Please do not fail us, or all is lost."&lt;br/&gt;
"Wait! I have some much more to ask you!" &lt;br/&gt;
 
The being fades from your view, screaming in utter misery, as a vile, evil laughter clouds your mind. You awake with  sweat running  down your face.  It could not be real! It was  only a dream!  In the distance  you hear one  final confirmation:&lt;br/&gt;
"Help us....  Help us...."&lt;br/&gt;
The voices fades as rapidly as they came. You look out your window and see the horrendous portal. You now know what you must do. You run  down into your  basement to your stock hold, then make&lt;br/&gt;
your way to  the ever-glowing portal.  You grip the  wand tightly as you step  through; what  happens next,  you will never forget.  You are  transported to a small  room.  Korax stands  before you,&lt;br/&gt;
mocking your efforts.&lt;br/&gt;
"So, you are the liberator."&lt;br/&gt;
You stand absolutely stiff, frozen in complete fear.&lt;br/&gt;
 
"Look at yourself, human; you can barely even move. How can you be the hero of prophecy?"&lt;br/&gt;
Out of pure courage (or stupidity),  you aim the staff that the wizard gave you towards Korax's black heart, and fire. The shot fazed Korax none. Korax roars at your infidelity.&lt;br/&gt;
"Do you  really  think  that your  pea-shooter  will  harm  me, human?" Korax laughs in your face. &lt;br/&gt;
"I think I  will play  a little game  with you,  player", Korax&lt;br/&gt;
says, "I will let you wander through my world.  If you are strong enough to  survive  against  my servants,  then I  will  come and personally rip your heart out."&lt;br/&gt;

Korax laughs again.  With a wave  of his hand,  you are  warped into a dark  and damp hallway;  you can still hear Korax laughing in the distance.  From now on, Korax will  be watching your every
move. Smells of recently slaughtered animals fill your head. You look behind  you and  see the  portal going  back home.  You desire to return to  the  safety and  comfort  of your  bed, but  you  must
continue  in your quest.  You turn back around  and see a room at the end of the hallway, but only God knows what lies beyond.</text>
    <sha1>9zr0z1upnr5yj6lu82n8bbnm0u5rf2v</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>