<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Dreadnaught and Knockabout</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>7637</id>
  <revision>
    <id>37162</id>
    <parentid>37147</parentid>
    <timestamp>2013-09-15T14:08:11Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <origin>37162</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2010" sha1="k51zsd9f1pnxeuk5kx478pl5cvo4mqf" xml:space="preserve">{{delete|Not a ZDoom mod, so outside of this wiki's scope.}}
{{wad
|author=Scott McNutt
|type=m
|port=GZDoom
|iwad=Hexen
|status=Released
|link=
|category = "also recommended"
|ru=1
}}

Two complete hubs for Hexen with heavy scripting and tons of poly-objects, by Scott McNutt author of SM Levels &amp; Darrell Esau (scripter extraordinaire).

In Dreadnaught you are Kane, an immortal who was doomed to roam the Earth by the god that created you. The punishment levelled at you for killing your own brother and thus brought terrible
violence to the Earth. The irony is that the god was a corrupt and cynical part of the supernatural universe overruling Earth and you, Kane, rebelled against being used as a pawn. Your adventures take
place in all ages of Earth. Your sword and battle prowess is at the service of any ruler who can pay your price. You are a true anti-hero who changes sides to suit your own advantage and mood.
You never age and remain as old as you were when the god cursed you. You can be killed but up to now no human has come close to doing so.
Scotts Portals, is the beginning of your long and tasking journey. From here you will have access to the other four.
The Swamps of Thark, The Tomb of Quarix and The Palace of Ice before you get access to Veda's  Vault. Once Veda's Vault is conquered you will revisit Scott's Portals to finish off the
remaining beasts and ghosts of days gone before you free yourself from the curse that was cast upon your soul.

In Knockabout...beyond Dreadnaught, Kane is continuing his majestic adventures. After surviving and conquering the onslaught that was brought upon his torn soul in 
Dreadnaught, Kane is back to finish his quest. Wheel of Fire is where you begin your illfated journey. It is here where you will have access to the other  4 levels, Slice and Dice, Game of Death, The Bell Tolls and HexQuake. You must complete the first 3 sublevels before gaining access to the final level and to face the fate that you have chosen and others have failed.</text>
    <sha1>k51zsd9f1pnxeuk5kx478pl5cvo4mqf</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>