<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Shadowcaster</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>7646</id>
  <revision>
    <id>37169</id>
    <parentid>37130</parentid>
    <timestamp>2013-09-15T14:09:22Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <origin>37169</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2070" sha1="1fpw6o3wjirvbleviealzrvo85ts60o" xml:space="preserve">{{delete|Not a ZDoom mod, so outside of this wiki's scope.}}
A 9 level replacement wad for Heretic by Stephen Clark (The Ultimate DooMer!). If you love puzzles, then prepare to be tested, because there are a wide variety of fiendish puzzles in this wad, covering all of Heretic's features, from the regular to the weird and wonderful! Plenty of secrets (5 each level), 


Story: Another time, another world.

You are Banedon, one of a sentient race of heretical elves known as the Sidhe. Renowned throughout the kingdom of Durenor for feats of bravery and heroism, you always get called up for quests of bravery and danger.  So, you are now standing in the grand palace of King Rimoah, where he tells you of grave danger that threatens these shores.

He tells you about the dark mage Tetrahagael, known as the Shadowcaster because his presence casts a shadow over the island where he resides. That shadow could soon be cast over the whole kingdom, because the King's mages of Durenor have discovered that he is summoning evil monsters through some kind of portal to another world, and is preparing an invasion force made up of these monsters!

No time to lose, then.  Your quest is to journey to the island of Fagranc, where the Shadowcaster resides, destroy him and the portal.  Not an easy task, even by your standards, but you do have some help.  The King's mages have prepared a boat imbued with a spell that will allow you to sneak onto the island without being detected by the dark magic (but not when you disembark).  And also there are many magical weapons and artefacts on the island that possess the power to destroy him and his evil summonings.

The next day, you grab your staff and elvenwand, and set sail for the island. As you approach, you can feel the presence of evil all around the place, it seems that the whole island could be infested with monsters.  You notice a small village, located on the far side of the island, away from the tower where the dark mage resides.

You head towards the village, hoping it is unoccupied but ready just in case....</text>
    <sha1>1fpw6o3wjirvbleviealzrvo85ts60o</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>