<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>A KillTracer</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>7760</id>
  <revision>
    <id>46807</id>
    <parentid>45099</parentid>
    <timestamp>2019-07-16T06:13:54Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Quaker540</username>
      <id>2135</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>Replaced the deprecated action function, and added hyperlinks for all functions and properties</comment>
    <origin>46807</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="3757" sha1="4kyowll8b2xj21h59av6jal247j0296" xml:space="preserve">{{codepointer|Monster AI}}
'''A_KillTracer''' [(string ''damagetype'' [, int ''flags'' [, string ''filter'' [, string ''species'' [, int ''src'' [, int ''inflict'']]]]])]

==Usage==
Kills the calling actor's [[actor pointer|tracer]]. Optionally, a damage type can be given. Note that damage inflicted by this codepointer is not affected by damage factors.

==Parameters==
*''damagetype'': if the actor dies, the actor will enter a death state based on the specified damage type if present (or pain state if using {{Flag|NODAMAGE}}). Default is "{{c|{{DamageType|None}}}}".
*''flags'': the following flags can be combined using the {{!}} character between name constants:
**'''KILS_FOILINVUL''' - kills monsters and/or missiles that have the {{Flag|INVULNERABLE}} flag.
**'''KILS_KILLMISSILES''' - causes missiles that are affected to enter their death state. Note that this follows the INVULNERABLE and NODAMAGE rules for monsters.
**'''KILS_NOMONSTERS''' - do not target monsters with this function. Alone, it makes the function do nothing, but can be combined with KILS_KILLMISSILES to only affect missiles.
**'''KILS_FOILBUDDHA''' — the ''{{Flag|BUDDHA|buddha}}'' effect is ignored when attempting to kill the actor.
**'''KILS_EXFILTER''' — inverts the case of the class name filter; the calling actor's tracer is only killed if its class name does not match the value passed to ''filter''.
**'''KILS_EXSPECIES''' — inverts the case of the [[species]] filter; the calling actor's tracer is only killed if its species does not match the value passed to ''species''.
**'''KILS_EITHER''' — the calling actor's tracer is killed if either of its class name or [[species]] matches the values passed to ''filter'' and ''species'', respectively.
*''filter'': the actor class to kill. The calling actor's tracer is only killed if its class name matches the specified filter class. Default is {{c|"None"}}.
*''species'': the actor [[species]] to kill. The calling actor's tracer is only killed if its species matches the specified species filter. Default is {{c|"None"}}.
* ''src'': Indicates the [[Actor pointer|actor pointer]] responsible for dealing the damage. A monster dealing the damage should use AAPTR_DEFAULT, and missiles should use AAPTR_TARGET (so monsters can identify missiles belonging to their owners and give proper credit for the kill). Default is AAPTR_DEFAULT.
* ''inflict'': The actor doing the actual damage. By changing this, the actor's flags upon the pointed actor are taken into account instead of the calling actor's own.

== Examples ==
This is a modified revenant, whos projectile will instantly freeze the player to death if it
flies for around 5 seconds, using A_KillTracer, with the "Ice" damage type.


 ACTOR Petriphant : Revenant
 {
  {{Property|Translation}} "Ice"
  {{Property|HitObituary}} "%o was punched by a Petriphant."
  {{Property|Obituary}} "%o was petrified by a Petriphant's fireball."
  States
  {
  Missile:
    SKEL J 0 Bright [[A_FaceTarget]]
    SKEL J 10 Bright [[A_FaceTarget]]
    SKEL K 10 [[A_SpawnProjectile]] ("StoneTracer", 40)
    SKEL K 10 [[A_FaceTarget]]
    Goto See
  }
 }
 
 ACTOR StoneTracer : RevenantTracer
 {
  {{Property|Translation}} "Ice"
  {{Property|DamageType}} Ice
  States
  {
  Spawn:
    FATB ABABABABA 4 Bright [[A_SeekerMissile]] (45, 90, SMF_PRECISE)
    FATB ABABABABA 4 Bright [[A_SeekerMissile]] (45, 90, SMF_PRECISE)
    FATB ABABABABA 4 Bright [[A_SeekerMissile]] (45, 90, SMF_PRECISE)
    FATB ABABABABA 4 Bright [[A_SeekerMissile]] (45, 90, SMF_PRECISE)
    FATB ABABABABA 4 Bright [[A_SeekerMissile]] (45, 90, SMF_PRECISE)
    FATB A 3 Bright '''A_KillTracer''' ("Ice")
    Loop
  Death:
    FBXP A 8 Bright
    FBXP B 6 Bright
    FBXP C 4 Bright
    Stop
  }
 }</text>
    <sha1>4kyowll8b2xj21h59av6jal247j0296</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>