<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>ACS PCodes</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>7764</id>
  <revision>
    <id>38394</id>
    <parentid>38389</parentid>
    <timestamp>2014-10-22T14:29:38Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>short introduction, categories, and link to document</comment>
    <origin>38394</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="8815" sha1="0m8jz0qihxx8yg4vmk5ez8s0k4dirzb" xml:space="preserve">The following is a list of [[ACS]] {{wp|p-code machine|p-code}}.

{| class="wikitable sortable"
|-
! # !! PCode !! Arguments !! Stack Offset !! Extension !! Description
|-
| 0 || NOP || 0 || 0 || Hexen || Does nothing.
|-
| 1 || TERMINATE || 0 || 0 || Hexen || Finishes the current script.
|-
| 2 || SUSPEND || 0 || 0 || Hexen || Holds the execution of the script until it is executed again, at which point it will resume.
|-
| 3 || PUSHNUMBER || 1 || 1 || Hexen || Pushes an integer onto the stack.
|-
| 4 || LSPEC1 || 1 || -1 || Hexen || Executes the line special, popping one argument from the stack.
|-
| 5 || LSPEC2 || 1 || -2 || Hexen || Executes the line special, popping two arguments from the stack.
|-
| 6 || LSPEC3 || 1 || -3 || Hexen || Executes the line special, popping three arguments from the stack.
|-
| 7 || LSPEC4 || 1 || -4 || Hexen || Executes the line special, popping four arguments from the stack.
|-
| 8 || LSPEC5 || 1 || -5 || Hexen || Executes the line special, popping five arguments from the stack.
|-
| 9 || LSPEC1DIRECT || 2 || 0 || Hexen || Executes the line special given by the first argument with a constant parameter given by the second argument.
|-
| 10 || LSPEC2DIRECT || 3 || 0 || Hexen || Executes the line special given by the first argument with two constant parameters given by the rest of the arguments.
|-
| 11 || LSPEC3DIRECT || 4 || 0 || Hexen || Executes the line special given by the first argument with three constant parameters given by the rest of the arguments.
|-
| 12 || LSPEC4DIRECT || 5 || 0 || Hexen || Executes the line special given by the first argument with four constant parameters given by the rest of the arguments.
|-
| 13 || LSPEC5DIRECT || 6 || 0 || Hexen || Executes the line special given by the first argument with five constant parameters given by the rest of the arguments.
|-
| 14 || ADD || 0 || -1 || Hexen || Pops two integers from the stack, adds them, and pushes the result.
|-
| 15 || SUBTRACT || 0 || -1 || Hexen || Pops two integers from the stack, subtracts them, and pushes the result.
|-
| 16 || MULTIPLY || 0 || -1 || Hexen || Pops two integers from the stack, multiplies them, and pushes the result.
|-
| 17 || DIVIDE || 0 || -1 || Hexen || Pops two integers from the stack, divides them, and pushes the result.  Division by zero causes an error.
|-
| 18 || MODULUS || 0 || -1 || Hexen || Pops two integers from the stack, divides them, and pushes the remainder.  Division by zero causes an error.
|-
| 19 || EQ || 0 || -1 || Hexen || Pops two integers from the stack and compares them for equality.  If they are equal, a 1 is pushed to the stack, otherwise 0.
|-
| 20 || NE || 0 || -1 || Hexen || Pops two integers from the stack and compares them for inequality.  If they are not equal, a 1 is pushed to the stack, otherwise 0.
|-
| 21 || LT || 0 || -1 || Hexen || Pops two integers from the stack and compares the second popped number to the first.  If the second number is less than the first, a 1 is pushed to the stack, otherwise 0.
|-
| 22 || GT || 0 || -1 || Hexen || Pops two integers from the stack and compares the second popped number to the first.  If the second number is greater than the first, a 1 is pushed to the stack, otherwise 0.
|-
| 23 || LE || 0 || -1 || Hexen || Pops two integers from the stack and compares the second popped number to the first.  If the second number is less than or equal to the first, a 1 is pushed to the stack, otherwise 0.
|-
| 24 || GE || 0 || -1 || Hexen || Pops two integers from the stack and compares the second popped number to the first.  If the second number is greater than or equal to the first, a 1 is pushed to the stack, otherwise 0.
|-
| 25 || ASSIGNSCRIPTVAR || 1 || -1 || Hexen || Pops an integer from the stack and assigns it to a local variable specified as the argument.
|-
| 26 || ASSIGNMAPVAR || 1 || -1 || Hexen || Pops an integer from the stack and assigns it to a map variable specified as the argument.
|-
| 27 || ASSIGNWORLDVAR || 1 || -1 || Hexen || Pops an integer from the stack and assigns it to a world variable specified as the argument.
|-
| 28 || PUSHSCRIPTVAR || 1 || 1 || Hexen || Pushes an integer from the local variable specified as the argument onto the stack.
|-
| 29 || PUSHMAPVAR || 1 || 1 || Hexen || Pushes an integer from the map variable specified as the argument onto the stack.
|-
| 30 || PUSHWORLDVAR || 1 || 1 || Hexen || Pushes an integer from the world variable specified as the argument onto the stack.
|-
| 31 || ADDSCRIPTVAR || 1 || -1 || Hexen || Pops an integer from the stack and adds it to the specified local variable.
|-
| 32 || ADDMAPVAR || 1 || -1 || Hexen || Pops an integer from the stack and adds it to the specified map variable.
|-
| 33 || ADDWORLDVAR || 1 || -1 || Hexen || Pops an integer from the stack and adds it to the specified world variable.
|-
| 34 || SUBSCRIPTVAR || 1 || -1 || Hexen || Pops an integer from the stack and subtracts it from the specified local variable.
|-
| 35 || SUBMAPVAR || 1 || -1 || Hexen || Pops an integer from the stack and subtracts it from the specified map variable.
|-
| 36 || SUBWORLDVAR || 1 || -1 || Hexen || Pops an integer from the stack and subtracts it from the specified world variable.
|-
| 37 || MULSCRIPTVAR || 1 || -1 || Hexen || Pops an integer from the stack and multiplies it with the specified local variable.
|-
| 38 || MULMAPVAR || 1 || -1 || Hexen || Pops an integer from the stack and multiplies it with the specified map variable.
|-
| 39 || MULWORLDVAR || 1 || -1 || Hexen || Pops an integer from the stack and multiplies it with the specified world variable.
|-
| 40 || DIVSCRIPTVAR || 1 || -1 || Hexen || Pops an integer from the stack and divides it from the specified local variable.  Division by zero causes an error.
|-
| 41 || DIVMAPVAR || 1 || -1 || Hexen || Pops an integer from the stack and divides it from the specified map variable.  Division by zero causes an error.
|-
| 42 || DIVWORLDVAR || 1 || -1 || Hexen || Pops an integer from the stack and divides it from the specified world variable.  Division by zero causes an error.
|-
| 43 || MODSCRIPTVAR || 1 || -1 || Hexen || Pops an integer from the stack and divides it from the specified local variable, leaving the remainder in the variable.  Division by zero causes an error.
|-
| 44 || MODMAPVAR || 1 || -1 || Hexen || Pops an integer from the stack and divides it from the specified map variable, leaving the remainder in the variable.  Division by zero causes an error.
|-
| 45 || MODWORLDVAR || 1 || -1 || Hexen || Pops an integer from the stack and divides it from the specified world variable, leaving the remainder in the variable.  Division by zero causes an error.
|-
| 46 || INCSCRIPTVAR || 1 || 0 || Hexen || Increments the specified local variable by 1.
|-
| 47 || INCMAPVAR || 1 || 0 || Hexen || Increments the specified map variable by 1.
|-
| 48 || INCWORLDVAR || 1 || 0 || Hexen || Increments the specified world variable by 1.
|-
| 49 || DECSCRIPTVAR || 1 || 0 || Hexen || Decrements the specified local variable by 1.
|-
| 50 || DECMAPVAR || 1 || 0 || Hexen || Decrements the specified map variable by 1.
|-
| 51 || DECWORLDVAR || 1 || 0 || Hexen || Decrements the specified world variable by 1.
|-
| 52 || GOTO || 1 || 0 || Hexen || Jumps to the specified offset in the script.
|-
| 53 || IFGOTO || 1 || -1 || Hexen || Pops an integer off the stack and jumps to the specified offset in the script if the popped number is not 0.
|-
| 54 || DROP || 0 || -1 || Hexen || Pops an item off the stack and discards it.
|-
| 55 || DELAY || 0 || -1 || Hexen || Pops an integer off the stack and delays the script by the popped number of tics.  See: [[Delay]].
|-
| 56 || DELAYDIRECT || 1 || 0 || Hexen || Delays the script by the number of tics specified by argument.  See: [[Delay]].
|-
| 57 || RANDOM || 0 || -1 || Hexen || Pops two numbers from the stack.  A random number between those two popped numbers is then pushed to the stack.  See: [[Random]].
|-
| 58 || RANDOMDIRECT || 2 || 1 || Hexen || Push a random number between the two numbers specified as arguments to the stack.  See: [[Random]].
|}

... to be continued ...

== CALLFUNC Functions ==

The CALLFUNC PCode references the following table to decide which function to call.  All functions push a single return value to the stack, and thus must be dropped by hand if the return value is ignored.

{| class="wikitable sortable"
|-
! # !! Function !! Arguments !! Return Type
|-
| 1 || GetLineUDMFInt || 2 || integer
|-
| 2 || GetLineUDMFFixed || 2 || fixed
|-
| 3 || GetThingUDMFInt || 2 || integer
|}

... to be continued ...

==External links==
* [https://bitbucket.org/Blzut3/acc/src ACC++ repository] &amp;mdash; this article is sourced from /docs/manual.odt

[[Category:ACS]][[Category:Technical aspects]]</text>
    <sha1>0m8jz0qihxx8yg4vmk5ez8s0k4dirzb</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>