<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>A SpawnParticle</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>7877</id>
  <revision>
    <id>52823</id>
    <parentid>52098</parentid>
    <timestamp>2024-08-03T12:56:24Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>SPZ</username>
      <id>2640</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>/* Usage */</comment>
    <origin>52823</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2176" sha1="rc6sd6i3t8pp5i9uqlpkbnnykbkc0tk" xml:space="preserve">{{codepointer|Spawn}}
void '''A_SpawnParticle'''(color ''color1'', int ''flags'' = 0, int ''lifetime'' = TICRATE, double ''size'' = 1, double ''angle'' = 0, double ''xoff'' = 0, double ''yoff'' = 0, double ''zoff'' = 0, double ''velx'' = 0, double ''vely'' = 0, double ''velz'' = 0, double ''accelx'' = 0, double ''accely'' = 0, double ''accelz'' = 0, double ''startalphaf'' = 1, double ''fadestepf'' = -1, double ''sizestep'' = 0)

==Usage==
Spawns a single [[particle]].

For a version that supports custom graphics, see '''[[A_SpawnParticleEx]]'''.

For a more robust [[Structs|struct]]-using version see '''[[SpawnParticle (ZScript)]]'''.

===Parameters===
*''color1'': The color of the particle. Can be used with a hexadecimal value or a predefined value such as "Black".
*''flags'': Customizes the behavior of the function. Multiple flags can be combined by using the bitwise OR operator (&lt;code&gt;|&lt;/code&gt;) between the constant names:
{{: SpawnParticle flags}}
:Default is 0.
*''lifetime'': The lifetime of the particle in [[tics]]. Default is &lt;code&gt;TICRATE&lt;/code&gt; which equals to one second (35 tics).
*''size'': The size of the particle. Default is 1.
*''angle'': The angle to offset the particle by. Default is 0.
*''x/yoff'': The distance from the actor to spawn the particle along the X axis. Note that this is not relative. Default is 0.
*''zoff'': How high up to spawn the particle from the actor's Z position. Default is 0.
*''velx/y/z'': The velocity along the X/Y/Z axis to apply to the particle. This is in absolute direction, not relative. Default is 0.
*''accelx/y/z'': Defines how much to accelerate the particle by over its lifespan. Default is 0.
*''startalphaf'': Specifies the particle's alpha upon spawning. Default is 1.0.
*''fadestepf'': The amount by which the particle fades each tic. The particle is automatically removed early if it fades completely before ''lifetime'' expires. -1 indicates automatic (a complete fade-out over the length of ''lifetime''). Default is -1.
*''sizestep'': The particle grows or shrinks in size by this amount per tic.

== Examples ==
{{noexamples}}

== See also ==
*[[A_SpawnParticleEx]]
*[[SpawnParticle (ZScript)]]</text>
    <sha1>rc6sd6i3t8pp5i9uqlpkbnnykbkc0tk</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>