<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>SpawnParticle</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>7882</id>
  <revision>
    <id>47182</id>
    <parentid>44310</parentid>
    <timestamp>2020-03-18T06:00:21Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Bauul</username>
      <id>2596</id>
    </contributor>
    <origin>47182</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2026" sha1="hz05ppnkjpj4upbz59w8236y759vh73" xml:space="preserve">void '''SpawnParticle''' (int ''color'' [, bool ''fullbright'' [, int ''lifetime'' [, int ''size'' [, fixed ''x'' [, fixed ''y'' [, fixed ''z'' [, fixed ''velx'' [, fixed ''vely'' [, fixed ''velz'' [, fixed ''accelx'' [, fixed ''accely'' [, fixed ''accelz'' [, int ''startalpha'' [, int ''fadestep'']]]]]]]]]]]]]]);

== Usage ==
Spawns a single [[Particles|particle]] at the x, y and z coordinates.

=== Parameters ===
*''color'': The color of the particle. This is a hexadecimal value, e.g. {{c|0xFF0000}} (which is bright red).
*''fullbright'': If {{c|true}}, it renders the particle fully bright. Default is {{c|false}}.
*''lifetime'': The lifetime of the particle in [[tics]]. This ranges from 0 to 255. Default is 35.
*''size'': The size of the particle, up to a maximum value of 65535. Default is 1.
*''x/y/z'': The absolute map coordinates at which to spawn the particle. Default is 0.
*''velx/vely/velz'': The velocity along the x/y/z axis. This is in absolute direction, not relative. Default is 0.
*''accelx/accely/accelz'': Defines how much to accelerate this particle by over its lifespan. Default is 0.
*''startalpha'': Specifies the alpha upon spawning. This ranges from 0 to 255. Default is 255.
*''fadestep'': The amount the particle fades each tic. This ranges from -1 to 255, with -1 indicating ''automatic'' mode (a complete fadeout over the length of lifetime). The particle is automatically removed early if it fades completely before lifetime expires. Default is -1.

== Examples ==
This a simplified version of the script that spawns the yellow "portal particles" at the start of Map01 of Eviternity.  The particles are spawned randomly across the width and height of a linedef and slowly fade out.

 Script "Eviternity_PortalParticles" [[Script types#ENTER|ENTER]]
 { 
  [[SpawnParticle]] (0xFFE74B, 1, [[Random]](30,45), 7 , [[Random]](-184.0,-72.0), -736.0, [[Random]](8.0, 120.0), 0.0, 3.0, 0.0, 0.0, 0.0, 0.0, 1.0, -1);
  [[Delay]](1);
  [[Restart]];
 }

[[category:ACS Level alteration functions]]</text>
    <sha1>hz05ppnkjpj4upbz59w8236y759vh73</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>