<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Doom Builder</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>796</id>
  <revision>
    <id>52126</id>
    <parentid>47071</parentid>
    <timestamp>2024-03-27T20:41:00Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Jekyll Grim Payne</username>
      <id>2175</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>added outdated note</comment>
    <origin>52126</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="4969" sha1="e81niw52amqbi4qlc46glaqp8na783g" xml:space="preserve">{{Doomwiki|link=Doom_Builder_2|name=DB2}}

{{Note|Doom Builder is outdated. It's recommended to use [[Ultimate Doom Builder]] for editing Doom maps, regardless of the target format.}}

[[File:DoomBuilder2 PreviewDoom2MAP14.png|thumb|Doom Builder 2 (r1715) displaying a section of MAP14 from &lt;i&gt;Doom 2&lt;/i&gt;]]
'''Doom Builder''' is a Doom [[Editing tools|level editor]] with full support for ZDoom editing, including the "Game-in-Hexen" and "Game-in-UDMF" [[map format]]s. It is being developed by [[Pascal vd Heiden]] (alias CodeImp) and is [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_software free software], licensed under the terms of the [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU_GPL GNU General Public License]. Popular features include lots of customizability, prefabs, advanced drawing code, and a 3D mode that lets you browse and edit your levels in real time.

See also the [[Doom Builder ACS configuration]].

The current version of Doom Builder is Doom Builder 2, a total rewrite. The last version of Doom Builder 1 is 1.68.

==Doom Builder==
The original Doom Builder was written mostly in Visual Basic. It can run on Windows 98, 2000, or XP, but not on newer versions of Windows (Vista, 7 and above). It can be used to create maps in the Doom and Hexen formats; but it is generally outdated and unsupported. It is able to parse [[DECORATE]] lumps to find custom actors, and also supports graphics defined in [[TEXTURES]].

==Doom Builder 2==
A complete rewrite in C#, DB2 (or Doom Builder 2) was the first map editor to support UDMF in addition to the older binary map formats.  Doom Builder 2 requires, at minimum, [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windows_XP Microsoft Windows XP], but it is crucial to have [http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/w0x726c2%28v=VS.90%29.aspx Microsoft .NET Framework 3.5] installed within the system - regardless of the Microsoft Windows version.

===Doom Builder X===
A fork of DB2 intended to update and maintain the DB2 workflow and interface without drastic changes.

===GZDoom Editing Plugin===
An alternate version of the 3D visual mode, which was never completed. It shows 3D floors and slopes. It has been replaced by GZDoom Builder, which does not use it.

===Doom Builder 64===
A fork of DB2 specialized on creating maps for {{dw|Doom64 EX}}. It cannot be used to edit maps in the formats supported by ZDoom.

===GZDoom Builder===
Another fork of DB2 specialized on creating maps for ZDoom and GZDoom. It boasts enhanced support for ZDoom features such as showing [[slope]]s, [[3D floor]]s, and [[dynamic light]]s in visual mode, displaying [[model]]s, and parsing [[MAPINFO]], [[GLDEFS]] and [[MODELDEF]] lumps in addition to DECORATE to obtain the data it needs to give an accurate preview of the level in 3D mode.

====GZDB-Bugfix====
A fork of GZDoom Builder mainly meant to keep the editor up-to-date with the latest GZDoom once the author of GZDB left the community.

====Ultimate Doom Builder (UDB)====
A continuation and rebranding of GZDoom Builder-Bugfix that on top of having all the original GZDB features, includes a slew of new features such as [[ZScript]] support, visual attenuated lights and spotlights support, and Doom 64-style sector color support. UDB has a native 64-bit build with several performance optimizations, better Linux compatibility, and an improved OpenGL-based 3D mode.

UDB requires at least OpenGL 3.3 capability to run, whereas GZDB-BF, like other DB2 forks, rely on Direct3D.

=={{LE|Editor keys|DECORATE keys}}==
Both versions of Doom Builder include a DECORATE parser used to obtain relevant information (such as [[editor number]], {{Property|Radius}}, {{Property|Height}}, {{Property|Scale}}, and so on) from custom actors. Additional information can be conveyed with keys in the form of special comments inserted within an actor's declaration block. GZDB and GZDB-BF also include parsers for MAPINFO and ZScript, and editor keys can be read if they are in an actor's Default block.

See [[Editor keys]] for a centralized full list.

==Forum links==
* {{Forum|t=19171|Doom Builder 2 thread}}
* {{Forum|t=26831|DB2.1.0 release thread}}
* {{Forum|t=27190|GZDoom Editing Plugin}}
* {{Forum|t=32392|GZDoom Builder thread}}
* {{Forum|t=54957|GZDB-Bugfix thread}}
* {{Forum|t=66745|Ultimate Doom Builder thread}}
* {{DWForum|t=96943|Doom Builder X thread}}

==External links==
* [http://www.doombuilder.com/ Doom Builder homepage]
* [https://doombuilder.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/doombuilder/ Doom Builder 2 SVN repository]
* [https://github.com/anotak/doombuilderx/ Doom Builder X repository]
* [https://github.com/m-x-d/GZDoom-Builder GZDoom Builder Git repository]
* [https://github.com/jewalky/GZDoom-Builder-Bugfix GZDB-Bugfix Git repository]
* [https://github.com/jewalky/UltimateDoomBuilder Ultimate Doom Builder Git repository]
* [https://doombuilder.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/doombuilder/branches/Builder64/ Doom Builder 64 SVN repository]
[[Category:Level editors]][[Category:Tools]]</text>
    <sha1>e81niw52amqbi4qlc46glaqp8na783g</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>