<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>ZDoom codepointer extensions</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>809</id>
  <revision>
    <id>31257</id>
    <parentid>31245</parentid>
    <timestamp>2011-09-20T18:02:36Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>templated links</comment>
    <origin>31257</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1924" sha1="40o7y1aqemgb5qluz7ysqecmntitl6v" xml:space="preserve">In addition to the {{dw|BEX}} [[codepointer]]s available from [[BOOM]], the following codepointers are also available in ZDoom:

== From {{dw|MBF}} ==
=== Detonate ===
The actor that uses this code pointer will create an explosion with size and damage determined by its Missile Damage field.
=== Mushroom ===
Creates a "mushroom cloud" of mancubus shots just above the actor.
=== Die ===
The actor that uses this dies.

== From [[Hexen]] ==
=== SetReflective ===
The actor becomes reflective, and any projectiles that strike it will bounce off of it, though it will still take damage.
=== UnSetReflective ===
The actor is no longer reflective.
=== SetInvulnerable ===
The actor becomes impervious to damage.
=== UnSetInvulnerable ===
The actor is able to take damage again.
=== SetShootable ===
The actor can be hit by projectiles/hitscan weapons.
=== UnSetShootable ===
The actor cannot be hit by projectiles/hitscan weapons.

== New to [[ZDoom]] ==
=== FireRailgun ===
Fires a railgun from the center of the player's screen. Only for player weapons.
=== FireRailgunRight ===
Fires a railgun from the right side of the player's screen. Only for player weapons.
=== FireRailgunLeft ===
Fires a railgun from the left side of the player's screen. Only for player weapons.
=== MonsterRail ===
Makes a monster fire a railgun. The amount of damage dealt by the railgun is determined by the monster's Missile Damage field.
=== RailWait ===
Exactly the same as NULL. In fact, you are encouraged to use NULL instead of this, because it is considered deprecated.
=== SetReflectiveInvulnerable ===
Makes the actor reflect projectiles and impervious to other types of damage.
=== UnSetReflectiveInvulnerable ===
Undoes the effect of SetReflectiveInvulnerable.
=== Gravity ===
Allows the actor to fall under the effects of gravity.
=== NoGravity ===
Causes the actor to float in the air instead of fall.
[[Category:Deprecated features]]</text>
    <sha1>40o7y1aqemgb5qluz7ysqecmntitl6v</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>