<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Adding weaponsections</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>826</id>
  <revision>
    <id>31556</id>
    <parentid>25941</parentid>
    <timestamp>2011-11-28T12:57:56Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <origin>31556</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1960" sha1="knpx7vr0b68vca3agx5yol6bwhyxmqo" xml:space="preserve">{{Tip|Starting with ZDoom 2.3.0, new and better ways to add weapons to slots are available.&lt;br&gt;See the article on [[weapon slots]] for more information.}}

{{WarnDeprecated}}

Weaponsections are used to alter the weapons that the player will use in a wad. In addition to adding these binds to the [[KEYCONF]] lump, the wad maker must also supply the sprites associated with the weapon. Sounds, however, are optional.

When making a new weaponsection, the "weaponsection" command must be used so [[ZDoom]] knows to only associate this particular binding with a particular wad file.

A few keywords are used when making these binds, which are as follows:

* addslotdefault - This is the normal bind, and simply adds a weapon to that key.
* setslot - This clears any binds already on this key before adding the weapon.
* defaultbind - This adds the weapon ''only'' if the key is currently unbound ''and'' this object is not already bound to a key.

An example of a KEYCONF lump which alters the weapon binding:

    weaponsection MyNewWeapons
    setslot 1 Fist
    addslotdefault 1 CWeapMace
    setslot 2

This will clear the "1" key, and add the fist weapon from Doom. The second line adds the Cleric's Mace after the fist. Weapon names can be found from a dumpclass via the console, and are case sensitive. The final line simply removes all binds from the "2" key.

The name after weaponsection specifies in which [[configuration file|ini]] section these weapon assignments will be saved. You should make this something related to your project to minimize the risk of using a section that another project also uses. "MyNewWeapons" is therefore a bad name to use when you are actually defining a weapon section, but it suffices for example purposes. If you were using this in a WAD named "The Uvlevian Empire", then "UvlevianEmpire" would be a suitable weaponsection name.

A list of weapons can be found on the [[SetWeapon]] page.

[[category:KEYCONF guides]]</text>
    <sha1>knpx7vr0b68vca3agx5yol6bwhyxmqo</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>