<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Creating simple breakable objects</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>831</id>
  <revision>
    <id>21701</id>
    <parentid>15296</parentid>
    <timestamp>2009-05-17T20:41:13Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>msg</comment>
    <origin>21701</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2049" sha1="6rvgn2seutn8yycxbfwfcihio0xfbxi" xml:space="preserve">{{WarnDeprecated|the modern [[DECORATE]] format}}

In addition to the normal commands that can be used with normal [[Creating simple decorations|decoration]] items, there are a few more that can be added to make the scenery breakable in the old [[The old DECORATE format|DECORATE format]]. Using this, you can recreate the destroyable trees that Hexen uses, and even add burn or freeze frames. 

* DeathFrames - Like frames, but gets played when the actor dies. 
* IceDeathFrames - Like DeathFrames, except it is used when the actor freezes to death. 
* BurnDeathFrames - Like DeathFrames, except it is used when the actor burns to death. 
* GenericIceDeath - Like IceDeathFrames, except you don't specify any frames here. The game will create a generic ice death for you. 
* BurnsAway - If you include this, then the thing disappears after it finishes the BurnDeathFrames animation. Otherwise, it stays at the last frame in the sequence. 
* DiesAway - Like BurnsAway, but it applies to normal DeathFrames instead. 
* DeathHeight - How tall the actor is after a normal death. 
* SolidOnDeath - Include this, and the actor will stick block you after it dies. Useful with DeathHeight. 
* BurnHeight - How tall the actor is after a burning death. 
* SolidOnBurn - Include this, and the actor will still block you after it burns to death. Useful with BurnHeight. 
* DeathSound - Sound the actor makes during a normal death. 
* BurnDeathSound - Sound the actor makes during a burning death. 
* Health - The actor's initial health. 

An example follows (for use in Hexen.wad): 

    breakable FooTree
    {
        Sprite TRDT
        Frames A
        DeathFrames "BCDEFG"
        GenericIceDeath
        BurnDeathFrames "H*I*J*K*L*M*N*OPQ"
        BurnDeathSound TreeExplode
        BurnHeight 20
        SolidOnBurn
        SolidOnDeath
        DeathHeight 20
        DeathSound BishopDeath
        Solid
        Radius 15
        Height 180
        Health 70
        Mass 700000
        NoBlood
        BurnsAway
    }

[[category:Old Decorate format]]</text>
    <sha1>6rvgn2seutn8yycxbfwfcihio0xfbxi</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>