<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>GetZAt</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>8885</id>
  <revision>
    <id>52794</id>
    <parentid>50161</parentid>
    <timestamp>2024-06-30T12:32:35Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Jekyll Grim Payne</username>
      <id>2175</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>Formatting</comment>
    <origin>52794</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="5102" sha1="pacf7d54vzost3ciynozbu2jgxdahoc" xml:space="preserve">'''{{class|Actor}}'''

native double '''GetZAt''(double ''px'' = 0, double ''py'' = 0, double ''angle'' = 0, int ''flags'' = 0, int ''pick_pointer'' = AAPTR_DEFAULT)

== Usage ==
Gets the Z of the floor or ceiling at coordinates ''x'' and ''y'' based on flags. This allows for more flexible checks than the floorz and ceilingz [[Actor properties]].

This function is capable of succeeding where [[A_CheckFloor]] and A_CheckCeiling have their shortcomings -- over ledges and at the edges of a hitbox. With a proper loop, an actor can detect if any part of the pointed actor is truly on the ground or touching the ceiling in its entirety or not.

Note that this function is to be used where an [[DECORATE expressions|expression]] is expected. It is mostly useful when combined with {{c|[[A_JumpIf]]}} or [[Actor_states#Anonymous_Functions|Anonymous Functions]].

== Parameters ==
* {{c|double '''px'''}}
:The x coordinates based on relativity to the pointer. Positive numbers move the check forward, negative moves it behind.
* {{c|double '''py'''}}
:Similar to X but for side-to-side. Positive numbers move the check to the right of the actor, negative moves it to the left.
* {{c|double '''angle'''}}
:The offset amount added to the actor's current angle. Positive amounts rotate the check to the left, negative to the right.
* {{c|int '''flags'''}}
:Multiple flags can be combined with &lt;code&gt;|&lt;/code&gt;. The following flags are available:
:* '''GZF_ABSOLUTEPOS''': Relativity is disabled and the x/y coordinates are absolute.
:* '''GZF_ABSOLUTEANG''': ''angle'' is not added to the actor's current angle.
:* '''GZF_CEILING''': The function checks for the ceiling's z instead of the floor's.
:* '''GZF_3DRESTRICT''': Ignores Z on top of midtextures and 3D floors that are above the pointer's position.
:* '''GZF_NOPORTALS''': Ignores the existence of portals and does not traverse into other sectors.
:* '''GZF_NO3DFLOOR''': Ignores all 3D floors above or below the pointer between it and the true floor/ceiling.
* {{c|int '''pick_pointer'''}}
:The pointer to examine. Default is {{c|{{const|AAPTR_DEFAULT}}}}. See [[actor pointers]].

=== Return value ===
double — Returns the floorz or ceilingz based on the flags above as a double.

==Examples==

This custom version of [[Classes:Blood|Blood]] enters a Death state upon hitting the floor and then leaves a pool on the floor (which is a flat sprite). However, in order to make sure that the flat sprite doesn't stick out into the air when it falls near a ledge or on a narrow stair, four GetZAt checks are introduced. Unless the floor height of four points 24 units away in 4 directions from the center of the BetterBlood actor is equal to the floor height under the actor's center, the pool doesn't appear.

===[[ZScript]] code===
In this example the sprites SPLTA-SPLTD are meant to be represent a pool of blood (viewed from above).
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="csharp"&gt;
class BetterBlood : Blood replaces Blood
{
	Default
	{
		-ALLOWPARTICLES
		+MISSILE
	}

	States
	{
	Spawn:
		BLUD CBA 8;
		wait;
	Death:
		TNT1 A 0 
		{
			// if any if these checks fail, destroy the actor by moving
			// to the "Null" state sequence:
			if (GetZAt(24,0) != floorz || GetZAt(-24,0) != floorz || GetZAt(0,24) != floorz || GetZAt(0,-24) != floorz)
			{
				return FindState("Null");
			}
			// otherwise make it a flat sprite and continue:
			bFLATSPRITE = true;
			return State(null);
		}
		SPLT A -1
		{
			// set the sprite frame randomly to A, B, C or D:
			frame = random(0,3);
		}
		stop;
	}
}&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

Another option in ZScript is to use a for loop and utilize the angle argument of {{c|GetZAt()}} to rotate the check. This will run the check every 30 degrees:
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="csharp"&gt;
class BetterBlood : Blood replaces Blood
{
	Default
	{
		-ALLOWPARTICLES
		+MISSILE
	}

	States
	{
	Spawn:
		BLUD CBA 8;
		wait;
	Death:
		TNT1 A 0 
		{
			// Check 24 units away from the actor, rotating 
			// the check by 30 degrees with every iteration:
			for (int i = 0; i &lt; 360; i += 30)
			{
				// As soon as this check fails destroy the 
				// actor by moving to the "Null" sequence:
				if (GetZAt(24, 0, i) != floorz)
				{
					return FindState("Null");
				}
			}
			// otherwise make it a flat sprite and continue:
			bFLATSPRITE = true;
			return State(null);
		}
		SPLT A -1
		{
			// set the sprite frame randomly to A, B, C or D:
			frame = random(0,3);
		}
		stop;
	}
}&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

===[[DECORATE]] code===
 Actor BetterBlood : Blood replaces Blood
 {
 	{{flag|-ALLOWPARTICLES}}
 	{{flag|+MISSILE}}
 
 	[[Actor states|States]]
 	{
 	Spawn:
 		BLUD CBA 8
 		wait
 	Death:
 		// go to the "Pool" state sequence only if all of these checks pass:
 		TNT1 A 0 [[A_JumpIf]](GetZAt(24,0) == floorz &amp;&amp; GetZAt(-24,0) == floorz &amp;&amp; GetZAt(0,24) == floorz &amp;&amp; GetZAt(0,-24) == floorz, "Pool")
 		stop
 	Pool:
 		// make it a flat sprite and set one of the frames randomly:
 		TNT1 A 0 [[A_ChangeFlag]]("FLATSPRITE",1)
 		TNT1 A 0 [[A_Jump]](256,1,2,3,4)
 		SPLT A -1
 		stop
 		SPLT B -1
 		stop
 		SPLT C -1
 		stop
 		SPLT D -1	
 		stop
 	}
 }</text>
    <sha1>pacf7d54vzost3ciynozbu2jgxdahoc</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>