<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>A OverlayOffset</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>8896</id>
  <revision>
    <id>47854</id>
    <parentid>47853</parentid>
    <timestamp>2020-09-18T22:43:53Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Quaker540</username>
      <id>2135</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>Made the page a bit more like A_WeaponOffset</comment>
    <origin>47854</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2126" sha1="gqwwrm55gbydvglkvrfxkh33sjg7rm1" xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE: A_OverlayOffset}}
'''A_OverlayOffset''' [(int ''layer''[, float ''x''[, float ''y''[, int ''flags'']]]])]

== Usage ==
Works just like [[A_WeaponOffset]] with the ability to adjust other layers, and can be called by weapons, players and inventory items. Offsets a weapon by the defined amount of ''x'' and ''y'' similar to the ''[[Offset]]'' frame keyword. This function has the following differences from the aforementioned ''Offset'' ability:

*Offsets are '''floats''', not integers.
*Offsets are not lost when firing a weapon.
*Offsets stack on top of weapon bobbing and behave independently, allowing [[A_WeaponReady]] calls to it with the WRF_NOBOB flag.
*Specifying the default coordinates does not serve as a preservative. They are absolute.
*Offsets can go beyond screen limitations.
*Because this is an action function itself, [[DECORATE_expressions|Decorate expressions]] can be used.

'''NOTE:''' If an overlay has ''PSPF_ADDWEAPON'', it will inherit the weapon's offsets, which default to (0,32) if none is specified. This should be kept in mind when offsetting the overlay. Simply set the X and Y offsets to 0 to have the overlay follow the weapon's position. This does not apply to [[A_WeaponOffset]] as that strictly targets the weapon layer itself, never overlays.
== Parameters ==
*''layer'' - The layer to adjust.
*''x'' - Adjusts horizontal position based on positive (right) or negative (left) numbers. Default is 0.
*''y'' - Adjusts vertical position. Default is 32. Larger values lower the weapon, and vice versa.
*''flags'' - Flags can be combined with the | separator.
:*'''WOF_KEEPX''' - ''x'' parameter will not be used.
:*'''WOF_KEEPY''' - ''y'' parameter will not be used.
:*'''WOF_ADD''' - Adds the current x and y parameters to the current offsets instead of overriding them. Also implies interpolation (see below).
:*'''WOF_INTERPOLATE''' - Interpolates the offset between tics, smoothing out the animation.

== Examples ==
{{noexamples}}

== See Also ==
*[[A_Overlay]]
*[[A_OverlayFlags]]
*[[A_WeaponOffset]]

{{DEFAULTSORT:OverlayOffset}}[[category:Decorate Weapon functions]]</text>
    <sha1>gqwwrm55gbydvglkvrfxkh33sjg7rm1</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>