<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>ZScript named arguments</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>8980</id>
  <revision>
    <id>53873</id>
    <parentid>53451</parentid>
    <timestamp>2024-11-25T09:03:02Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Jekyll Grim Payne</username>
      <id>2175</id>
    </contributor>
    <origin>53873</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1853" sha1="r8nuif3s51lmwlfwnf2ja6vdrjkwj3q" xml:space="preserve">{{ZScriptNote}}

[[ZScript]] supports the ability to add in named arguments. This is useful for leaving other arguments blank in functions and also clearly defining, what argument is for what.

{{new|4.13.0}} In addition, with named arguments, the order of the arguments can be changed as desired, as long as all required arguments are provided.

In order to use a named argument, provide its name in the function, followed by &lt;code&gt;:&lt;/code&gt; and the value for the argument.

== 4.13.0 onward ==
As of GZDoom 4.13.0, named arguments provide extra features:
* Required parameters cannot be skipped, but you can provide their names
* Using named arguments allows passing arguments to functions in any order

For these new features to work, ZScript version must be set to 4.13.0 or later.

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="csharp"&gt;
version "4.13.0" // as usual, this only needs to be defined once in the root zscript file

// elsewhere in the code:

// Skips xofs, yofs, yvel, and angle parameters. Arguments are
// provided in arbitrary order, with flags being defined
// before offsets and velocity:
A_SpawnItemEx(missile: 'Rocket', flags: SXF_NOCHECKPOSITION|SXF_TRANSFERPITCH|SXF_SETTARGET, zofs: 32, xvel: cos(pitch) * 20, zvel: -sin(pitch) * 20);
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

== Pre-4.13.0 ==
In earlier versions of ZScript certain restrictions are present:
* Required parameters cannot be skipped, and their names cannot be used.
* All arguments must be provided in the same order as they're defined in the function

&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="csharp"&gt;
// Skips xofs, yofs, yvel, and angle parameters. These are also in chronological order:
A_SpawnItemEx('Rocket', zofs: 32, xvel: cos(pitch) * 20, zvel: -sin(pitch) * 20, flags: SXF_NOCHECKPOSITION|SXF_TRANSFERPITCH|SXF_SETTARGET);
&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

[[Category:ZScript]][[Category:Editing concepts]][[Category:Features]]</text>
    <sha1>r8nuif3s51lmwlfwnf2ja6vdrjkwj3q</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>