<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>GAMEMODE</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>8995</id>
  <revision>
    <id>43676</id>
    <timestamp>2017-01-08T21:41:01Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Tiger</username>
      <id>2074</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>Imported article from the Zandronum wiki; this feature allows game mode alterations - but is not so commonly utilized.  Do note that I unlinked the game modes, unsure if the page should be mirrored.</comment>
    <origin>43676</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1754" sha1="1wfc2inzybixfkbubzmhobks3ph59um" xml:space="preserve">{{STFeature}}
This special lump allows the current SkullTag game modes to be reconfigured.  Such game modes can be Deathmatch, Duel, SkullTag, Capture the Flag, Possession, etc....
The hard coded game modes internally use a bunch of flags to configure certain stuff and to share code. The GAMEMODE lump allows you to alter the flags a game mode uses so that you can combine game mode traits. The syntax for the lump is as follows:

&lt;pre&gt;
GAMEMODENAME {
    removeflag FLAGNAME1
    addflag FLAGNAME2
}
&lt;/pre&gt;

=Flags=
*''COOPERATIVE''
Cooperative is a flag that distinguishes the coop modes (Cooperative, Survival, Invasion) from others game modes.
*''DEATHMATCH''
Players are spawned at deathmatch starts (needs Zandronum 3.0 to work properly).
*''TEAMGAME''
Players are spawned at team starts (needs Zandronum 3.0 to work properly).
*''USEFLAGASTEAMITEM''
*''PLAYERSEARNKILLS''
Display the players kills (monsters) on the scoreboard
*''PLAYERSEARNFRAGS''
Display the players frags on the scoreboard
*''PLAYERSEARNPOINTS''
Display the players points (score in ctf)
*''PLAYERSEARNWINS''
Display the players wins on the scoreboard (used in lms)
*''DONTSPAWNMAPTHINGS''
Items and weapons aren't spawned (monsters are still spawned)
*''MAPRESETS''
*''DEADSPECTATORS''
*''PLAYERSONTEAMS''
Display the team selection menu when pressing the spacebar (joining)
*''USEMAXLIVES''
*''USETEAMITEM''
*''MAPRESET_RESETS_MAPTIME''

=Gamemode names=
*Cooperative
*Survival
*Invasion
*Deathmatch
*Teamplay
*Duel
*Terminator
*LastManStanding
*TeamLMS
*Possession
*TeamPossession
*TeamGame
*CTF
*OneFlagCTF
*Skulltag
*Domination

=Example=
For instance, if you would like to have teams in coop, the lump needs to be:
&lt;pre&gt;
cooperative {
    addflag PLAYERSONTEAMS
}
&lt;/pre&gt;</text>
    <sha1>1wfc2inzybixfkbubzmhobks3ph59um</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>