<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>GetTeamProperty</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>9001</id>
  <revision>
    <id>43687</id>
    <timestamp>2017-01-08T22:41:56Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Tiger</username>
      <id>2074</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>Imported article from the zandronum wiki.</comment>
    <origin>43687</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2140" sha1="g0pfpn63wjxtm76x67pzqrqzs8946wu" xml:space="preserve">{{STFeature}}
int '''GetTeamProperty''' (int ''team'', int ''prop'')

==Usage==

Returns the requested information on the specified team.

==Properties==

&lt;div style="border: 1px dotted; white-space: pre-wrap;"&gt;
;TPROP_NumLivePlayers
:Returns number of live players remaining on this team.
;TPROP_IsValid
:Whether the team is valid and can be joined to.
;TPROP_Score
:Returns the effective score of this team. This is frags in team deathmatch, wins in TLMS, flags in CTF, etc.
;TPROP_TextColor
:Text color for the team. This returns a "color range" identifier, which can be used in the ''color'' field in HudMessage.
;TPROP_PlayerStartNum
:Returns the id of what the team spawns on.
;TPROP_Spread
:Returns the spread of points between teams.
;TPROP_Assister
:The player who returned the team's item. If a score occurrs, this person will get an Assist medal. -1 if nobody is eligible for an assist.
;TPROP_Carrier
:The enemy player carrying this team's item. -1 if team item is not stolen.
;TPROP_FragCount
:Returns total frags of this team.
;TPROP_DeathCount
:Returns total deaths of this team.
;TPROP_WinCount
:Returns total wins.of this team. (TLMS)
;TPROP_PointCount
:Returns total point count of this team. (CTF, Skulltag, Possession, Teamgame)
;TPROP_ReturnTics
:How many tics until the dropped team item will be automatically returned to its pedestal. 0 if the team item is not dropped in the first place.
;TPROP_NumPlayers
:Returns number of players on a team.
;TPROP_TeamItem
:Dynamic string containing the class name of the team item, such as BlueFlag.
;TPROP_WinnerTheme
:Dynamic string containing the music played for members of this team if this team won.
;TPROP_LoserTheme
:Dynamic string containing the music played for members of this team if this team lost.
;TPROP_Name
:Dynamic string containing the name of team.&lt;/div&gt;
Note: TPROP_ReturnTics and TPROP_Assister do not work in client-side scripts yet. 8/28/2012

TPROP_Name, TPROP_TeamItem, TPROP_WinnerTheme, TPROP_LoserTheme are dynamic strings akin to those returned by [http://zdoom.org/wiki/strparam StrParam]. After one tick, they expire.

==Examples==
{{noexamples}}</text>
    <sha1>g0pfpn63wjxtm76x67pzqrqzs8946wu</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>