<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>LibADLMIDI</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>9287</id>
  <revision>
    <id>47884</id>
    <parentid>47882</parentid>
    <timestamp>2020-10-06T20:58:02Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Wohlstand</username>
      <id>2594</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>/* OPL cores */ Clarify license for the Opal emulator, it's in Public Domain</comment>
    <origin>47884</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="3869" sha1="meal26d5c44im7gnxj279elpi46exzp" xml:space="preserve">'''libADLMIDI''' - is a software MIDI synthesizer based on {{wp|Yamaha YMF262|OPL3}} chips emulation. It is the one of [[software synthesizer]]s offered by ZDoom which does not use [[sound fonts]]. It's similar to [[OPL synth emulation]] synthesizer, however, it has a different base and workflow algorithm. It doesn't support using of OP2 lumps from WAD files as [[OPL synth emulation]] does. It has the own set of embedded GM banks are taken from various games and musical software or was built by various people. Together with embedded banks, it has a support of custom banks in WOPL format which gives ability to build a complete GS or XG compatible bank that has more than 128 melodic and 80 percussion instruments. In GZDoom, OPL-specific options can be edited from the [[advanced sound options]] menu.

== Features ==
* OPL3 emulation with four-operator mode support
* FM patches from a number of known PC games, copied from files typical to AIL = Miles Sound System / DMX / HMI = Human Machine Interfaces / Creative IBK.
* Pitch-bender with adjustable range
* Vibrato that responds to RPN/NRPN parameters
* Sustain (a.k.a. Pedal hold) and Sostenuto enable/disable
* Use automatic arpeggio with chords to relieve channel pressure
* Support for multiple concurrent MIDI synthesizers (per-track device/port select FF 09 message), can be used to overcome 16 channel limit
* Support for custom banks of [https://github.com/Wohlstand/OPL3BankEditor/blob/master/Specifications/WOPL-and-OPLI-Specification.txt WOPL format]
* Partial support for GS and XG standards (having more instruments than in one 128:128 GM set and ability to use multiple channels for percussion purposes, and a support for some GS/XG exclusive controllers)
* CC74 "Brightness" affects a modulator scale (to simulate frequency cut-off on WT synths)
* Portamento support (CC5, CC37, and CC65)
* SysEx support that supports some generic, GS, and XG features
* Full-panning stereo option 

== OPL cores ==
The OPL core emulates a number of OPL chips. ZDoom extends them with features that did not exist on the emulated hardware, notably full [[MIDI]] stereo panning (OPL2 is normally mono, and OPL3 limited to 3 panning positions), though such enhancements can be turned off from the [[advanced sound options]] menu. There are three different cores available:

;DOSBox OPL3:
:This OPL3 core comes from the {{wp|DOSBox}} project. This is the only emulator affected by the "Run at PCM rate" feature which allows running the emulation with fewer cycles to reduce CPU usage on slow machines.

;Nuked OPL3:
:This OPL3 core was contributed by Alexey Khokholov.

;Nuked OPL3 v1.7:
:The older version of Nuked OPL3, but slightly optimized and works a bit faster than Nuked OPL3 1.8.

;Opal OPL3:
:This OPL3 core comes from the [https://www.3eality.com/productions/reality-adlib-tracker Reality AdLib Tracker] project. It's an incomplete OPL3-only emulator that lacks some features like OPL2 and rhythm mode. It is in the Public Domain.

;Java OPL3:
:This OPL3 core is a {{wp|C++}} port of "[http://opl3.cozendey.com/ That Vintage Tone]", Robson Cozendey's OPL emulator written in {{wp|Java (programming language)|Java}}.

== See also ==
* [[OPL synth emulation]]
* [[libOPNMIDI]]
* [[Sound options]]

== External links ==
* [https://github.com/Wohlstand/OPL3BankEditor OPL3 Bank Editor] - a utility that allows the creation of custom WOPL banks are can be used with this synthesizer.
* [https://github.com/Wohlstand/libADLMIDI libADLMIDI] - GitHub page that contains latest source code of this synthesizer and related documentation.
* [https://github.com/Wohlstand/OPL3BankEditor/blob/master/Specifications/WOPL-and-OPLI-Specification.txt WOPL format specification] - A complete specification of WOPL bank format used by this synthesizer.
* [http://www.dosbox.com/ DOSBox project]
[[Category:Audio systems]]</text>
    <sha1>meal26d5c44im7gnxj279elpi46exzp</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>