<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>DEHEXTRA</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>9439</id>
  <revision>
    <id>47791</id>
    <parentid>47790</parentid>
    <timestamp>2020-08-09T15:25:11Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Gez</username>
      <id>1283</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>/* Features */ these "numbers" don't seem to correspond to anything, technically speaking, so I found them more confusing than anything else.</comment>
    <origin>47791</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2053" sha1="5ilpfz358sqmiawux9737oech5qi79z" xml:space="preserve">{{doomwiki}}
{{Gzdoomfeature}}
The '''DEHEXTRA''' standard, also known as ''DeHackEd Extended'' or ''DeHackEd Extra'', is a extension standard for [[DeHackEd]] patches first introduced in the Doom Retro source port. It provides a significant increase in the number of [[thing]]s and [[sprite]]s that can be utilized, in addition to the inclusion of 2,910 new states or codepointers. These can be utilized for new map object types, new non-replacing [[monster]]s and decorations, or to add additional frames to existing things for smoother animations. The additional objects are called {{c|MT_EXTRA}} in Doom Retro.

GZDoom provides support for the standard. The WhackEd editor provides support for DEHEXTRA features through the Doom Retro configuration parameter.

==Features==
* 2,910 additional states/codepointers (numbered 1,089 to 3,999)
* 100 additional things (numbered 150 to 249)
* 100 additional sprites (numbered 145 to 244)

The following additional entries are supported in {{c|THING}} blocks:
{| {{prettytable}}
! Entry || Description
|-
| Gib health || -
|-
| Dropped item || -
|-
| Pickup width || -
|-
| Project pass height || -
|-
| Fullbright || -
|}

==Examples==
DEHEXTRA has been utilized in the following mods:
* Black Ops: Smooth animated weapons using the new additional states for improved animation, with Doomguy wearing black gloves.
* SMOOTHED: Smooth animated beastiary utilizing code from the Smooth Doom project. 

Both mods can be used together to provide a more streamlined Doom experience in terms of animation.

==Trivia==
* Unlike [[DECORATE]] or [[ZScript]], DEHEXTRA is not to be considered a [[lump]], as it should be thought of as more of an ''extension'' to DeHackEd.

==External links==
* [https://github.com/bradharding/doomretro/wiki/INFORMATION-FOR-MAPPERS DEHEXTRA info page], on Doom Retro Wiki
* [https://www.doomworld.com/forum/topic/115638-dehextra-discussion-split-from-pr-umapinfo-thread/ DEHEXTRA thread], at DoomWorld
[[category:Editing concepts]]
[[Category:GZDoom features]]
[[Category:Glossary]]</text>
    <sha1>5ilpfz358sqmiawux9737oech5qi79z</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>