<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>A StartSoundIfNotSame</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>9570</id>
  <revision>
    <id>53846</id>
    <parentid>53845</parentid>
    <timestamp>2024-11-23T14:35:16Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Jekyll Grim Payne</username>
      <id>2175</id>
    </contributor>
    <origin>53846</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2774" sha1="kwnzqgvcnocawl27smphi8oh7jq0209" xml:space="preserve">__NOTOC__{{codepointer|Sound}}

'''{{class|Actor}}'''

{{c|native clearscope void '''A_StartSoundIfNotSame'''(sound ''whattoplay'', sound ''checkagainst', int slot {{=}} ''CHAN_BODY'', int ''flags'' {{=}} 0, double ''volume'' {{=}} 1.0, double ''attenuation'' {{=}} ATTN_NORM, double ''pitch'' {{=}} 0.0, double ''startTime'' {{=}} 0.0)}}

== Usage ==
Plays the specified sound only if it is different from the one to check against.

The two sounds are considered different if they have different names. For [[SNDINFO#alias|aliases]], the function checks the name of the sound which is referenced by the alias in order to make a decision. A [[SNDINFO#random|random sound]]'s assigned set of sounds is of no consequence, as the function only checks the sound's name.

=== Parameters ===
*{{c|Sound '''whattoplay'''}}
:The desired sound to play, as defined in [[SNDINFO]].
*{{c|Sound '''checkagainst'''}}
:The sound to compare to, as defined in [[SNDINFO]]. If this sound is playing, ''whattoplay'' sound will not be played.
*{{c|int '''slot'''}}
:The sound slot used for the sound. Unlike {{c|[[A_PlaySound]]}}, the slot is not limited to predefined slots and can be any positive number other than 0 (which enables special behavior). The predefined slots are:
{{:StartSound channels}}
*{{c|int '''flags'''}}
{{: StartSound flags}}
*double '''volume'''
:The volume of the sound, which ranges from 0 to 1.0. Default 1.0.
*{{c|double '''attenuation'''}}
:This is a positive value that specifies how quickly the sound fades with distance from its source. The exact formula for attenuation is: '''attenuation = default max hearable distance / desired max hearable distance'''. So, for example, in Doom the default max hearable distance is 1200; with attenuation of 20 the max hearable distance for the sound will be 60 map units (1200 / 20 = 60). This argument also accepts the following predefined constants: 
:*'''ATTN_NONE''' — Plays the sound globally at the specified volume, disregarding distance. 
:*'''ATTN_NORM''' — Uses the {{c|close_dist}} and {{c|clipping_dist}} fields defined in the sound definition. Default.
:*'''ATTN_IDLE''' — Uses Doom's normal default sound attenuation behavior. 
:*'''ATTN_STATIC''' — Fades quickly (inaudible from 512 units).
*{{c|double '''pitch'''}}
:The sound pitch to play the sound with. Default is 0, which means the engine uses whatever pitch shift (range) that is defined in SNDINFO, if any. For non-zero values anything lower than 1.0 will slow down the sound, while higher values speed it up.
*{{c|double '''startTime'''}}
:Sets how much of the sound to skip when starting. The value can be anywhere between 0 and 1.0, translating to 0% to 100%. Default is 0.

== Examples ==
{{noexamples}}

== See also ==
*[[A_StartSound]]</text>
    <sha1>kwnzqgvcnocawl27smphi8oh7jq0209</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>