<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Classes:DynamicValueInterpolator</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>9667</id>
  <revision>
    <id>53077</id>
    <parentid>53076</parentid>
    <timestamp>2024-09-12T23:01:28Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Jekyll Grim Payne</username>
      <id>2175</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <origin>53077</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2430" sha1="l56vjqrg1y4nq5j2nelqqqzm97q6g21" xml:space="preserve">{{ZScriptNote}}

'''DynamicValueInterpolator''' is a data-scoped class that allows for gradual change of a value, which can be used for something like a health indicator lerping over a few tics instead of changing its value instantly, or a similar effect with a graphical element. It can be used in any scope.

'''DynamicValueInterpolator''' is very similar to '''{{class|LinearValueInterpolator}}'''; the only difference is that it applies easing-in/easing-out effect to interpolation by performing differently-sized steps, whereas '''LinearValueInterpolator''', as implied by its name, interpolates linearly.

Note, both interpolators update every [[tic]] regardless of the scope they were created from, so in UI scope this method will not be particularly smooth, since it'll still be tied to the default 35-tic framerate.

== Fields ==
*int '''mCurrentValue''' - The current value contained in the interpolator
*int '''mMinChange''' - The minimum change from from the original value to the target value per interpolator's update
*int '''mMaxChange''' - The maximum value from from the original value to the target value per interpolator's update
*double '''mChangeFactor''' - The change factor

== Methods ==
=== Static ===
{{c|static '''DynamicValueInterpolator''' Create(int ''startval'', double ''changefactor'', int ''minchange'', int ''maxchange'')}}

This function instantiates a new interpolator. It should be cast to a local field in the HUD (or other UI) class in order to interact with it.

Arguments:
*int '''startval''' - The original value
*double '''changefactor''' - The fraction of the amount between the current value and the target value the interpolator should cover per one {{c|Update()}} call
*int '''minchange''' - The minimum change from from the original value to the target value per interpolator's update
*int '''maxchange''' - The maximum value from from the original value to the target value per interpolator's update

=== Dynamic ===
* {{c|void '''Update'''(int ''destvalue'')}}
:Updates the interpolator, setting a new target value for it to move towards from the current value. The new target value is defined by the '''{{c|destvalue}}''' argument.

* {{c|int '''GetValue'''()}}
:Returns the current value in the interpolator (contained in the {{c|mCurrentValue}} field).

* {{c|void '''Reset'''(int ''value'')}}
:Sets the interpolator's current value to '''{{c|value}}'''.

[[Category:ZScript]]</text>
    <sha1>l56vjqrg1y4nq5j2nelqqqzm97q6g21</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>