<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>PostBeginPlay</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>9736</id>
  <revision>
    <id>51955</id>
    <parentid>51006</parentid>
    <timestamp>2024-03-13T12:31:43Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Jekyll Grim Payne</username>
      <id>2175</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>/* Usage */</comment>
    <origin>51955</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1769" sha1="q9q8zzkxjg75rj0eqoow0iub1whuy6o" xml:space="preserve">__NOTOC__

'''[[Thinker]]'''

{{c|virtual void '''PostBeginPlay'''()}}

==Usage==

A virtual function used by the [[Thinker]] class (which includes actors). It's called right after [[BeginPlay]] and before the first [[Tick]] call. For actors, it happens after the actor has already spawned, but before they actually enter their Spawn state.

This function can be overridden to perform one-time setups, like giving local variables a value, setting flags and such, before any of that data gets overridden or referenced in the states.

'''WARNING:''' Due to the way GZDoom handles calling a state's function (a state change immediately calls the function attached to the new state), there is no guarantee that '''PostBeginPlay''' runs before any state, especially in weapons/inventory items. Timing-critical operations should not rely on this assumption, and would be better deferred for a few tics into the weapon/inventory's existence.

{{warning|On [[PlayerPawn]] actors, weird quirks can occur if [[Voodoo doll|voodoo dolls]] are present and '''PostBeginPlay''' is overridden without proper handling, because both the original PlayerPawn and its voodoo doll will execute the override at the same time. See the [[Voodoo doll]] page for information on how to check if a PlayerPawn is a voodoo doll or not.}}

==Examples==
This version of the [[Classes:Zombieman|Zombieman]] defines an integer field &lt;code&gt;foo&lt;/code&gt; which is set to 15 as soon as this actor spawns:
&lt;syntaxhighlight lang="csharp"&gt;
class MyZombieman : Zombieman
{
	int foo;

	override void PostBeginPlay()
	{
		Super.PostBeginPlay();
		foo = 15;
	}
}&lt;/syntaxhighlight&gt;

[[Category:ZScript]]
[[Category:ZScript virtual functions]]
[[Category:Actor virtual functions]]
[[Category:Thinker virtual functions]]</text>
    <sha1>q9q8zzkxjg75rj0eqoow0iub1whuy6o</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>