<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Structs:KeyBindings</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>9751</id>
  <revision>
    <id>53060</id>
    <parentid>51173</parentid>
    <timestamp>2024-09-05T20:07:09Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Jekyll Grim Payne</username>
      <id>2175</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>/* Dynamic */</comment>
    <origin>53060</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2318" sha1="hfp5onmrvabw8qk0jewheqwp6i5k7w8" xml:space="preserve">{{ZScriptNote}}

This struct contains functionality related to key bindings.

== Methods ==

All methods are defined as &lt;code&gt;native&lt;/code&gt;, meaning their inner workings are handled in C++.
=== Static ===
The keys recognized by these methods are integer values either from the [https://github.com/ZDoom/gzdoom/blob/fb6e4becaadea0a6d64d711c6757e471ad22d62c/wadsrc/static/zscript/engine/inputevents.zs#L85 InputEvent] struct, or obtained with &lt;code&gt;GetKeysForCommand&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;GetAllKeysForCommand&lt;/code&gt;.
*{{c|static String '''NameKeys'''(int k1, int k2)}}
:Returns the names of the two provided keys. This function is essentially deprecated, being superseded by the more efficient &lt;code&gt;NameAllKeys()&lt;/code&gt;.
*{{c|static String '''NameAllKeys'''(array&lt;int&gt; list, bool colors }}={{c| true)}}
:Returns the names of all keys contained in the provided array. The string is colorized by default, but that can be circumvented by passing &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt; to the &lt;code&gt;colors&lt;/code&gt; argument (so that the string can be later colorized with the appropriate string-drawing function arguments or [[Text colors|color codes]]).

=== Dynamic ===
Dynamic KeyBindings methods can be called in [[ZScript]] on the global &lt;code&gt;Bindings&lt;/code&gt; pointer.

The command arguments are what you would type in the console to trigger that action.

*{{c|int, int '''GetKeysForCommand'''(String cmd)}}
:Returns the first two keys for the provided command. This function is essentially deprecated, being superseded by the more robust &lt;code&gt;GetAllKeysForCommand&lt;/code&gt;.
*{{c|void '''GetAllKeysForCommand'''(out array&lt;int&gt; list, String cmd)}}
:Fills the provided array with keys for the provided command.
*{{c|String '''GetBinding'''(int key)}}
:Returns the command bound to the provided key as a string. If used within an {{class|EventHandler}} '''InputProcess()''' override, &lt;code&gt;e.KeyScan&lt;/code&gt; can be passed here, and the function will return the name of the console command tied to that key.
*{{c|void '''SetBind'''(int key, String cmd)}}
:Binds the specified command to the specified key. &lt;u&gt;Can only be called in a UI event from a Menu class.&lt;/u&gt;
*{{c|void '''UnbindACommand'''(String str)}}
:Unbinds the specified command from a key. &lt;u&gt;Can only be called in a UI event from a Menu class.&lt;/u&gt;

[[Category:ZScript]]
[[Category:Structs]]</text>
    <sha1>hfp5onmrvabw8qk0jewheqwp6i5k7w8</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>