<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>StartSound flags</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>9894</id>
  <revision>
    <id>53673</id>
    <parentid>53671</parentid>
    <timestamp>2024-11-12T00:42:01Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Jekyll Grim Payne</username>
      <id>2175</id>
    </contributor>
    <origin>53673</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1861" sha1="0ovotr87qvb0ef4srtkpxy1hqw9xpcf" xml:space="preserve">&lt;noinclude&gt;
{{note|This page is meant to be included into other pages that describe sound functions, such as [[A_StartSound]], using the '''&lt;nowiki&gt;{{: StartSound flags}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;''' syntax. (This note will not be included.)}}
&lt;/noinclude&gt;:Adjusts how the sound is played. Multiple flags can be combined with &lt;code&gt;|&lt;/code&gt;:
:*'''CHANF_DEFAULT''' — No flags. Default.
:*'''CHANF_LISTENERZ''' — Play the sound from the listener's Z position instead of the caller's.
:*'''CHANF_MAYBE_LOCAL''' — Sound is subject to {{c|{{CVAR|C|compat_silentpickup}}}} and will not play if started by an actor other than the listener when the compatibility flag is enabled.
:*'''CHANF_UI''' — Sound isn't preserved in saves and will play while the game is paused.
:*'''CHANF_NOPAUSE''' — Don't pause the sound.
:*'''CHANF_LOOP''' — Loops the sound.
:*'''CHANF_OVERLAP''' — Don't stop any sounds in the channel and instead play over them.
:*'''CHANF_LOCAL''' — Only play the sound if the listener is the one doing so.
:*'''CHANF_NOSTOP''' — If the channel is occupied, do not play the sound.
:*'''CHANF_TRANSIENT''' — Sound isn't preserved in saves. '''{{color|red|Note:}}''' As of GZDoom 4.13.1, while the flag is exported to ZScript, the constant for it isn't. Instead, its bit value can be passed directly: &lt;code&gt;32768&lt;/code&gt;.
:*'''CHANF_FORCE''' — Play the sound even if it will be immediately paused upon doing so.&lt;noinclude&gt;
:*'''CHANF_SINGULAR''' — Only play the sound if it isn't already being played by something. ''(This flag is marked with &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;noinclude&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt; in this template, because it's not fully exported. Plus there's [[A_StartSoundIfNotSame]])''&lt;/noinclude&gt;
:*'''CHANF_LOOPING''' — Combines CHANF_LOOP and CHANF_NOSTOP. It is equivalent to the ''looping'' parameter of [[A_PlaySound]].&lt;noinclude&gt;

[[Category:Include templates]]</text>
    <sha1>0ovotr87qvb0ef4srtkpxy1hqw9xpcf</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>