<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>Chase flags</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>9910</id>
  <revision>
    <id>52689</id>
    <timestamp>2024-05-21T09:32:36Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Jekyll Grim Payne</username>
      <id>2175</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>Created page with ":Flags can be combined by using the &lt;code&gt;|&lt;/code&gt; character between the constant names. :*'''CHF_FASTCHASE''' – Actor will randomly attempt to strafe left or right around t..."</comment>
    <origin>52689</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1681" sha1="iycdizctry03i91e6nep3wkwft3a5ge" xml:space="preserve">:Flags can be combined by using the &lt;code&gt;|&lt;/code&gt; character between the constant names.
:*'''CHF_FASTCHASE''' – Actor will randomly attempt to strafe left or right around the target, like the "player bosses" in ''[[Hexen]]''. Note that the calling actor will ignore their {{c|{{property|MaxDropOffHeight}}}} property when strafing, and so may strafe off cliffs or into pits from which they can not escape. Setting the {{flag|NODROPOFF}} flag will prevent this from happening.
:*'''CHF_NOPLAYACTIVE''' – Actor will not play active sounds.
:*'''CHF_NIGHTMAREFAST''' – Actor will move twice as fast in ''Nightmare!'' difficulty setting or equivalent. 
:*'''CHF_RESURRECT''' – Actor will enter the "Heal" [[Actor_states#States|state]] (if defined) upon encountering a revivable corpse, like the {{Class|Archvile|Arch-Vile}}.
:*'''CHF_DONTMOVE''' – Actor will not move.
:*'''CHF_NORANDOMTURN''' – Actor will not change its chasing angle to its target if its beyond a certain degree until something blocks the way (obstacle or wall).
:*'''CHF_NODIRECTIONTURN''' – Actor will not turn its angle to face the direction of travel.
:*'''CHF_NOPOSTATTACKTURN''' – Actor will not turn itself to its target after attacking.
:*'''CHF_STOPIFBLOCKED''' – Actor cannot turn away from obstacles blocking it. It will simply not move, but can still angle itself.
:*'''CHF_DONTIDLE''' – Hostile actors will not jump to their [[Actor_states#States|Spawn or Idle]] state once they no longer have a target. Allowing you to define custom states for them to jump to, when they have no target.
:*'''CHF_DONTTURN''' – Implies CHF_NORANDOMTURN, CHF_NOPOSTATTACKTURN and CHF_STOPIFBLOCKED.</text>
    <sha1>iycdizctry03i91e6nep3wkwft3a5ge</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>