<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>LOF flags</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>9912</id>
  <revision>
    <id>52700</id>
    <timestamp>2024-05-21T19:03:38Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Jekyll Grim Payne</username>
      <id>2175</id>
    </contributor>
    <comment>Created page with ":* '''LOF_NOSIGHTCHECK'''&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; do not process sight checks (makes monster blind). :* '''LOF_NOSOUNDCHECK'''&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; do not process sound target checks (makes mons..."</comment>
    <origin>52700</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="1333" sha1="j5z3muzbj1isryopt0al272g5ddydny" xml:space="preserve">:* '''LOF_NOSIGHTCHECK'''&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; do not process sight checks (makes monster blind).
:* '''LOF_NOSOUNDCHECK'''&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; do not process sound target checks (makes monster deaf).
:: ''Note'': this is '''not''' the same as using '''{{flag|AMBUSH}}''': When the AMBUSH flag is specified for a monster, if the player makes a sound in the same room (and in range of the monster if ''maxheardist'' is set), the monster will react to the player if they walk within the monster's current line of sight, regardless of the direction it is facing (FOV is ignored). This flag will make the monster completely deaf, preventing it from reacting to the player at all, regardless of the sounds they make.
:* '''LOF_DONTCHASEGOAL'''&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; do not leave to chase after a goal from this state, even if the actor has one. This can be used to prevent a monster from breaking from its idle animations to walk over to a goal.
:* '''LOF_NOSEESOUND'''&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; do not play the actor's sight sound if it wakes up from this state.
:* '''LOF_FULLVOLSEESOUND'''&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; Play the see sound globally at full volume (like a boss).
:* '''LOF_NOJUMP'''&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; acquire a target, but do not jump to any other state, allows to check the target and jump manually into the See state based on conditions without interrupting the idle animation.</text>
    <sha1>j5z3muzbj1isryopt0al272g5ddydny</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>