<page xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/">
  <title>SetViewPos</title>
  <ns>0</ns>
  <id>9935</id>
  <revision>
    <id>54142</id>
    <parentid>53304</parentid>
    <timestamp>2025-01-20T04:53:48Z</timestamp>
    <contributor>
      <username>Dileepvr</username>
      <id>2636</id>
    </contributor>
    <minor />
    <comment>FOV was made to affect the view scale in orthographic mode</comment>
    <origin>54142</origin>
    <model>wikitext</model>
    <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    <text bytes="2864" sha1="bz8uzggoywqm4b534v7y20fs23gxaxw" xml:space="preserve">{{ZScriptNote}}

'''[[Classes:Actor|Actor]]'''

native void '''SetViewPos''' (Vector3 ''offset'', int ''flags'' = -1)

== Usage ==
Used to set the {{c|offset}} and {{c|flags}} fields within the {{c|native readonly ViewPosition ViewPos}} field in the {{class|Actor}} class. Typically used to offset the viewpoint of the {{class|PlayerPawn}} or camera actor.

===Parameters===
*{{c|vector3 '''offset'''}}
:The vector for the viewpoint's offset.
*{{c|int '''flags'''}}
:Any combination of the {{c|VPSF}} flags for the {{class|ViewPosition}} class.
:The flags that can be set are:
:*'''VPSF_ABSOLUTEOFFSET''' — Don't include angles.
::Does not take the actor's {{c|angle}} and {{c|pitch}} into account when applying the offset. When this flag is not set, the offset is computed in the actor's local frame where the actor is always facing the positive x-direction. When the flag is set, the global level axes are used.
:*'''VPSF_ABSOLUTEPOS''' — Use absolute position.
::Uses the offset as the absolute position in the global level's coordinates, instead of relative to actor's position.
:*'''VPSF_ALLOWOUTOFBOUNDS''' {{new|4.13.0}} — Allow viewpoint to go out of bounds (hardware renderer only).
::Allows the viewpoint (but not the actor) to be out of bounds of the level. Backface culling will let you see into the level from behind single-sided walls. Rendering of all skies are disabled when this is set for the viewpoint camera/actor. Intra-frustum horizontal clipping is disabled when this flag is set. A vertical clipper has been added to compensate, but expect a drop in framerate at shallow view pitches.
:*'''VPSF_ORTHOGRAPHIC''' {{new|4.13.0}} — Use orthographic projection (hardware renderer only).
::Switches the viewpoint's projection matrix from perspective to orthographic. All geometry is rendered the same size irrespective of distance from viewpoint. [[FOV]] setting (up to 175 degrees) and the length of the {{c|Vector3 '''Offset'''}} field will determine the scale of things, with the latter required to be greater than zero. This is useful for isometric mode cameras (See [[Isometric Mode]] tutorial). Typically set along with {{c|VPSF_ALLOWOUTOFBOUNDS}}. This flag disables visual rendering for all portals, though playsim is unaffected. In addition, depending on the sign of the camera/actor's pitch, either all floors (pitching upward) or all ceilings (pitching downward) are not rendered. Reflections in flats will not work correctly. The renderer does not traverse the [[Node|BSP]] tree but does a simple bounding-box check for all subsectors if either the CVar {{c|{{CVAR|R|r_radarclipper}}}} is false, or the {{c|{{MapProperty|NoFogOfWar}}}} property is set for the map in the [[MAPINFO]] lump, resulting in a slightly increased framerate.

== Example ==
{{noexamples}}

== See also ==
* {{class|ViewPosition}}

[[Category:ZScript]]</text>
    <sha1>bz8uzggoywqm4b534v7y20fs23gxaxw</sha1>
  </revision>
</page>